[MUSIC]
Okay, so that's just a quick overview of
essentially the type
system that you have with AIDL and using
those basic building blocks.
Then we can make all kinds of other
interesting things.
I did a little little experiment, just for
fun I ran a search
through all the Android source code to see
how often they use AIDL interfaces.
And I found hundreds and hundreds of
examples of where it's used in the
frameworks.
It's used a little bit less over in
the apps and providers portion of the
packages directory.
But it's still used there as well.
It's used probably a dozen or so times.
But it's used hundreds of times in the
main part of Android.
Which means you are often accessing stuff
as a, an app
developer, an Android that is using AIDL
in one way or another.
So getting, getting to know how it works
is useful.
All right the next thing I want to talk
about is
how you go about actually implementing
AIDL interfaces using, using eclipse.
And then, kind of talk about sort of
what's going on under the hood.
Now, some of what we're going to talk
about here is not strictly necessary.
You can get a long way in life as an
Android
developer and not know some of things I'm
going to tell you.
But I'm going to show some of it to you
because I think it's interesting to learn
how it works.
And as I mentioned last time it's also
useful because it
helps you appreciate the tedious and error
prone programming you're not doing.
Because it's done for you by having a AIDL
compiler.
All right, first let's talk about how you
use eclipse.
So basically what you do, it's really
easy, if you're not
using eclipse there's a few other steps
you may have to do.
But if you're using eclipse it's really
simple.
You go ahead and create a bunch of AIDL
files.
So here's an example where I've got AIDL
files that are in
my source directory and you can organize
this as you see fit.
One common way to do it is you might put
your
AIDL files in a separate sub folder under
the source folder.
So that you can have AIDL files separate
from the normal Java files.
That's just one thing you can do.
And so, what eclipse would then do is it
will go ahead and automatically compile
every file that finds in the source
directory that isn't a .AILD file.
It sticks those files.
Which are then converted into Java files
in the gen directory.
So source and gen are basically peers.
They're siblings at the same level of the,
the directory hierarchy of the Eclipse.
And the way the packages and projects work
and so on.
And so if you go take a look at.
If you very quickly take a look at the gen
directory after you plop AIDL files into
the source directory.
You will discover that the ADL, AIDL
compiler has
run, and it's created Java files on your
behalf.
And the Java files contain a bunch of
things, and we'll talk about them.
One thing they contain is an actual
interface,
a Java interface, that corresponds to your
interface.
And that's very important for what you're
doing.
Then they also contain a couple of other
things as well.
They also contain a stub, which you're
going to, is
going to be used by the service that
implements this thing.
Or it doesnt always have to be a service,
whoever the
implementor is, of the interface will be
relating to the stub.
And there's also something called a proxy,
and that's what the client will be using.
Now, when you're dealing with just
conventional synchronous
communication between activities and
services or services and services.
Then, in that case, the proxy is typically
used by the activity or the client, and
the.
Stub is used by the service.
But as we'll see when we start doing
asynchronous calls, the
concept of a client and service gets
flipped around a little bit.
And so, you actually may have an activity
that is also implementing a stub.
And that's so it can get call-backs that
come back to it from the service.
Which is invoking one-way methods on
call-back objects that where passed to it.
And we'll talk about that and I'll show
you the examples.
That, that's one reason why I wanted to
skip the
quiz, so I could cover all that stuff in
detail.
Okay.
And if you take a look at the
documentation here,
you'll find out lots more information
about how AIDL works.
Now, there's a lot of different moving
parts here, and it
helps to break them down by a number of
different criteria.
So, let's kind of do this.
Assuming we have an interface, like the
iDownload interface, then we're going to
go ahead and have a couple of different
kinds of entities involved.
And when you take a look at your
implementation when you take look at the
generated code.
You'll see all these things and how they,
they appear.
So I'm just going to give you high level
view first.
So there's some stuff that comes out of
Android, out of the box.
There's this IBinder interface that's
defined as part of Android.
There's a binder class which is defined as
part of Android.
The binder is typically something that's
local.
And the IBinder is an interface that
allows you to be
able to access something whose
implementation may in fact be remote.
Where remote means in a separate process.
So those are the things that Android gives
you out of the box, their always
available.
Then there's certain things that are
generated by the AIDLcompiler.
So the AIDL compiler will generate the
stub class that's nested
inside of this other interface we're going
to talk about later.
And then there's also proxy class which
is nested inside the stub for various
reasons.
And we'll see how those guys get used in a
second.
And then finally what you do as an
implementer of the service.
That wants to define this interface that
wants to provide an implementation to this
interface.
You come along and you inherit from the
generated stub
and you override the methods that were
defined in the interface.
So that you give implementations that are
meaningful
in whatever it is your trying to do.
And it turns out that this particular
hierarchy here the one that goes like
this.
These are all service related kinds of
things and
then the proxy is something that the
client uses.
So the client uses the proxy, the other
service side, the server side.
Which, which might be a service or it may
be a service that's a call back service.
Those things are inheriting from, from the
the binder hierarchy.
And there's a real nice tutorial out there
that talks about all this stuff.
There are a lot of great tutorials, by the
way, on,
on binders and AIDL so if there's anything
you're confused about.
And my conversation, you might want to
take a look and there's
lots more material out there you can take
a look at.
So let's take a little bit of time and
kind of look at
what actually is spit out by the AIDL
compactor, cause it's kind of cool.
So you'll see that what happens is that
there's this
interface that's generated and that
extends this I interface class.
Our interface.
And then there's a static abstract class
called a stub
and as you can see here it extends the
binder.
And it also implements your interface.
So in our case, that was the, the
I download interface which has the
download image method.
So there's a class called stub and it
inherits.
From binder, and it implements the
download, interface.
And, then basically, this is this thing
that's going to
be sort of on the implementation side of
the house.
And then there's a constructor for stub,
that's going to go ahead and register.
An instance of this object with the
underlying binder framework.
So that's how the binder framework knows
that
you've got an object that needs to be
dispatched.
It registers it by using thing called
attach interface.
There's also another method that's very
important.
We see this getting used a couple
different places called.
As interface, and as interface is used by,
typically used by the on service connected
hook method.
That gets called back by the Android
binder framework and the bound service
framework.
When the onbind method returns, and what
that does is it allows you to
take a binder object or an IBinder object
which is what comes back from.
The server side, the service side, and be
able to narrow it, or downcast it down
to the appropriate underlying, interface
that we're trying to define here.
Which in our case would be the IDownload
service.
And you can see it's got a bunch of
gobbledygook
code here where it's trying to check to
see whether.
We need to have a proxy made, or whether
we're the server side, whatnot.
And if we need a proxy, which we're going
to in
this case, it goes ahead and it says, new
IDownload.Stub.Proxy obj.
And that creates a proxy.
I'm going to look at the proxy on the next
page, two, two pages from now.
In fact, lemme, I tell you what, Let's go
take a look at
the proxy real quick and I'll come back
and talk about the other stuff.
So, here's what the proxy looks like.
The proxy is nested inside of the stub.
And basically what the proxy does is, the
proxy's going to stash away the IBinder.
And then it's going to use it shortly.
And it's going to use it when the client
calls the method through the proxy.
The method, in our case, being
downloadImage.
So when the client calls downloadImage on
the proxy.
What happens is you can see here is that
it takes in the string.
Which is the URI and this, this code by
the way is all autogenerated by the ALDI
compiler.
And you can see as you look at it its all
pretty low level and nasty.
And whats it essentially doing is its
creating a pair of
parcels to contain the data that were
going to send over there.
And to get the reply back, it's creating
these two parcels and then it's going
ahead.
And it's going to take the URI that we
pass in and
it's going to write it as a string into
the underscored data parcel.
So that, [INAUDIBLE] basically doing is
it's copying the, the bytes
in our URI that's coming, it's coming from
the client side.
Into this parcel, which keeps track of
it's type and other metadata.
Then it goes ahead and calls this method
called transact.
And we'll cover that in a second.
And what transact does is it says, here's
the operation that I want performed.
I want to do the.
Transaction download image operation.
And here's the data it should work on,
which
in this case is the string containing the
URI.
And here's where I want you to put the
reply.
And we'll see what happens in a second in
that method.
And then when it's done, when this thing
returns, we take the
reply and we copy its result as a string
into underscore result.
And that's what we return as the return
value from that particular method.
So as I, as I say here I simplified this
ever so much.
Just because I wanted to make sure that
you would be able
to follow along with what it's doing
without getting it too complicated.
Here then is the method called in response
to the call to transact.
So as you can see here we call download
image.
That calls mRemote, which is the remote
binder object or a proxy to it.
transact, that ends up calling back in the
stub, the on transact method.
And you can see what on transact does is
it takes a
look at the code, keep in mind the code is
shown over here.
Here's the code that was passed in the
transaction.
Download image.
And it has a bunch of stuff.
I'm just showing the part that's
important.
It says, if this is the transaction on
download image, or
download image case, then go ahead, and
read its data string.
And then, invoke an up call, on the
actual implementation method, that was
defined by the user.
Who subclass this whole thing in the first
place.
We'll look at that in a couple slides.
That's the actual call that does the
actual work.
And so it demarshals the parameter and
passes it to the call back.
And then when it comes back here as a
string and it marshals that up
as a string and then that gets sent back
over to the client as a reply.
Ok, so any questions about that?
So, that's basically the set of things
that the proxy and stub
are doing under the hood to do stuff like
register you.
So here's, I'll highlight this guy.
To go ahead and register, the stub
instances, these, these binder objects
so that they can be dispatched ultimately
by the, by the binder framework.
It has a way of being able to take
an IBinder and turning it back into your
interface.
As part of that process it may have to
create a proxy.
The proxy is an object that has a method,
has the same name
as the receiver, but when it's invoked,
it, it doesn't do the work.
It goes ahead and marshals the parameters,
calls this transact method to pass them
over.
And then when it comes back it takes the
return value and then cracks
it open and returns it back to something
that's expected by the, the caller.
To notice what's going on here, is that
this is Java land and this is sort of
goobledily gook, passing data around,
possible between different languages land.
And so, this is the linearization stage.
So, I think I mentioned before that, what
a.
What a proxy does is it converts a method
call into a message.
And that message is something that
represents the information in the
method call so that it can be passed over
to a receiver.
And that receiver doesn't have to be
written in the same language it
doesn't run in the same address phase and
so on and so forth.
So, it gives you flexibility to
pass information correctly and efficiently
across processes.
The receiver side, the stub side gets
called back as the
objects come up, fall underneath the
binder framework and [UNKNOWN] binder.
And the on transact method is called and
that does this stuff.
And that ends up ultimately calling the
download image method that we
have to implement as the people who want
to define this service.
So let's take a look at that part.
So, now that we've talked about the
generated proxy and the generated stub,
let's
talk a little bit more about what you
actually do to use this stuff.
Everything I've talked about for the past
ten minutes you really
don't have to know in order to use what
I'm talking about.
But if useful as long as you understand
the principles.
And by the way if you use other
technologies like
Korbel or Microsoft com, or other things
like enterprise java beans.
They're doing essentially is the same kind
of thing.
The patterns they use which will be stuff
like the
proxy pattern, the adaptor pattern, the
broker patter and so on.
Those are all the sam patterns, just
different realizations.
In different languages in different
middleware, frameworks in different ways.
Okay, so if you take a close look at the
generated code, by the AIDL compiler.
You'll see that there's an abstract method
called, a set of abstract methods.
One for every method that was defined in
the original AIDL interface.
So if we have download image then there's
going
to be an abstract method called download
image here.
And we have to implement this.
And you either implement it by
sub-classing it
from Stub or creating an anonymous inner
class.
Or sub-classing and then forwarding.
You know, however you want to do it.
When the, somebody has to implement
download image to
do the thing that you actually have to get
done.
So, here's what you do.
You start out by typically creating a
private instance of an, the AIDL-generated
Stub class.
And again there's various ways to do this,
the most common
way you'll typically see people do it is
they'll go ahead and.
Use this format where you make a new
anonymous object, and
you give the implementation here, just
like you guys are doing.
And that gets created somewhere, either in
the OnCreate method
or it gets created at class scope or what
not.
And then you fill in the implementation of
this stuff as you see fit,
either implementing it directly or
delegating it
to someone else to do the work.
And then the final thing you do is you
make sure that, that object.
Is returned as the result from the on bind
method, so that binder,
which implements this interface, is
going to get returned back to the caller.
And, and we'll see later that, you know,
think about how this comes back to you.
This comes back via the on service
connected
call, that'll come back as a, as an
iBinder.
And then you're going to go ahead and say,
hey,
take this thing, and treat it as an
interface.
Which will, narrow it down, using a proxy,
to get
you back a way to talk to the interface
itself.
All right, so let's kind of see, how all
of these pieces, actually work, end to
end.
Because there's a lot of moving parts.
And some of them are pretty easy to
understand some of the
more harder to understand, not all of them
you have to understand.
But I'm going to show you how it works
sort of
end to end to a certain level of, of
detail.
So here we have a client, the client is
going to go ahead and call download image
on the stub.proxy.
So we've got this proxy.
And it's going to say download image.
And as we saw that's going to convert
the parameter and the return result into
parcels.
And those are going to get used to pass to
n remote.transact.
And that's going to take the data that
goes there and it's going to be.
Submitted by a lower level mechanism
probably written
in the, you know, native code at some
level.
That works atop the underlying LINUX
operating system.
And it uses an IO control, an ioctl which
is basically
a way of passing information to the low
level device drivers.
The low level device driver in this
particular case, of course.
Is the binary driver and that's the guy
that knows how
to move the data back and forth between
sender and receiver.
The data comes up on the other side; which
causes the thread that's sitting
there waiting for the data to unblock from
a call to ioctl, from ioctl.
And keep in mind there's a pool of threads
and they just take turns waiting for work
to do.
And so some thread is chosen.
It's, it's turned to run.
And it takes the data which is pretty low
level at this point and it goes ahead
and cracks it open, looks inside it and
figures out which binder object is this
actually for.
And it uses that information that was
registered earlier when we called the, the
attach
interface method on the stub, or, that was
called forest by the constructor of the
stub.
it uses that information to go find the
appropriate binder object, and call it's
on transact.
Hook.
And the on transact hook as we saw does
the de-martialing of the parameter.
And it goes ahead and it invokes the up
call, it's called
an up call, to the download image method
on our particular service.
So that goes ahead and does its work.
Now, I don't show the next set of things
but what'll happen is.
On the way out of that method callback, on
the way back from that up call.
The result is taken, so when, when
Download Image
returns a string, the generated stub takes
that string,
stuffs it back into the parcel that it was
sent along with the original called the on
transact.
And then, it unwinds the whole thing, it
goes backwards.
So it'll return everybody on blocks, and
we
end up ultimately back at the original
call site.
And the result comes back, as a return
value
from, the download image in location, on
the proxy itself.
So the proxy blocks, it looks just like a
regular
method call, just like a regular two way
method call.
But in fact, the processing was done by a
different method in
a different process for the object that
was the target of that invocation.
And that's what's commonly known as a
remote procedure
call, or remote method call, or some
variant on that.
Okay any questions about that?
So it's a good thing to know how all these
things work.
By the way, lest you think this is only
limited
to things running on the same hardware
platform like the device.
Obviously, there's a long, long history
going back to the 70's and
80's of people doing remote procedure
call, where you span network boundaries.
And the abstractions are more or less the
same as what we're talking about here.
It's just that you can talk with things
that
are on physically different hosts
connected to a network.
Android's AIDL and [UNKNOWN] RPC does not
work that way, but the various
RPC mechanisms you might use if you were
to use, say web services.
Or other types of middleware built in, to
on top of the underline mechanisms.
You can use those to talk from an Android
device to something else using remote
procedure calls as well.
There's a very nice article here that
gives more
information about binders and, and shows
lots of examples.
And, more code you can look at to see how
all the various pieces fit together.
Something else that's important to talk
about in
this context is the issue of call
semantics.
So what are the appropriate call semantics
for the AIDL and Binder RPC mechanisms.
And it turns out there's a couple
subtleties
here that you need to be aware of.
So, if you are in the same address space.
And you invoke an operation on, on a,
through a proxy.
What that does is that ends up just being
a direct
method call to the receiver; which is in
the same address space.
So if you're calling in the main thread of
control, the UI
thread, the call will actually be run in
the main thread of control.
So, it's just borrowing.
Excuse me.
It's borrowing the threat of control in
order to be able to run the requests.
So that's just a direct call.
Likewise, if the caller is in a separate
thread of control, again the thread will
be borrowed.
This is what's commonly called a
co-location optimization.
So it's taking advantage of things when
they're co-located in the same
address space, and it's removing a lot of
overhead; which is great.
It's exactly what you want.
Conversely if you invoke operations on
objects that run in a
separate address space; like another
process,
then the semantics are slightly different.
Rather than just calling it directly;
which it
can't do, because it can't get to the.
[UNKNOWN] the other process directory.
Instead what it's going to do, is it's
going to go ahead and do all the steps
that we just talked about to marshal up
the data, send it down through the layers.
And it'll pop up the other side, and it'll
run in a thread from a pool of threads.
So the key thing to remember there is when
you start calling
things that are going to run remotely with
AIDL and bind to RPC,.
You have to make sure your objects are
thread safe, that they've got the proper
synchronization.
And well take a look at some examples of
how to do
that, and then you know the return value
goes back the other direction.
The behavior of one way methods changes
the symatix a bit.
The main difference being that when you do
a one way method it
doesnt block the caller all the way until
it gets to the other side.
In fact its that kind of a fire and forget
model, it just sort
of says okay I pass it off
to the underlying operating system on the
clients.
Side and then I return, and that call
continues but I as the
client am not obliged to wait any longer
for the data to, to occur.
So it returns right away and there is no
actual return value.
Now just to be confusing, if you end up
doing
a one way call that's co-located in the
same address space.
Then that is actually going to be a two
way call in the sense that.
The call doesn't return to the caller
until the method finishes running.
But there will be no return values that
come back or out parameters.
So, these are typically compromises people
make just to simplify the implementation.
And, and make it work in ways that are
going to be optimized.
Not always necessarily semantically
consistent, but.
Optimal and easy to implement.
Okay, so to summarize this particular
discussion, AIDL is the interface
definition language that we use and
Android uses it to generate code.
And this code allows us to be able
to have multiple processes communicating
back and forth.
On the same piece of physical hardware the
device keep in mind
again that there's no reason to be limited
to that in general.
That's just the way Android does it and if
you
end up talking between processes that run
on different processes.
You end up talking processes on this same
machine then it's going to
have to generate the code the ADL
compatible have to generate code.
To do the marshalling and de-marshalling.
And that was the stuff that we looked at.
That's the stuff you don't have to write.
The only way you would end up writing code
like
that is either if you're going to write a
parcelable class.
In which case you have to fill in the read
from message
and write to message hook methods, and
they would do all those steps.
Or if you don't want to use AIDL and
you're
going to encode the data through a, some
other means.
Like a, something that you would, like a
parcel that you
would use if you were going to use
messages and messengers.
Let's see, whoops, that's annoying, hold
on.
Let me get rid of
this [SOUND].
All right, so, the interface definition
language that's
defined by, by Android is very similar to
Java.
It's also very similar to CORBA, and
Microsoft IDL and so on.
It's a little bit lighter weight, they
don't provide all of the
full-blown bells and whistles that some of
these other, more powerful things do.
And it basically uses these proxies in
order to be able to send
the values back and forth without having
to worry about address space issues.
And as I mentioned before, if you.
Do a little searching in Android, you will
find lots and lots and
lots of examples of AIDL used to pass
information around for lots of things.
And that's because under the hood, Android
is set
up to do a lot of communication between
different processes.
So that can be handled in a way that's
very transparent to the applications for
the most part.
But it allows for much greater flexibility
in how the system is configured.
And how the system is able to be moved
around and co-located or remoted.
Without changing the way in which the code
is structured.
Okay, so any questions about that?
[SOUND]
[MUSIC]