[MUSIC]
Welcome to the next part of the module
on Android services and local interprocess
communication mechanisms.
Which continues our analysis of how to
program a bound service.
The previous video summarized the overall
design.
And the individual steps involved in
programming bound services
in general, and the unique ID generator
service in particular.
We now take a closer look at the
protocol used to communicate between
activities and services.
Using the unique ID generator application
as a running example.
Well first examine the protocol for
launching
connecting and interacting with a bound
service.
When Android activity framework invokes
the on start hook method
on the unique id generator activity it
calls bind service.
Passing in the intent associated with a
bound service.
And the service connection object.
This method starts a unique ID generator
service if it's not already running.
Android service framework then invokes the
onBind factory method which returns
the iBinder associated with the messenger
that encapsulates the request handler.
The service framework then dispatches the
on service connected
hook method on the service connection
object in the activity.
Which encapsulates the iBinder returned
from onbind in a messenger
and assigns it to a data member in the
activity.
When a user presses the get unique ID
button, the
corresponding get unique ID method, is
dispatched, which creates a request
message, containing a reply messenger, and
calls the request messenger's send
method, to pass the message to the unique
ID generator service.
The message passed to send is forwarded by
the Android binder and
hammer frameworks to the handle message
hook method of the request handler.
Which creates a runable that encapsulates
the request message
and enques the runable into a thread pool
executor.
One of the threads in the pool.
DQs that are runnable generates a system
wide unique ID and
returns the ID back to the reply handler
running in the activity.
Androids binder and hammer frameworks once
again collaborate to
dispatch the handler message hook method
on the reply handler.
Which displays the unique ID to the
screen.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Next, we'll examine the protocol for
unbinding and shutting down a bound
service.
When an activity is completely obscured by
another activity,
the Android activity framework dispatches
the activity's onStop hook method.
When the unique ID generator activities
onStop method
is dispatched, it caused the unbind
service method.
If this activity was the last client
connected to the service, the Android
service framework dispatches the services
onUnbind
hook method, which returns false by
default.
As shown here.
After a services onUnbind returns false,
the Android service framework dispatches
it's on destroy hook method which cleans
up any allocated resources.
For example.
The auditory hook method and the unique ID
generator service shuts down the executor
thread pull.
Although we've examined the interactions
between components in the
context of the unique id generator
application this protocol
for launching connecting communicating,
and shutting down a bound
service is representative for essentially
all of bound services.
[MUSIC]
Now, that we've examined the protocol for
interacting
between activity and service components in
the unique id
generator application, we'll begin to
delve deeper into
the detailed design and the implementation
of it's' classes.
The unique id generator service contains a
request messenger that encapsulates.
A request handler and passes this
messenger back to
the unique ID generator activity when it
calls bind service.
The activity stores the request messenger
and
creates a reply messenger that
encapsulates a reply
handler and sends it to the service
by the request handler's handle message
hook method.
Which then generates and sends a
system-wide unique ID back
to the handle message hook method of the
activity's reply handler.
Now that the symmetry in the design has a
unique id generator application
which defines request reply messengers
that encapsulates request
and reply handlers in the service and
activity respectively.
[MUSIC]
We'll start by analyzing the unique ID
generator activity.
Which extends activity, and interacts with
the user to call
a bound service that generates a system
wide unique ID.
This activity defines several data
members.
Including a text view that defines a
location,
where the unique ID is displayed to the
user.
And a reference to the messenger
implemented in the unique ID generator
service.
A service connection data member is also
defined.
And used to receive a messenger reference
after the activity calls
bind service with an intent that
designates the unique ID generator
service.
After the service is connected, Android
service
framework dispatches the on service
connected hook method.
Which creates a new messenger that
encapsulates the
ibinder returned by the services onbind
factory method.
If the service crashes Android
service framework dispatches the onservice
disconnected
hook method to inform the activity not to
send any more requests.
Until the service is running again.
When the activity becomes visible Androids
activity framework
calls the onStart hook method, which calls
bind service.
Passing the appropriate intent returned by
the make
intent factory method and the service
connection object
use it to dispatch call backs to the
activity when a connection is established
with the service.
[MUSIC]
When the user presses the generate unique
ID button,
Android's activity framework dispatches
the the generate unique ID method.
This method creates a request message and
a new messenger that encapsulates the
reply handler .Which is then stored in the
request message's reply to field.
The request message is then passed to the
unique ID generator service as a parameter
to
the send method, via the reference to the
request messenger return from the services
onBind factory method.
The reply to this request message is
processed
by the activities reply handler, which
extends handler.
And receives reply containing the unique
ID
sent by the Unique ID Generator Service.
When the service sends this reply, the
binder framework and hammer
framework collaborate to dispatch the
handle message hook method which invokes
the unique ID helper method defined in the
Unique ID Generator
Service to extract the unique ID
encapsulated in the reply message.
This helper method shields the activity
from the
details of how the reply message is
implemented.
The unique id is then displayed on the
screen.
When the unique id generator activity is
completely
obscured by another activity the android
activity framework.
Dispatches the activity's onStop hook
method which
calls unbindService to disconnect from the
UniqueIDGeneratorService.
If or when the activity becomes visible
again, its onStart hook method will
automatically be
dispatched by the Android activity
framework and
the connection to the service will be
re-established.
Via bindService.
[MUSIC]
The UniqueIDGeneratorService extends
service and generates
unique ID's within a pool of threads.
Which enable multiple client requests to
run concurrently
an can improve performance on a multicore
device.
Unique ID generator service defines
several
data members used throughout its
implementation.
Including the executor service
That provides a thread pool used to
service client requests,
the maximum number of threads in that
pool, a shared preferences
object that stores unique IDs
persistently, and a messenger that
receives
request messages request messages sent
from the Unique ID Generator Activity.
The onBind factory method.
Returns the Ibinder associated with this
request messenger when
the activity binds to the unique ID
generator service.
When this service is launched the Android
service framework dispatches it's onCreate
hook method.
Which initializes the data members
outlined above.
For example, it first creates a request
messenger that encapsulates
a request handler used to process request
messages received from clients.
It then obtains a reference to the default
file
used by the shared preferences framework
for this service.
As shown here.
Finally, it initializes a fixed thread
pool executor that's
configured to use in MAX THREADS, as shown
here.
The unique ID generator service also
defines several helper methods that shield
the
unique ID generator activity from the
details of how the service is implemented.
For example.
Make intent is a factory method that
creates
and intent associated with a Unique ID
generator service.
Likewise, the unique ID method extracts
the unique ID string from the
bundle of data contained in the reply
message and returns it to the caller.
[MUSIC]
Request messages sent from a unique ID
generator activity to the
unique ID generator service are processed
by the request handling which
extends handler and overrides the handle
message hook method that's dispatched
by the hammer framework when a request
message arrives from the activity.
This hook method stores a reference to the
reply messenger.
In a local variable, and then creates, and
then queues
an anonymous runnable that's executed in a
thread in the
thread pool, where it generates a unique
ID, and sends
the ID back to the activity via the Reply
Messenger Reference.
The Generate Unique ID Method returns
a message containing a unique system-wide
ID.
This id is computed by calling the random
uu id method.
Which returns an immutable representation
of 128
bit universally unique id as shown here.
Although the value returned by random uu
id has a very
low probability of duplicates as discussed
here, our implementation takes no chances.
So it runs in a loop and compares the
results returned by random UUID with a
value stored in the shared preferences
object which
is implemented internally by a Java Hash
Map.
As shown in this past name when a
unique value is found it's added to the
persistent
collection of unique id's and then
returned as
a string in the bundled data of reply
message.
Sent back to the activity.
[MUSIC]
In summary, applications can use services
to
implement long duration operations in the
background.
A service is particularly useful for
packaging a cohesive set of
functionality into a form that's
independent
of the component that initiates it.
Which enables the service to be shared by
multiple applications.
We have examined several services that
package functionality
for downloading images and generating
system wide unique I.D.'s.
Started services are easy to program for
simple one
way interactions from an activity to a
service, however,.
They require more complex and ad hoc
programming for extended two-way
conversations with their clients.
In contrast, bound services may be a
better choice
for more complex two-way interactions
between activities and services.
For example, they support two-way
conversations.
Use either generic or typed interfaces.
Likewise, common initialization and
communication mechanisms are handled by
the Android service framework and its
connection callback protocol.
Moreover, their lifecycle is managed
automatically by the Android service
framework.
Since they're shut down when no clients
are bound to them.
However, programmers must understand the
details of the
multi step client service connection and
interaction protocol.
Which involves event driven call backs.
Knowledge of the broker pattern helps to
clarify key roles
and relationships In bound services, as
described in upcoming videos.
[MUSIC]