[MUSIC]
Welcome to the next part of the module,
which begins our discussion of the monitor
object
pattern that forms the basis for many
concurrency
libraries, applications and services in
Java and Android.
This part first summarizes the challenges
that the monitor object pattern addresses
and
then describes its intent, applicability,
structure, dynamics,
consequences and outlines some common
known uses.
Based on material from the posted to book
and summarized at this link.
To motivate the need for this pattern and
to introduce an example that
we'll use throughout our discussion of
this pattern, we generalize from several
examples
covered in previous parts of this
module, where concurrent applications and
services need
to coordinate the interactions of multiple
producer
and consumer threads via a shared queue.
A common problem in this type of software
is
that naive implementations of a shared
queue will incur
race conditions or busy waiting, when
multiple threads put
and take items in to and from the queue.
For example, concurrent threads can
corrupt the
queues internal state, if it's not
synchronized properly.
Likewise, threads will incur busy waiting
when the
queue is empty or full, which wastes CPU
cycles.
A common solution to these problems is to
apply the monitor object pattern to
synchronize the shared queue in a manner
that's efficient and relatively easy to
program.
Earlier parts of this module have shown
implementations of the monitor object
pattern in the video on Java condition
objects and Java built-in monitor objects.
This part expands upon this earlier
coverage to examine
the pattern more comprehensively using the
Java-linked blocking queue.
Described at this link as a running
example to
make the discussion of the monitor object
pattern more concrete.
Link blocking queue is similar to the
array
blocking queue we examined in this earlier
video.
A detailed comparison of the performance
differences between link
blocking queue and array blocking queue
appear at this link.
[MUSIC]
As correctly inefficient, the monitor
object pattern appears in the POSA2 book.
The intent of this pattern is to
synchronize concurrent method execution
to ensure that only method at a time runs
within an object.
It also allows an object's methods
to cooperatively schedule their execution
sequence.
This pattern is applicable under several
conditions.
For example, it's often the case that an
object's
interface methods can define its
scheduling and synchronization boundaries.
To separate concerns and protect object
state from uncontrolled changes, object
oriented programmers are accustomed to
accessing
objects only through their interface
methods.
It's straight forward to extend this
object oriented programming
model to protect an objects data from
uncontrolled concurrent changes.
Concurrent software is often easier to
program with only
one method at a time is active within an
object.
Likewise, concurrent software's also often
easier to program when clients
aren't responsible for serializing method
execution in an object since
it's tedious and error-prone to explicitly
acquire and release low-level
synchronization and scheduling mechanisms,
such as locks and condition variables.
Finally, an object's methods may need
to interact cooperatively during their
execution.
For example, if one thread must block
awaiting a
resource during its execution, it should
be able to relinquish
its thread of control voluntarily, so
methods called from
other threads can access the object to
update the resource.
When a method relinquishes its thread of
control
voluntarily, it must ensure that object
specific invariance hold.
Likewise, it must resume executing within
an
object only when it's in a stable state.
[MUSIC]
This diagram shows the structure of the
monitor object pattern.
The monitor object class exports one or
more synchronize methods.
To protect the internal state of the
monitor object from race
conditions, all clients must access the
monitor object only through these methods.
Each synchronized method typically
executes in the
thread of the client that invokes it.
Java's link blocking queue, described at
this link, is
an example of a class implemented as a
monitor object.
Each monitor object contains one or more
monitor locks.
What you use to insure mutual exclusion of
its synchronized methods on a per object
basis.
Each synchronized method acquires and
releases
a monitor lock while entering or exiting
the monitor object, to ensure it's
internal state is protected from race
conditions.
For example, the link blocking queue
class,
uses two Java reentrant locks, take lock
and
put lock, as it's monitor locks protect
the
current queue from corruption due to
concurrent access.
Multiple synchronized methods running in
separate threads can
cooperatively synchronize and schedule
their execution sequences by
waiting for and notifying each other by
one
or more monitor conditions associated with
the monitor object.
Synchronized methods use a monitor lock in
conjunction with one of
our monitor conditions to determine when
to suspend and resume their processing.
For example, the link blocking queue class
uses two Java
condition objects, not empty and not full,
as it's monitor conditions
to coordinate producer and consumer
threads that attempt to take elements
from or put elements to an empty or full
queue respectively.
[MUSIC]
This UML sequence diagram shows the
dynamic
interactions between participants in the
monitor object pattern.
When thread T1 invokes a synchronized
method on a monitor
object, the method must first acquire the
object's monitor lock.
A monitor lock can't be acquired as long
as another
synchronized method in thread T2 is
executing within the monitor object.
In this case, client thread T1 will
lock until the synchronized method
acquires a lock.
After the synchronized method called by T1
is finished executing, the monitor lock is
released so that other synchronized
methods called
by other threads can access the monitor
object.
For example, if thread T1 calls the
synchronized take method on a
linked blocking queue, it will block until
it can acquire the take lock.
If synchronize method must block or
otherwise
can't make immediate progress, it can wait
on one of its monitored conditions,
causing
it to leave the monitor object
temporarily.
The monitor object implementation is
responsible for ensuring that the
object is in a stable state, before
switching to another thread.
When a synchronized method leaves the
monitor object, the client's thread is
suspended on that monitor condition, and
the monitor lock is released atomically.
Another synchronized method in another
thread
can now execute within the monitor object.
For example, if thread T1 calls a
synchronized take method on an
empty link blocking queue, it will wait on
the not empty condition.
A synchronized method can notify a monitor
condition, which awakens a thread
of a synchronized method, that it
suspended itself on the monitor condition.
For example, if thread T2 calls a
synchronized
put method to add a new element to
the link blocking queue, it will notify
the
not empty condition object, which may
awaken thread T1.
A synchronized method can also notify all
synchronized methods
that suspended their thread earlier on the
monitor condition.
In this case, all suspended threads are
awaken, and one of them
at a time can acquire the monitor lock and
run within monitor object.
After a suspended synchronized method is
notified, its execution can
resume at the point where it waited on the
monitor condition.
This resumption is typically performed
implicitly by
having the monitor lock reacquired
atomically before
the notified thread reenters the monitor
object
and resumes execution of the synchronized
method.
For example, when the not empty condition
object
at thread T1 is waiting on is notified by
thread T2, T1 will reacquire the take lock
and
continue trying to take an element from
the queue.
Due to the non-deterministic nature of
concurrency, however, thread
T1 may or may not actually add an element
to
the queue, which is why calls to wait on a
condition object should nearly always be
invoked within a loop.
[MUSIC]
The monitor object pattern provider two
key benefits to developers of concurrent
software.
First, it presents a concise programming
model
for sharing an object among cooperating
threads.
For example, concurrent access to a link
blocking queue corresponds to conventional
method indications.
Likewise, clients need not be concerned
with explicit
serialization mechanisms when invoking
methods on a monitor object.
A second benefit is that synchronized
method's
can use their monitor conditions to
determine
when a thread should suspend or resume
its execution and that of collaborating
threads.
For example, put and take methods on a
linked blocking
queue can suspend themselves and a wait to
be notified when
internal state changes occur without using
an efficient polling, which
allows monitor objects to cooperatively
execute their methods in multiple threads.
They're also several drawbacks to the
monitor object pattern however.
One drawback occurs, when a single monitor
lock is used per monitor object, which
limits scannability, due to the increased
contention,
when multiple threads serialize on the
single lock.
The link blocking queue class, shows one
way to improve scannability, by defining
multiple monitor locks, as we'll examine
further, in the next part of this module.
Another drawback involves the complicated
extensibility semantics resulting from
tight
coupling between a monitor object's
functionality and its concurrency control
mechanisms,
which makes it hard to change
synchronization in scheduling policies
or mechanisms without modifying the
implementations of a monitor object's
methods.
This link contains more discussion of the
inheritance anomaly problem related to
this drawback.
[MUSIC]
There are many known uses of the monitor
object pattern.
Originating with the Dijkstra and
Hoare-style
monitors that define programming language
features to
encapsulate functions and their internal
variables into
thread-safe modules, as described at this
link.
Java built-in monitor objects are based on
a subset
of the Dijkstra Hoare-style monitors as
described at this link.
Any Java object can be used as a monitor
object that contains a single monitor
lock and a single monitor condition as
described in the previous video in this
module.
Java monitor objects are convenient for
simple use cases
because they allow threads to serialize
their execution implicitly via
synchronized methods and coordinate their
activities via calls to wait,
notify and notify all methods, defined on
all Java objects.
Although Java built-in monitor objects are
not
well suited for more sophisticated use
cases,
such as the classes in Java util
concurrent and Android's concurrency
frameworks, the monitor
object pattern is still widely applied in
this code, as shown in our analysis
of the link blocking queue class in part
two of the monitor object pattern video.
C++ libraries also provide portable
building blocks for implementing monitor
objects.
For example, ACE provides many reusable
open source
C++ wrapper facades for mutual exclusion,
or mutex
locks and condition variables that are
portable to
many operating system platforms, as
described at this link.
Likewise C++11 specifies mutex locks and
condition variables that enable
developers to write multi-threaded code in
a standard way, as described at this link.
[MUSIC]
In summary, concurrent software often
contains objects whose
methods are invoked concurrently by
multiple client threads.
To protect the internal state of objects
shared by multiple
threads, it's necessary to synchronize and
schedule access to them.
To simplify programming, it's often
helpful if the
interface and object exposes to its
clients is the
same, regardless of whether the object is
shared by
multiple threads or just accessed by a
single thread.
The monitor object pattern provides an
intuitive
programming model that enables client
threads to share
objects and cooperatively ensure their
serialized yet
interleaved execution sequence, as
described at this link.
[MUSIC]