[MUSIC]
Welcome to the next part of the module
on Android services and local interprocess
communication mechanisms.
Which begins our analysis of how to
program a bound service.
A bound service offers a client server
interface that allows extended
two way conversations between one or more
clients and the service.
As shown in an earlier video.
To understand how to develop a bound
service with
a pair of messengers, this part will
analyze key
elements and steps in design of an
application that
can currently retrieves a system wide,
persistent unique identifier.
And displays it to the user.
Before delving into the details of this
program we will first
outline the overall structure and
functionality
of the unique ID generator application.
This application contains the unique ID
generator activity that
calls bind service on a unique ID
generator service.
When Android calls it's life cycle hook
method.
This service returns a reference to
a manager through it's onBind factory
method.
The activity receives this reference by
the on-service connected
hook method, and stores it in a local data
member.
When the user clicks the generate unique
ID button, the activity
uses the messenger reference to send a
request message to the service.
This message contains a reference to a
reply messenger defined in the activity,
that
the service uses to return the system wide
unique ID, back to the activity.
The service receives this message via a
handle message hook method
and enqueues the message in a background
thread for subsequent processing.
This background thread generates the
unique ID and returns
the result by calling send on the reply
messenger reference.
The activity then receives this reply
message via a handle
message hook method and displays the
unique ID to the user.
The source code for the unique ID
generator application is available at this
link.
So download it, and watch this video, and
the next one, carefully.
Perhaps multiple times, to learn how it
works.
This example contains four primary
classes, as well
as various Android bound service,
concurrency, and communication mechanisms.
So we'll progressively analyze the design
and implementation from
various perspectives to show how all the
pieces work.
And fit together.
[MUSIC]
We'll now summarize the steps involved in
programming a bound service.
Using our unique ID application as a
running
example to reality each step in general a
client.
Typically in activity launches about
servers by calling the buying service
method to creat a so call persistent
connection as discuss here.
For example, the unique ID generator
activity uses a factor method
that creat a tenth command that identifies
a series of starts.
Wich in this case is the unique ID
generator service.
In addition to passing the intent to
buying service the climist most also
provide a service connection object thats
use
to monitor the connection with the
service.
Hook methods defined in the
service connection object, are
automatically called
back by Android's service framework, where
connections are established, and lost.
As shown here.
In response to the bind service
call, Android's activity manager service,
launches
the service, if it's not already
running using the activator pattern
described here.
The activity manager service starts the
service
asynchronously so the bind service method
does not
block the client synchronously while the
unique
ID generator service is being launched and
run.
After the service is up and running
Androids service framework invokes the
onCreate and on
bind hook methods to perform
initialization activities it
inherits these methods from the service
super class.
The unique generator services onCreate
method.
Initializes its data members, such as the
messenger, that
hands requests for unique IDs, an object
that stores
these IDs persistently, and an executor
that manages the
pool of threads used to process client
requests concurrently.
Likewise, onBind returns an IBinder object
that enables
a client to communicate with a bound
service.
The object returned from onBind is
typically initialized in
the onCreate hook method or in a data
member definition.
For example the unique ID generator
service
onBind factory method calls get binder to
return
the binder the request messenger users to
communicate
with it's associated request handle as
discussed here.
Although multiple clients can connect to a
bound service Android
service framework only calls the services
on bind factory method.
To retrieve the Ibinder when the first
client binds.
It catches this Ibinder and redelivers it
to any additional clients that bind
without calling onBind again as discussed
here.
Service connection class implements a call
back driven protocol that the Android
service
framework uses to establish a connection
between a client and a bound service.
After a connection to the service has been
established,.
This framework automatically dispatches
the onServiceConnected
hook method to give the client
the ibinder object of the communication
channel that's connected to the service.
The unique ID generator activity overrides
this method.
To get the I Binder to the messenger
that's returned from the on bind factory
method which is then encapsulated in a
new messenger reference data member for
later use.
The Android service framework
automatically
dispatches the on-service disconnected
hook method.
When a connection to the service has been
lost.
This can happen when the process hosting
the service
has crashed or has been killed by the
Android RunTime.
This hook method does not remove the
service connection itself.
Which remains active.
So the client will receive a call back to
on
service connected when the bound service
is up and running again.
The client can interact with the service
after the connection is established, and
the on service connected method returns
it the interface to the communication
channel.
This interface an be generic.
Such as the mechanisms that perform inter
process communication in the unique ID
generator application via send and handle
message
calls on messenger and handle objects
respectively.
An interface can also be type specific
such as the mechanisms for inter
process communication based on the Android
Interface
Definition Language shown in an upcoming
video.
Both approaches use the Android binder
framework and implementation patterns.
Such as broker and proxy the unique ID
generator application uses a pair
of messengers to communicate the unique
generator service defines a request
messenger that
encapsulates a request handler this
messenger
is past the unique generator activity by
the onBind factory method and subsequently
used to send a request to the service.
Likewise, unique ID generator activity
defines a
reply messenger that encapsulates a reply
handler.
This messenger is passed to the unique ID
generator service as the reply to field
in the request message, and used to send
the unique ID back to the activity.
When a bound service is launched, its life
cycle typically depends on the components
accessing it.
In particular, a bound service usually
doesn't run in the background
indefinitely, but instead is managed
automatically by the Android service
framework.
Based on whether it's bound to any clients
as shown here.
When a client is done interacting with a
bound
service, it calls unBindService which
informs the Android service framework.
That the client no longer wants to receive
calls if the service is restarted.
When all clients have unbound from a
service the Android
service framework calls its on unBind hook
method which returns false
by default but can be programmed to return
true if
the service is on rebind hook method
should be called later.
When new clients bind to it.
OnRebind is used when a service continues
running after all it's clients have
unbound.
Which happens if a bound service is also a
started service.
Which isn't uncommon but supported use
case as discussed here.
When the service is unbound from all
clients Android service framework
dispatches it's on destroy hook method
unless it's also a started service.
This hook method cleans up any resources
that may have been allocated.
Such as shutting down, the thread pool
executor, in the unique ID generator
service.
It's a good idea to call unBindService,
when an activity
stops, or when it's done interacting with
a bound service.
So that Android's service framework, can
shut
down the service, when it's not being
used.
When a clan activity is destroyed.
Android, automatically unBinds it, from
any bound services it's connected to.
[MUSIC]
>> In summary, a bound service is the
server,
in client server interactions that run on
Android devices.
For example, the unique ID generator
application defines a bound service.
That allows activities to bind to the
service
send requests relieve replies and perform
inner process communication.
A bound service typically lives only while
it serves other
application components for example the
unique ID generator service does
not run in the background indefinitely but
only lives as
long as the unique ID generator activities
that bind to it.
It's also possible to define hybrid
models.
That comply in bound and started services.
In particular, if a bound service also
implements the onStart command
hook method it won't be destroyed when
it's unbound from all clients.
If the onUnbind method returns true the
onRebind hook method will
be called the next time a client binds to
the service.
Instead of having it receive a call, to
onbind, on rebind is past the intent,
originally used to bind to the service, by
the bind service method call, as discussed
here.
Although hybrid services are not nearly as
common, as either started, or bound
services.
The Android media playback service, is an
example of a hybrid service.
That's both started and bound, as shown at
this path name.
[MUSIC]