[MUSIC]
Welcome to the next part of the module on
Android Services and local inter-process
communication mechanisms, which presents
an overview of the Android Interface
Definition Language commonly
known as AIDL and the binder inter-process
communication framework.
In this part, we'll summarize how these
Android mechanisms enable activities to
communicate concurrently with objects
residing in
bound services, either synchronously, or
asynchronously.
The AIDL and Binder provide
powerful mechanisms for object-orientated
inter-process
communication, that largely mimic typed
method invocations on Java objects.
Throughout this video we'll motivate these
mechanisms in the context of a
bound download application that uses the
AIDL and Binder to interact with
a pair of bound services to
download images synchronously and
asynchronously from
a remote web server and display them in
the user interface thread.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The design as the example application is
similar to the programming assignment
available here.
So I encourage you to download it and
follow along with the video to understand
common
methods and patterns of programming bound
services using
the Android Interface Definition Language
and Binder mechanisms.
Although these mechanisms are powerful,
there are a number
of constructs and steps required to use
them effectively.
So I also will recommend you watch these
optional videos to explore these
mechanisms in more detail.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC]
Services may need to run in different
processes in
their clients for the reasons discussed in
a previous video.
However, to enhance security and
reliability, objects in one Android
process
generally can't access objects in the
address space of another process.
Since processes are intentionally designed
to
protect their contents from access by
other
processes, operating systems provide
strictly mediated and
controlled inter-process communication
mechanisms, as discussed here.
For example, activities in Android that
communicate
with objects and services residing in
other processes,
must perform several additional steps
beyond what's needed
to communicate with objects in their own
process.
In particular, they must decompose and
transform the data
in their objects which may be arbitrarily
complex into byte streams that
the underlying Linux operating system can
understand, and then exchange these byte
streams across address spaces via Linux
inter-process communication mechanisms.
At the heart of these steps are
marshaling and demarshaling mechanisms
which are discussed here.
In the context of Android, marshaling
converts the native
representation of Java Object Data, such
as, ents, shorts, doubles,
and arrays of these types into a
serialized byte stream
representation suitable for transmission
to a different processes address base.
Conversely, demarshaling converts the data
in a serialized byte stream
representation to reconstitute an object
in a native Java representation.
For example, the activity and services
processes in our bound
download application exchange Java
strings, containing the desired URL of
an image on a remote server and the path
name
to the file where the image is downloaded
on the device.
The mechanisms in AIDL and Binder support
the marshaling and
demarshaling of a much wider range of data
types beyond
strings, including all the primitive data
types in Java as
well as references to objects that reside
in other processes.
[MUSIC]
Manually writing code to perform
marshaling and
demarshaling is tedious and error prone
since
programmers must understand low-level
details of how
to convert every field of an object's data
into a byte stream on the client side, so
that the byte stream can
later be correctly converted back into a
copy of the object of the callee side.
To simplify this conversion process,
Android defines an
interface definitional language called
AIDL, and an associated
compiler that automatically generates
proxies and stubs to
perform marshaling and demarshaling
respectively, as covered here.
The syntax and semantics of AIDL are
similar to Java interfaces,
plus some enhancements and restrictions
covered by Professor Porter in this video.
For example, the bound download
application defined the downloader AIDL
interface.
A caller passes its download image method,
a
string, containing a URL as an input
parameters to
callee, and the callee then returns a
string containing
the downloaded image path name back to the
caller.
When an application is built, Eclipse
automatically
compiles the AIDL files in a project
source directory and stores the generated
proxies
and stubs into the project's GEN
directory.
The generated Java file name matches the
AIDL file name but with a .Java extension.
For example, Downloader AIDL results in
downloader Java as discussed here.
The actual transfer of marshaled data is
performed
in conjunction with the Android binder
framework, which implements
a lightweight remote method call mechanism
designed for
high performance intra and inter-process
communication, as covered here.
However, applications rarely access the
underlying binder framework directly.
Instead, the proxies generated by the AIDL
compiler, marshal method parameters pass
by callers.
The proxies then use binder mechanisms to
transfer the
marshaled data to the target object in the
callee's process.
The binder framework there then uses the
generated
stubs to demarshal the data, and invoke
the designated
method implementations, to perform
computations in the callee's
process and return any results back to the
caller.
[MUSIC].
The bulk of the Android binder framework
is implemented via a device driver that
resides
in the Linux kernel and is optimized for
inter, and intra-process communication on
an Android device.
Internally, it's implemented using shared
memory, which minimizes data copying.
The Binder framework also provides a pool
of threads
that run within each Linux process hosting
Android applications
which enables multiple client requests to
run concurrently and
scalably, especially on multicore devices
that are becoming ubiquitous.
A detailed analysis of the Android Binder
framework appears here.
The use of AIDL not only simplifies
inter-process communication, it also
simplifies inter-language communication.
For example, although most application
services are written in Java, it's also
possible to write services in other
programming languages such C or C++.
Many Android system services are written
in C++, including the media player
service, Sensor Service and Audio and
Surface Flinger services, as shown here.
The proxies and stubs generated by the
AIDL compiler are used
at several points in the path from caller
to callee and back.
The proxies generated by the AIDL compiler
marshal caller data into
parcels which are containers for data and
object references, as shown here.
The binder framework on the caller side
copies these parcels from the caller's
process to the callee's process, where the
binder framework on the callee's side
uses the stubs generated by the AIDL
compiler to demarshal the contents of
the parcels into the native representation
expected by methods in the callee's
object.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC]
By default, methods defined in AIDL
interfaces provide
two-way synchronous invocation semantics,
where the caller sends input parameters
to the callee and then blocks
synchronously until the
callee's method implementation returns
results back to the caller.
When a caller invokes an AIDL method on an
object that
spans process boundaries the method
implementation is dispatched in the
callee's
process by the binder framework which runs
the method implementation in
a thread selected from a per-process pool
of threads that it manages.
In contrast, if an AIDL method is
pre-fixed with a one-way key word, the
behavior
is different when a caller invokes this
method on an object that spans process
boundaries.
In this case, the caller does not block
synchronously waiting for the
results, but instead, it returns
immediately
while the callee executes the method
asynchronously.
Two-way asynchronous communication
interactions can therefore be
implemented via the Binder framework by
defining two
AIDL interfaces, one for requests and one
for results, each defined using one-way,
non-blocking methods.
In this design, the caller creates a
results object
and invokes a one-way call to pass a
reference to
this object along with any input
parameters to the
callee, but does not block synchronously
waiting for the results.
The callee runs this method implementation
in a thread selected by
the binder framework from the per-process
pool of threads that it manages.
When the callee finishes executing, it
sends the
results back to the caller by invoking a
one-way
method call on the results object it
originally
received, which essentially turns the
callee into a caller.
Naturally, this one-way callback from the
original callee back to the original
caller doesn't block either, making the
two-way interactions fully asynchronous.
The Binder framework in the original
caller's process dispatches the method on
the
results object in a thread selected from
the per-process pool of threads it
manages.
Since AIDL invocations that span process
boundaries are handled in threads
from the Binder's thread pool rather than
from their user interface thread,
application developers must ensure that
any object accessed via these calls,
are properly synchronized to avoid race
conditions, if they access shared state.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC]
In summary, AIDL is a language that
enables
developers to define Binder-based
interfaces to bound services.
When the Android Interface Definition
Language and
Binder framework are used together, they
provide
several key capabilities to applications
that communicate
with Bound services residing in separate
processes.
First, they provide an object-oriented
IPC mechanism that simplifies
communication between
activities and services, by largely
mimicking
typed method invocations between Java
objects.
In contrast, the generic messenger-based
approach covered in previous videos,
requires applications to manually put and
get data into and from messages, which can
be problematic since the schema of the
messages may be more implicit
and thus tedious and error prone,
than the explicitly-typed interfaces
defined using AIDL.
Second, the AIDL and Binder enable method
calls, spanning process boundaries to
run concurrently in a pool of threads
managed by the Binder framework.
As a result, application developers don't
have to explicitly manipulate threads,
handlers, runables,
or messages, which reduces accidental
complexity
and codifies a design space more
consistently.
Third, the AIDL and Binder simplify the
development of activities and services
that can communicate via two-way
asynchronous
interactions that block neither callers
nor callees.
Fully asynchronous programs can be more
robust and scalable as long as
developers understand the relevant
patterns, such
as state, asynchronous completion token
and proacter.
The AIDL and Binder implementations apply
the Broker pattern to connect clients with
objects residing in Bound services in a
different address base, and mediate method
invocations
from clients to these objects by
encapsulating application code from
low-level inter-process communication
details such as connection management,
marshaling and
demarshaling, data transfer, concurrency
and process crashes.
Other patterns are also applied in
Android's implementation of Broker,
including proxy and activator as discussed
in an upcoming section.
The AIDL and Binder are used extensively
in Android, and
hundreds of AIDL files appear in Android's
frameworks and packaged applications.
[BLANK_AUDIO]