[MUSIC]
Welcome to the next part of the module,
which continues our discussion of the
Monitor Object
Pattern, that forms the basis for many
concurrency
libraries, applications and services in
Java and Android.
This part provides a detailed analysis of
how the
Monitor Object Pattern is implemented and
applied in Android.
To make the discussion concrete, we'll
examine the implementation
of the LinkedBlockingQueue class described
at this link, which is
a bounded blocking queue based on linked
nodes that
queues elements in first in, first out, or
FIFA order.
The four steps used to implement the
monitor object pattern are described
in detail in the POSA 2 book, and are
summarized at this link.
These steps include defining the interface
methods.
Defining the implementation methods,
defining
the internal state and synchronization
and scheduling mechanisms, and
implementing all methods and data members.
We'll examine each of these implementation
steps next.
[MUSIC]
We'll start by defining the monitor
objects' interface methods which
expose us to the public methods that are
visible to clients.
These methods are typically synchronized
so only one of them at
a time can be executed by a thread within
the monitor object.
For example, the link blocking queue
inherits from the
blocking queue interface as shown at this
path name.
Blocking queue defines the put and take
methods
along with other methods as described at
this link.
The semantics of Put are to insert the
specified element
into a queue waiting, if necessary, for
space to become available.
Likewise, the semantics of take are to
retrieve and to remove the
head of the queue, waiting if necessary,
until an element becomes available.
The next step is to define implementation
methods.
Which are private or protected and that's
below
the surface of what's directly visible to
clients.
The implementation of linkedBlockingQueue
applies the thread safe
interface pattern which minimizes locking
overhead by ensuring that
intra-object method calls do not
re-acquire a lock held
by the object already, as described at
this link.
Two implementation methods we describe are
enqueue and dequeue.
Enqueue is called by Put.
It links a node at the end of the queue.
Dequeue is called by Take.
It removes a node from the head of the
queue.
Both implementation methods assume the
interface methods that call them.
Acquire and release the appropriate
monitor lock
as designated by the thread safe interface
pattern.
A monitor object contains data members
that define its internal state.
Which must be protected from corruption by
race conditions resulting from
unserialized concurrent access.
A monitor object therefore also contains
one or more
monitor locks, that serialize the
execution of its synchronized
methods, as well as one or more monitor
conditions
that coordinate and schedule the execution
of its synchronized methods.
There's typically a separate monitor
condition
for each of the following situations.
Cases in which a synchronized method must
suspend its processing
to wait for some event or state change to
occur.
Or cases in which a synchronized method
must resume other threads
whose synchronized methods have suspended
themselves previously on the monitor
condition.
Monitor object implementation is
responsible for insuring it's
in a stable state for releasing its
monitor lock.
Stable states can be described by
invariants, such as a need for
all elements in a linked blocking queue to
be connected by valid pointers.
The invariant must hold whenever a
synchronized
method waits on a corresponding monitor
condition.
Similarly, when the monitor object is
modified
and the thread scheduler decides to resume
awaiting
thread, the monitor object implementation
is responsible for
ensuring the invariant is indeed satisfied
before proceeding.
This check is necessary because other
threads my
have changed the state of the monitor
object.
Between the notification, and the
resumption.
As a result, the monitor object must
ensure the invariant
is satisfied, before allowing a
synchronized method to resume its
execution.
The internal state of the
LinkedBlockingQueue class, consists
of head and last data members of type
node.
Which stores an element in a pointer to
the next node in a linked queue.
It also contains a capacity member that
indicates
the maximum number of elements that can be
in
the queue before it's considered full and
a count
of the number of elements currently in the
queue.
Count is implemented as an atomic integer.
Wich cold be incremented and decrimented
anatomically and
efficiently for multiple threads, as
described this link.
Link blocking Q also uses the reaction
log, the condition option
classes to find the job you took to in
current package describing
this link, to protect it's internal state
from race conditions and
coordinate interaction with the threads
and put owner from the q currently.
It contains a pair of condition objects.
Not full, and not empty.
To enable blocking, put and take method
calls
when the queue is full and empty,
respectively.
Likewise, it can contains a pair of metric
locks, a lock and take lock.
Which are used together with the atomic
integer count to optimize
concurrent calls to put and take as
described at this link.
The next step in implementing this pattern
involves
developing all the monitor object's
methods and data members.
We'll analyse a portion of the linked
blocking queue implementation, so you may
want to download its source code,
available
at this path name, and follow along.
There are two sub-steps involved in
implementing
a monitor object's methods and data
members.
The first sub step is to initialize its
data members.
Including its monitor locks and monitor
conditions.
For example, linked blocking queue
initializes its reentrant locks, condition
objects, and the atomic integer in the
class definition itself.
Likewise, its capacity, head, and last
data members are initialized in its
constructor.
The second sub-step involves developing
the interface and implementation methods
in accordance with the thread-safe
interface pattern described at this link.
We'll examine portions of the put and take
method implementation.
Which also applied the guarded suspension
pattern described at this link.
The Put Method inserts its element E
parameter into the queue using the guarded
suspension pattern to wait for space to
become available if the queue is full.
Put initializes the AtomicInteger to the
number of elements in the.
Queue and then acquires the putLock.
Once this lock is acquired, a try block is
used to check if the queue is
full, which occurs as long as the number
of nodes in the queue equals the capacity.
While the queue is full, the calling
thread waits on the not full condition
object.
Once another thread notifies the queue
it's no longer full,.
The loop exits, and the enqueue
implementation method is
called, which links the newly created node
into the queue.
Since enqueue is an implementation method,
it assumes its caller hold the put lock.
After enqueue returns, the atomic integer
is used to check if the queue
is still not full, in which case the not
full condition object is signaled.
There by allowing other waiting threads
successfully
put an element on to the queue.
When the tri block is done, the putlock is
released automatically.
Finally, if local variable c equals 0,
which indicates the queue is
no longer empty, since the actual kind of
elements is c plus 1.
The signal not empty method is called.
This method acquires the takeLock and
signals the notEmpty condition object to
notify any thread blocked on take that the
queue is no longer empty.
We'll now briefly outline the take method
implementation which retrieves and removes
the head of the queue, waiting
if necessary until an element becomes
available.
The portion of its implementation shown on
this slide
is similar to the put method we just
analyzed.
For example Take acquires the takelock
waits on the not empty
condition object while the number of
elements in the queue equals 0.
And then dequeues and returns the head
element in the queue to the caller.
Take also signals the notEmpty and
notFullCondition objects
in a manner similar to the put method.
So you may want to examine the Android
source
code for all the details that aren't
covered here.
Now that we've shown how the link
blocking queue implements the monitor
object pattern.
I'll show an example of where
this pattern-oriented queue is applied in
Android.
This example is part of the Android
calendar application located
at this path name which displays, creates,
edits, and deletes events.
From each Google account that synchronizes
with an Android device.
This application contains an event loader
class shown at this path
name which contains a link blocking queue
that's initialized in it's constructors.
Event loader methods running in the user
interface thread can use this queue to
put requests for one or more days worth of
events to a loader thread.
Which takes the request.
And queries the Android Calendar provider.
Describe at this link, to load the
designated events
from an SQLA database and display them to
the user.
The loader thread is created and launched
in the Start Background Thread method.
For example, the Event loaders load events
in background method, sends a
load request to the loader thread by the
linked blocking used Quick Method.
Likewise, the loader threads run method
blocks a
link blocking queues Take method, waiting
for newer quests.
When the loader thread receives a request,
it calls processed request.
This method triggers a series of method
calls, that ultimately query the Android
calendar provider.
To load the requested events from a
database on the device.
Query can be a long running call, so it
should be done in a background
thread to avoid blocking the user
interface
thread and triggering an application not
responding exception.
When the query is done, the process
request method posts a runable call back
to the user interface thread, which
formats
and displays the calendar events to the
user.
The next module in the section will
explain how android concurrency frame
rates can post runnables from background
threads to the use interface thread.
In the meantime this link provides an
overview of
the Android application threading model
that explains how post works.
So you might want to read this material
to prepare for our discussion in an
upcoming video.
[MUSIC]
In summary, Android applies the monitor
object pattern directly or indirectly to
many of its class libraries and frameworks
that are accessed concurrently by
multiple threads; including the A-synch
task
framework and various blocking queues and
decks, and thread pool executor
implementations
provided by the Java Util Concurrent
package.
Describe at this link.
In general, android implements monitor
objects via the Java.util.concurrency
mechanisms, rather
than the synchronize methods provided by
java built in monitor objects.
Thee mechanisms enable developers of
monitor objects more fine grained
serialization
and provide greater flexibility and
capabilities
than Java's built in monitor objects.
The key point, however, is that knowledge
of
the monitor object pattern guided the
design and implementation
of these Android software component,
regardless of whether they
used the built-in or user defined monitor
object mechanisms.
[MUSIC]