We're going to begin by taking a look
at the vulnerabilities in the Create Story
activity.
Now, this, this application has a number
of issues, and one of the
ones that we saw, from the Vulnerability
Checker application was that we could.
Obtain the location of the device without
ever
having the, the location permissions that
we would need.
We could get find location for a device
without having
any of the associated permissions in the
Vulnerability Checker app.
So if you open up the create story
activity, which
is the edu.vum.mocha.ui package and then
find the set location method.
The [UNKNOWN] where the actual
vulnerability
is that's allowing the Vulnerability
Checker app.
To obtain the location of the device
without having the associated permission.
And the way that this is happening is that
the iRemember app is logging the location
that it's receiving whenever the location
is updated in the create story activity.
So.
This line right here is related to the
vulnerability disclosures that were linked
in the assignment description.
And that is, whenever you log data on
certain versions of Android, it's possible
for other apps
to read the log files that are being
created by simply asking for permission to
read logs.
Now, on Android 4.1 and above, this has
been changed.
So, you can no longer ask for permission
to read
the log files, for an arbitrary other
application or at all.
Only system apps that are pre-installed by
the OEM or by
Google, can actually go and obtain this
permission to read logs.
But previously, and on older versions of
Android, it
is possible to read the logs of a device.
And in this case, when the location is
updated, in the set location method.
The first thing it does is logs that
location.
And this might be a helpful thing for
developer to try to see
that this method is actually being called,
or understands the information related to.
Where the device is.
What data's coming in.
Why a particular bug is present or isn't
present.
But these types of log messages,
particularly in
this case, can potentially, you know,
expose sensitive information.
In this case, another app is able to get
access to the location of the device.
Without ever actually having their
associated permission.
So this is a case where we're.
Using logging to accidentally allow a
privilege escalation and something,
some order app to get access to data that
it shouldn't have access to.
Now, if you wanted to go and fix this,
this wasn't one of the requirements for
the assignment.
But the easiest way to fix this, is just
to command this line out.
If this line isn't there, it's not
possible.
And preferably you don't have this line at
all where you have some type of field
process that automatically removes the
logging statements so
that you don't accidentally expose some
other data.
So, you know, location isn't the only
thing you need to worry about logging.
You shouldn't be logging.
Yeah.
Usernames, or, contact information.
Or anything else that you could get with
a, with a, permission.
So, be careful and [UNKNOWN] when you're
logging data in some type of application.
The
sound record activity also has, or also
participates, in a privilege escalation.
So if you'll open up the sound record
activity in
the same package and then look for the
onCreate method.
We'll all be look at the chain of events
that lead to this privilege escalation.
So one of the first things that we see in
the onCreate method.
Is that the activity actually extracts a
file name that it's going
to later use from an intent; so whoever
starts this activity can
send in an intent with a file name extra
that it will
then read out of that intent when it goes
to start up.
Now the reason this is important is later
on
what we're going to see is that the same
file name,
which is declared at the top of the file
in the activity gets used in a number of
places.
In particular, we see down here in the
start plain.
Method, which is going to actually go and
read and play the, some file that's been
recorded.
It's using that file name.
So that means that we're going to be
saving something to the m file name.
If we scroll a little farther down and we
see start recording.
Here's where the problem starts to emerge.
This sound record activity.
Creates a media recorder, and then begins
grabbing the audio from the
device, and saving it to whatever file
name was provided in the intent.
So in this case, the caller can specify a
file,
where they want all of this audio to be
saved.
And that file can be a file that this app
has control
over, or it can be a file that just
happens to be.
World readable.
Or that this app can write to.
And some other app can potentially read
from.
So you can imagine another app could
potentially,
if they could get access to the sound
record
activity, provide a file name that the
sound
recording activity should go and record
some sound to.
Now the key question is how would another
app get access
to this sound record activity if it lives
inside of another app.
That isn't that app's own.
So in this case the sound record activity
is
declared in the Android manifest for the
iRemember app.
So down here at the bottom of the Android
manifest for this project, which you'll
see in the.
Eclipse project.
And, this is where the sound record
activity
is declared, and one of the interesting
things
that we see, is that this activity doesn't
specify, a value for the Android app
exported.
So, we can say, and add the attribute.
Exported.
And if we say true, then this activity is
accessible by any other activity or app on
a device.
They can send an intent to it to start it.
If we set.
Exported to false.
Then components of other applications that
aren't in
this app cannot send invest to this
activity.
Exported means that no one else should be
able to talk to this activity.
But, in this case we see something
interesting and
that's there's no value present at all for
Export.
We do see, however, that there's an intent
filter.
And this leads to one tricky issue, and
that
is, if you don't specify a value for
exported.
If you don't have the Android exported
tag, or attribute on the activity tag.
Then the default value is dependent upon
whether
or not the activity has any intent
filters.
So, if the activity has an intent filter,
than exported defaults to true.
In which case other apps, or components of
other apps can send intents to this
activity.
If it has an intent it doesn't have an
intent folders then it defaults to false.
In which case other apps or components of
those other apps cannot send intents to
it.
So in this case because we don't
explicitly set.
Android exported the false.
And we have an intent filter.
It means that, the default value for
exported in this case is true.
And this activity has exported.
So, what we have here, is the equivalence,
of having Android exported.
True, so that is what this, whether or not
we specify export it doesn't matter
because since we haven't specified it and
we have an intent filter,it defaults to
true.
Now there's a number of ways that we can
fix this.
One is if we had the Sound Record
Activity not take this [INAUDIBLE] file
name that's it
going to record audio to it as parameter
that would
be helpful as we always recorded to a
file.
That was under the control of this app.
But that may not always make sense.
And, since we might want to have the
capability of allowing other apps or
activities or
some other caller to specify where the
file
name is that we should store the audio to.
We should still have a way of providing
that capability but protecting in some
way.
One way that we could protect it is if we
knew that we only wanted the
app, the activity to be called internally,
would
be to add the Android exported equals
false attribute.
So this would guarantee that the activity
wasn't called.
And we could remove this intent filter
which isn't actually used.
Even if we didn't spend, specify Android
exported equals false
and we just removed the ten, intent
filter, that would
also plug the vulnerability or plug the
leak that we
have from the Vulnerability Checker being
able to record sound through.
And this app.
However, it would probably be ideal to
have Android exported
false, regardless of whether or not we
remove the intent filter.
Another way that might be even a, a more
powerful mechanism particularly if we did
want to expose this sounder activity to
other apps and the components of other
apps.
Would be to add a permission that's
required.
So in this case, we could say that we're
going to require the same permissions that
we require.
So in this case, we're requiring the
record
audio permission in order to make this
possible.
So we could require that callers of the
sound record activity also have the record
audio permission.
So this would probably be the most full
proof way to do it.
As if we wanted to not only not export it
but also require that whoever calls it has
record audio but.
It probably an other, great way to do it
would be simply to add the record audio
permission.
So, if a caller has record audio
permission, then they can call
you and tell you to record the file,
wherever you, they want.
Because, they already have that capability
themselves.
They already have that privilege
themselves, it doesn't matter.
You are not exposing or creating a
privilege escalation.
If they go off and do something
inappropriate with that data.
It's their fault and not your fault at
that point.
You could also, of course, not have this
and have Android export equals false if
you do
not ever intend for this activity to be
called by an external component of some
other app.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Now if we go back to the sound record
activity some people may ask well isn't
the real problem that we're accepting in
file
name in the onCreate method from another
intent?
Shouldn't we remove this line here?
And that's not really the root of the
problem in this case.
It's certainly part of what's happening,
and part of the problem,
and part of the, one of the links in the
chain, but
the fact that this activity in and of it's
self, accepts
a file name to save some audio file to, is
not necessarily.
A security issue.
It might be good if the app somehow
checked that
file, and whether or not it was
appropriate to save audio
there, but it's, it's not really that
app's job if
the caller is making the decision on where
to save it.
But what is that app's job is to make
sure if it is recording audio and it is
allowing
somebody else to get access to it, that it
does
protect it with the appropriate
permission, in this case requiring.
Whoever the caller is, to also have the
record audio permission.
The next vulnerability that we're going to
look at, is in the log-in activity class.
If you'll open this class and then look at
the
getLoginID method, and the getLogin file
method, which is just above.
The, get log-in ID method.
We can see one of the vulnerabilities
that's happening.
So, first off this app is storing a user
name and password
on disc, which is really a bad idea in an
app altogether.
Now the reason for this is, is that.
If you store something on the file system,
then you have to be protected in some way.
In this case, you know, you would prefer
to see this app encrypting that data so
that
if somebody obtained physical access to
the device
or obtained access to the device in some
way.
That attacker couldn't simply read the
password for that user out of that file.
And interpret it.
You would like that file to be encrypted.
But, that of itself isn't necessarily a
security vulnerability for this app.
Yes, it's a bad practice, and something
that should not be done.
But it still requires somebody probably
getting physical access
to the device, in order to read that
password off.
Now, do I think that it is a good
idea that this app is storing password in
plain text?
Absolutely not.
It should be removed if possible.
Absolutely it should be removed.
You shouldn't do that.
But for this assignment, really what we
wanted to point out,
was that we wanted to have some data that
was so obvious.
And clearly something that other apps
shouldn't get access to, to try
to illustrate another type of
vulnerability that was taking place.
In this case, what we see is that when we
ask for getLoginId, we are getting the
login file to get that actual place where
that,
that file is stored with the username and
password.
And if we go to the getLoginFile method,
what
we'll see is that we're using this
StorageUtilities class.
To get the output media file or
essentially
where we're going to be storing the
username and password.
And we're passing a number of different
values into this get output media file.
One of them that's a little suspicious is
this max security value.
So let's take a look at the storage
utilities,
get output media file method, and see
what's actually happening.
Well we see that we're passing in a
context a type of file,
the security level that should be applied,
and then the name of the file.
And if we go back to the login activity,
we'll see that we have the context.
We have the type of file, that we're
saving some text.
We have a security level, max security.
And then we have login.text, which is the
name of the file that we're storing.
And if we go down below, what we see is
that if the security level is
private, we're going to store it in the
app's private data storage.
Otherwise.
We're going to store it and one of many
other places in which case
all of the other places that we might
store happened to be on the external
storage directory which before Android 4.4
was a publicly readable and location.
So in this case unless we explicitly set
security to private we're
going to store on the external storage
which could be read by another app.
Now in this case, what we see is we're
passing in max security.
Which, if you see this number over here,
you
can see, is actually set to the maximum
integer value.
Now the question is, what does security
private equal?
Well, if we mouse over the red, we see
security private.
Is actually equal to 1.
So this is a vulnerability because what
we're doing is
we're passing in an inappropriate value
for the security level.
Which is causing this login data to be
stored in a world readable location on
external storage.
So on, under Android 4.4 it would be
possible for another app to
read this app's login data because it's
accidentally storing it on the external
storage directory.
So in this case what we have is an issue
where
the get login file method and the login
activity is inappropriately using.
The get, getoutputmedia file, method or,
inappropriate using, inappropriately using
the API.
That's exposed by storage utilities.
By passing in max security.
As a value.
So, because there wasn't a bound, on what
you could
provide, for that integer and because only
certain values made sense.
In this case, whoever wrote the getlogin
file method, made a mistake.
Was passing an incorrect value, and
because of that, this line has created
a security vulnerability, that is this
line is inappropriately using
another API causing information that
should be private always, to leak on
to the external storage, where other apps
can get access to it.
This app shouldn't be storing passwords in
the first place.
But that in and of itself is not the key
issue here.
The k, the number one issue that needs to
be fixed is
that this app is storing that sensitive
data in a location that's inappropriate.
The next security issue is related to the
one that we just saw with login activity.
And what we saw with login activity was
that the user
of the storage utilities API was using the
storage utilities API inappropriately.
Causing some data to be leaked.
So one of the security or stylistic issues
that we have going on in storage
utilities.
That we would like to fix is the fact that
it's so easy to make a mistake and
accidentally have the wrong security
applied to the data
that's being stored, and in essence
suddenly start leaking data.
So let's start by taking a look at these
flags that are being used.
To determine the security level of where
files get stored.
The
first thing we see is we're using
integers.
So as we saw before, when we use the
integer, the login activity was able
to pass in a value that we hadn't
explicitly come up with a, a
interpretation of.
So in this case, because our value was max
integer value and we hadn't defined that.
The fact that we're using integer as
the type to specify these flags was
problematic.
It made it easier for the caller to make a
mistake.
The second issue that we're going to see.
Is that here we're defining the default
value.
The default security level to be 0, which
is security public.
Now when I say default value.
If you initialize an integer, by default
it's going to be 0.
So if a caller.
Provided an uninitialized value to the
method.
We're going to see in a second, it's going
to default to security public.
Now, if we scroll down and we get look at
the get output media file method, we see
that security is being passed in and then
clearly
their expecting one of those integers
above to be used.
But it's very easy that the caller could
provide the wrong integer value as we saw.
And if they do provide the wrong integer
value and
they provide something that has not
explicitly had a value defined.
Then what we see is down here in this
conditional logic.
That unless they explicitly say security
private, the default
is going to be to store it as insecure.
It's going to be to store it in external
files where anybody can read it.
So in this case, it's a security
vulnerability here that
the default branch of this L statement is
driven by.
A value being correctly value.
So unless you correctly provide a value
for the security.
It's going to default to this else branch
and store things on the external storage
directory.
What we would really like is for the
default to be security private.
But in this case, that's not the default.
Security private only works if.
We explicitly set a value for it.
So one way to do this, to fix this would
be to swap
these out so we could say move these
values up here, then
move the private down here and we make
this.
Security public and we'll reformat that.
So now what we say is unless you
explicitly set the value to be
public, then we're going to by default
store it in the public storage directory.
And this would plug this hole and provide
a better experience for.
Users.
Now you are required to fix this as a part
of your assignment
but a much better way of structuring this
would be a make it so
that unless the explicitly say that they
want to public in know what
the value is to make it public that you're
going to make it private.
Similarly at the top in order to also make
sure that this works.
By default we would like to move this and
make so that private is 0 and public is 1.
This way ideally if they don't provide a
value for the security.
If they don't, use an uninitialized
variable it will default to private.
Now it would be much better rather than
using integers to use a enom of some type.
I'm not going to walk through the full
solution for that.
It's fairly simple to do.
You could declare a enom with two
different values to secure
your private and security public, and then
require that, that enom be
passed down later.
So how do we go about fixing the
vulnerability in the login activity?
The first thing that we need to do and
the only thing that's needed in order to
plug the
leak that the Vulnerability Checker is
exploiting is to make
sure that we provide a correct value for
the security.
So in this case we switch from our max
security that we arbitrarily came up with.
To an actual value for security that's
defined by the API.
In this case, StorageUtilities.security
private.
And doing this alone is a valid solution
to the
assignment that will plug particularly
with the Vulnerability Checker issues.
Ideally though you really wouldn't like to
store passwords.
So, an enhancement that we could do that's
not required for a valid solution, but
would be much better practice is to
rel, eliminate, the storage of the
plain-text password.
So in this case, there aren't any other
activities
that actually depend upon the password
being in this file.
So we can simply remove.
The line, appropriate lines from the login
collect.
We can remove the appropriate lines from
any applications where we're relying on
it.
And actually, in this case it's only one
other place we can remove the get
password,
method completely, because as you'll see
when we
remove this, no other activities depend
upon it.
And we don't depend upon it ourselves.
So we can completely eliminate this
un-needed password, that we
happen to be storing for some reason in
this file.
And we've significantly improved our
security.
We still also provided backwards
capability, compatibility, with all of the
other all of the other activities, that
may depend upon it.
There's some other activities, that depend
on this get login ID.
Method.
But, we're not storing a password with it.
We're just storing a login idea.
Now if you really wanted to be paranoid
and, and try to improve the
security even more, you could not even
store the login ID on the file system.
And instead you could have this method
since it's
a static method and the caller always
provides a context.
You could potentially have this method,
pop-up a dialogue of some sort.
To actually prompt the user for their
log-in ID, every time this method was
called.
Or, you could use a log-in ID and have it
stored on disk, like we're doing here.
But, remove the password, as we did, below
by.
Commenting out these lines.
And then removing the get password method.
Those would be better ways of solving the
issue by completely eliminating the
password from the file.
But either way, we, we need to make sure
that this file is stored privately.
Because even if we're just storing the
login ID, that's
really not something that we should be
saving on the file.
Somewhere where that file is publicly
readable and
letting any app get access to the login
ID.
It's, it's okay, potentially, to store
that data because if
an attacker did steal the phone and did
get the login
id, they still wouldn't have the password,
where as if
we're storing both, they could have access
to both of them.
But either way, we need to make sure apps,
other apps, can't get access to this
file, which is clearly something that is
suppose
to be private and internal to this
iRemember app.
To recap, the vulnerabilities that we were
looking for to be identified.
The first one is at the Android manifest,
at line 56.
The intent filter here that's being added
without an.
Corresponding explicit values set for
Android and exported.
Causes this activity to be exported.
And because of that another app can access
the sound report activity.
The second vulnerability was on line 382
of the create story activity.
And this is where we are logging the
location of the device to.
The log, and another app on certain
versions of Android, could
potentially read that location causing a
yet again, another privilege escalation.
In login activity, on line 48, there is a
inappropriate usage of the storage
utilities get output media file.
API by providing max val, max security as
the value.
Which isn't defined.
And causes this file to be stored on
external storage, where it's accessible.
And then the final two lines of
vulnerabilities were the fact
that, and it's not actually a
vulnerability, more of a stylistic
problem.
That's causing the APIs or storage
utilities to be used inappropriately.
Is it on line-24.
We're setting the default value to public
for the security.
And then lower down in the get output
media
file method on line 76, we're making the
default branch.
Be to store the data that's provided on
external
storage directory where some other app can
potentially read it.
We're not making the default be secure.
So those were the key vulnerabilities that
should have been
identified in the quiz for the first part
of the assignment.
Now that we've gone through all of the
vulnerabilities that needed to be
discovered in this app, let's talk about
the peer grading aspect of this
assignment.
And how to assess whether or not somebody
has fixed the vulnerabilities in
the login activity and the Android
manifest
file that we needed to have fixed.
In the login activity, there are a couple
different ways that you could fix this
vulnerability.
One is as we've done here, to swap from
max security,
to the appropriate flag which would be
storage utilities dot security private.
If the code that the person is using is
storing anything on disk.
Then that data should be stored in private
storage.
Now there is a couple of ways you can
written this, rewritten this method.
You could have rewritten this to use the
appropriate flag and in this case security
private.
If somebody rewrote this to automatically
themselves directly decide the data.
The private data directory of the app and
return
a file in that, that would also
potentially be okay.
That's fine if the person is not using the
storage utility API at all because
they say it's broken, they're instead
going to
provide an appropriate file to store
things to.
Or if the person uses security private.
To fix things.
That's also a valid solution.
Another valid solution, if they do the
work to make things compile properly,
is to completely eliminate the storage of
the log-in information in the file.
So if you went.
And eliminated all of the, places where
they're storing this data in the file.
And then eliminate the places where there
are reading
this out to instead obtain the values some
other way.
That would also be a legitimate, approach
to fixing this.
So you could change get login id to prompt
the user with some kind of gooey.
To get their login ID and similarly you
could
change if they get getPassword method is
still there.
You could change that to prompt the person
to appropriately provide their password
when its needed.
So any, any solution that either switches
the storage
to be private, most people will probably
have taken an.
Switched max security to something like
storageutilities.securityprivate.
However, if you also went and directly
create and or obtain
a file, it's within the apps' private
storage, that's also fine.
It's also okay if you completely eliminate
the
storage of the ID and the password on
disk.
And provide some appropriate mechanism to
prevent the dependence of,
on the login ID method and the if
getPassword method,
[UNKNOWN] anybody that was actually
dependent upon that method to still
work properly but remove the storage on,
on the file.
The password, the login ID, that also is
appropriate.
However.
If you are storing something on the file,
you must
have either security private, or a file
looked up and returned.
That is in private data directory, of the
app.
Just change in the name of the file is not
sufficient.
If that file is still on the external
storage directory, or is world readable.
Just.
Removing the, storage of the username and
password, if
it causes compilation errors and other
parts of the app.
Or causes a crash, somewhere else in the
app.
That also is an insufficient solution.
So, what you want to look for, is either
if they are storing things on a file.
That they are doing it in a way, that
still makes sure that file is stored in
the private.
A storage of that app and not accessible
to other apps.
Or, if they're not doing that, and they're
getting rid of the file entirely.
That the app still compiles and works
correctly because either they're providing
some alternate method for getting the
login ID, and getting the password.
Or they come up with some other solution
that can eliminate those things
and still allow the rest of the app to
compile and function correctly.
For the second vulnerability that needed
to be fixed.
In this case with the sound recorder
activity.
What you want to look for is that where
the sound record activity is declared.
That the person has done one of a couple
of things.
One valid solution is to add the
RECORD_AUDIO permission to that
activity so that all callers have to have
the RECORD_AUDIO permission.
And that will stop.
[UNKNOWN] Any potential privilege
escalation.
Another potential solution would be just
to
eliminate the intent filter from the
activity.
So that it's not exported.
Now, the only challenge with solution.
It is a valid solution and should be
counted peer review as being correct.
The only challenge with this solution is
down the road if somebody decides to add
an intent filter back to this activity,
and they don't understand how Android
Exporter works.
They could potentially introduce that
vulnerability again.
And then a third valid way of fixing
things is to add.
Exported equals false to this activity so
that
it's not accessible by external callers at
all.
So those are the three different ways that
somebody could potentially fix
that privilege escalation that's traveling
through the sound record activity.
And any of those.
Ways of fixing it should all be counted as
correct within the peer grade.