[MUSIC]
So welcome to the next class.
What we're going to be covering today is a
continuation of the discussion of the
Android Interface
Definition Language, and we're going to
talk about some
of the syntax and supported data types
first.
And then we're going to go in some more
detail how you implement AIDL interfaces.
Looking at the internals, what's generated
by
the AIDL compiler, and then we'll look at
some examples illustrating how to use AIDL
and
the binder for both synchronous and
asynchronous communication.
So first let's start by talking about the
supported data types.
So we're going to discuss the syntax for
the Android interface definition language.
And sort of the way in which it's, it
supports
various kinds of data types that you
define in Java.
So, AIDL allows application developers to
declare
their business logic methods, using a
Java-like, syntax.
So, the key thing here is Java-like.
If you know Java interfaces,
then understanding AIDL is very
straightforward.
But be aware, as we'll see in a second,
that not everything that
you get in a Java interface is going to
show up in AIDL.
There's a number of restrictions, which
are good things to know.
So here's a very simple example, this
comes
out of the Android source code; there's
something in
there called the, the drop box manager
service or
the iDrop box manager service, I standing
for interface.
And as you can see there you can go ahead
and add an entry, which is a drop box
manager entry.
And you can go ahead and then get the next
entry.
You could iterate through this thing one
thing at a time
getting back the entries that are in a
drop box entry.
So you can imagine that, that's probably
used
internally by Android to allow you to
access your
drop box content from your Android phone
which is
a very useful thing to be able to do.
So here are things that are similar with,
with the Java interfaces.
So if you know Java then you know that
it's possible to define
interfaces to have methods that have typed
parameters and optionally a return value.
You could also have a void to not return
anything but
it's common to have a return value of some
kind as well.
So, pretty much everything you know about
Java interfaces will apply to AIDL.
With a few key exceptions.
So here are some of the differences.
You cannot define any static fields in
AIDL
interfaces, whereas you can do that in
Java interfaces.
Any non primitive parameters, in other
words things
that aren't in float, double, things like
that.
They have to be defined indicating the
direction in which the parameter is being
passed.
And the three directions are, in, which is
the default for
for primitives and the only way to do it
for primitives,
and what that says is that the data will
be copied
from the caller over to the address space
of the receiver.
So that's what in means.
Out means the opposite, it means that the
data will be copied from
the receiver and returned as a so-called
out parameter back to the caller.
And then finally inout.
Which is, you pass an in and you get a
result back.
I looked through all of Android and I
could find no examples of
where anything in Android used the inout
parameter passing mode in terms of
direction.
So it's not very common.
The most common things are in.
There's somethings that use out, and it's
important to
remember to do this because when you start
trying
to pass data between the address spaces,
then you
want to limit the amount of data that's
passed.
So when you say in, it only goes with the
request, it doesn't go with the response.
When you say out, it only comes back with
a response and doesn't, nothing goes over
with the request.
So that's why they typically do this.
And this is also characteristic of other
interface definition languages.
Thinks like Corba or Microsoft's IDL they
use for Comm and decomm.
So this is a very common thing to do.
Another set of things that are different,
is that you can have one way methods.
So unlike a regular Java interface where
you invoke a
method and it basically returns something,
which could be void.
with, with, but it, but the point is when
you invoke
that method it's going to block until the
method call is done.
Whether it returns anything or not, the
caller is blocked
for the duration of the call in a normal
Java interface.
With android and AIDL however you can
designate methods as being one way.
And one way means that you invoke it, its
copied from the
callers address space down into the
operating system, and then the call
returns
right away, it doesnt wait until the call
goes over to the receiver
side, is turned back into a method call,
is processed and so on.
So that means that they're going to return
much more quickly.
And we're going to use this one way
capability
later when we start talking about
asynchronous mechanisms.
How you can use asynchronous communication
and AIDL by using
one way, wha, by using a pair of one-way
methods.
So one-way methods don't block the caller.
Another thing, methods can't throw
exceptions.
Which is kind of an unusual thing, but
that's
just one of the things that they, they do.
You, you can't, you can't throw the
exceptions yourself.
They don't propagate those through the
call.
That's something that's ki, kind of
strange.
I don't know why they, they do that.
In languages like, like CorbaIDL, you can
in
fact throw exceptions, and they get
propagated back.
And then another thing that you can't do
in AIDL, that you can
do in regular Java, you can't
have interfaces that inherit from other
interfaces.
So you have to do some other thing, in
order to to make them composed together in
some way.
There's a number of different, primitive
operations that are supported, as
parameters, or return values, from AIDL,
or AIDL methods in Android.
The typical things you'd expect, right?
So bool, array of bool, byte, int and
array of int.
Long, array of long.
Character, array of character.
float, array of float.
Double, array of double, et cetera.
Those are all the kinds of things you can
pass back and forth.
You can also return character sequences
and strings as well.
And just poking around an Android for a
few
minutes, just to look and see what was out
there.
There's something that's called the
interface for the email service.
As you can see here, you can create
folders, you can delete folders, you can
rename folders.
And that allows you to pass in, basically
account IDs, and names of things.
The account ID being a long, the string
being used as the name.
So there's some examples of how you're
passing primitives are
around, very straightforward, not that
much different from normal java
programming.
You can also pass around lists, so there's
this thing called java.utilList and
internally it uses the
Java.utilArrayList as the implementation,
the mapping of the
IDL list abstraction is this underlying
Java list abstraction.
And you can support generic lists.
Here's an example of an interface that,
that's defined
in, in parts of Android where you could
have
this thing that would go and lookup what
network
interfaces are available, and you could do
this, this query.
And when the query's complete, you get
back this list of or sorry.
You, you go ahead and get back a list of
things that
have completed, which tell you what
operators are connected to the network.
So there's an example of where you're
getting back a
list of something, in this case a list of
operator info.
So that's how you can use those kinds of
things.
There's also something called, a map,
which under
the hood, maps to the underlying Java hash
map.
They don't support generic maps, you have
to give it a type.
Unlike lists, where you can support
generic lists.
And when I looked through the Android
source code,
I couldn't find any examples of maps being
used.
So I guess it's kind of sort of a science
fiction-like thing.
Or maybe it's a map of a, a fantasy place
that doesn't really exist.
Like the Shire, or Mordor or something
like that.
So they don't really have a lot of use of
maps,
but they're available if you, if you tend
to use them.
I think people tend to use parcels and
parcellables instead for various things.
That's the next topic.
So you can actually define your own data
types and have them passable back
and forth as parameters or return values
from methods defined in AIDL interfaces.
And the way that you do this is kind of
interesting.
So, you define your own class.
Like, this is one I got out of Android for
the status bar.
Icons.
There's something called a status bar icon
which implements personable.
And you as the implementor of that class
are
obliged to fill in a number of hook
methods.
Like, read from parcel, write to parcel,
and so on.
And at the appropriate times, as this
android is doing its thing, it'll
end up invoking those methods in the stub
or in the proxy in
order to get the, the state of the
particular instance of this thing,
and then pass that back and forth under
the hood as a parcel.
[COUGH] And you can see down here, here an
example of how we would this, we would
say.
Here's an interface called istatusbar;
which
is actually a real interface in Android.
And you can have parcelable StatusBarIcon
that just say hey, this, this
guy is being defined as a user defined
type; with parcelable properties.
This, read from parcel and write to parcel
hook methods that are defined.
And then here's a method called setIcon
that takes in a StatusBarIcon as a
parameter.
So, it's pretty open-ended; you can go
ahead and add
these things as you see fit to Android,
and it, it
makes it easier for you to define types
that can
be used with the overall IDL AIDL
mechanisms that Android supports.
Any questions about that?
>> Yeah?
>> Why is there no direction for the
primitives, so like, INT indexes and that
thing.
>> Because in in Java, these things are
going to be passed by value.
>> Okay.
>> So you, you can't get the result back.
Because they don't have the, Java doesn't
have the same thing you do in
C or C++ where you could take the address
of or pass a reference.
That's why.
So, as you can see here status bar icon is
a, is a Java source file
this other thing is an AIDL source file,
and so you can make those work together.
There's a description that you can find on
the
Android webpage that talks more about how
you pass
objects, and it goes through and shows you
an
example of how to do this kind of thing.
So to summarize this particular discussion
AIDL, Android
Interface Definition Language, is a
relatively simple syntax.
It's, it's a subset of the full blown Java
interface syntax, and it lets
you define interfaces and then define
methods
that take parameters and return values,
optionally.
As we talked about before there, there's a
subset of things
you can do that you can't do all the full
blown stuff.
The parameters and return values can be
any
of the supported types we just talked
about.
And, you can even have interface
parameters passed.
And we'll see this later when we
start to talk about asynchronous
interfaces in AIDL.
What you can do is you can essentially
create objects
that live in a client that are instances,
or implementations,
of interfaces, and then you can pass the
references to
those things as parameters, or return
values, to other AIDL methods.
And this gives you the very powerful
ability to be able to
pass essentially objects using factories
or other gang of four style patterns.
And the receivers, when they get those
interfaces, can then make method calls on
them.
So you can essentially pass remote object
references around and
access them from other processes in other
parts of the system.
And we'll see a bunch of examples on how
that works.
Basically what you end up doing is you end
up creating this AIDL file using your
favorite editor.
Typically you'd end up using either the
IDE editor environment that you have in
Eclipse
or, or your own editor that you may choose
like Emacs or VI, or what not.
And the thing you always have to remember
is that each interface goes into a
separate file.
So here's a file that has that iDownload
interface.
Here's a file that has iDownload callback
Those have to be defined in separate
files.
And that, that gets a little bit
squirrel-y and confusing at times.
You'd like to be able to glum them all
together
but they don't' support that kind of
combination of, of interfaces.
You have to do them one per file.
And that means you, you'll, as you'll see
in a
minute when we look at some of the
examples, you
have to do a little bit of other syntactic
sugar,
to, to make sure that the files know about
each other.
That they understand, for example, in this
particular case, notice
how the iDownload interface, uses
a reference to the iDownloadCallback
interface.
And so we would have to basically import
the iDownload call back interface into
this file so it would be visible to be
usable by the underlying system.
And I think they just did this to make it
easier to write the compiler honestly.
There's no need to do it.
Other languages give you more powerful
ways of
being able to deal with multiple
interfaces per file.
[MUSIC]