[MUSIC].
Welcome to the first part of the module on
Java concurrency mechanisms.
In this part we present an overview of the
Java
mechanisms available on Android to
implement concurrent software via
multi-threading.
Android supports many standard
Java concurrency and synchronization
mechanisms.
We covered Java threads in the first
several parts of this module.
And then covered the core Java
synchronization mechanisms in the later
parts.
If you're already familiar with Java
threading, you
can skim through this video or skip it
altogether.
There are several ways to understand Java
threads.
First, there's a conceptual view, where
Java threads are units of computation that
can run simultaneously within a process,
which
is ultimately a Linux process on Android.
These threads can communicate with each
other via shared objects or message
passing.
Second, there's an implementation view.
Where each Java thread has a stack,
a program counter, and other registers,
which
comprise state that's unique to each
thread, as well as heap and static areas.
Which comprise state that's shared by all
threads within a process.
[MUSIC].
Now that I've given a brief overview of
Java
threads, let's show how to program threads
in Android.
All Java threads must be given some code
to run.
Which is typically done in one of two
ways.
One way is to extend the thread class and
override its run hook method.
As shown in the code snippet on
this slide, where my thread inherits from
thread.
And defines a run method that's invoked
automatically when my thread is started.
Another way is to implement the runnable
interface and override its run hook
method.
There's several ways to implement the
runnable interface.
The approach shown in this slide defines a
named runnable implementation,
passes it to an anonymous thread object,
then calls its start method.
Which instructs the Java virtual machine
to create the resources
needed to run the thread, and invokes its
run hook method.
Alternatively, the approach shown on this
slide, defines and starts
a thread, using an anonymous inner class
as the runnable.
Which is a common idiom used throughout
Android.
This link compares and contrasts these
various approaches.
Regardless of how a thread is created, the
Java virtual machine, known as Dalvic on
Android, creates
the threads, resources and invokes its run
hook method
when another thread calls start on the
thread instance.
That run method can execute concurrently
with
respect to other computations in other
threads.
It can call blocking IO operations on
network connections and
files, receive messages from a looper and
process them, et cetera.
You can generally run any code in a
thread.
Though Android restrict GUI operations to
the user interface thread.
A thread can execute as long as it's run
hook method hasn't returned.
Though the Android Linux thread scheduler
can transparently suspend and
resume a thread many times through out
it's life cycle.
If a thread needs to run forever, it
requires
some sort of infinite loop that prevents
run from returning.
After the run hook method returns, the
thread
is no longer active and various things can
happen.
For example, another thread might have
called the thread's join method
to wait for it to complete, or the thread
could simply evaporate.
The Java virtual machine reclaims and
recycles the thread's resources once its
complete.
While allowing other threads in the
program to continue running.
[MUSIC]
the Java thread class has dozens of
methods that are documented in this link.
We've covered some of the most important
methods already.
For example, the start method initiates
thread execution.
Join waits for a thread to finish, and run
is a hook method that executes user code.
Some other methods commonly used in
Android
software, and shown later in this mook,
include sleep, which causes a thread to
sleep for a given period of time.
Interrupt, which posts an interrupt
request to a
thread indicating that it should shut
itself down voluntarily.
And current thread, which returns the
thread object
associated with a currently executing
thread of control.
[MUSIC].
In summary, some concurrency mechanisms
supported by Android are based on standard
Java threading classes which provide a
programming model that's familiar to many
developers.
This link points to a tutorial on the
concurrency support
provided by the Java programming language
and its class libraries.
Android also supports powerful concurrency
mechanisms from the
Java util concurrent package documented at
this link.
For example, it's thread pull, executor
and future are
used in various parts of the Android
middleware itself.
Writing an Android programs using Java
threads has drawbacks however.
Since it's subtly different than writing
multi-threaded Java programs in other
environments.
For example, Android doesn't allow
background
Java threads to access the display, but
instead requires them to post runnables or
messages to the user interface threads
looper.
In practice therefore, many Android
applications
use the idiomatic concurrency frameworks
that are
described in this link and covered in the
next module in this section.
[MUSIC]