[MUSIC].
Welcome to the second part of the module,
on Java concurrency and mechanisms.
Now that we explored the basics of Java
concurrency in part one,
this part dwells deeper into the structure
and functionality of Java threads.
Even if you're already familiar with Java
threads, you may learn something from
this video, since we discuss various
thread
implementation aspects of the android
software stack.
A thread is a complex piece of software
that interacts with other hardware and
software entities.
To get a bird's eye view of these
interactions, the state machine on this
slide that
depicts the key states of the thread
during
its life cycle, which are documented in
this link.
Although you don't need all these details
to program Java threads effectively, we
will
walk through each state, to help you
better understand a thread's behavior and
interactions.
When a Java program creates a thread
object, it's initially in a new state.
After the program calls the start method
on the thread.
The state machine transitions to the
runnable state.
When the Android Linux, scheduler selects
the thread
to execute, it transitions to the running
state, at
which point the Java virtual machine
invokes its
run hook method to start executing user
provided code.
If this user calls sleep or other timed
operations, the state machines
transitions to the timed waiting for state
for the designated period of time.
When this wait time elapses the thread
becomes runable again.
After the thread scheduler starts running
the thread,
it might attempt to access a guarded
resource.
Such as the synchronize method or block,
protected by a lock, which will
transition the thread to the block state
if the lock is not available.
When the resource is obtained the thread
becomes runnable again.
After the thread scheduler starts running
the thread, it might wait on
a condition variable, causing the state
machine to transition to the waiting
state.
When another thread notifies this
condition
variable, the thread again becomes
runable.
Finally, when a thread's run method
returns, the thread is
terminated and its resources are released
by the Java virtual machine.
This link contains a UML state
chart visualizing and summarizing all
these states.
[MUSIC]
The two most fundamental phases of a Java
threads life cycle involves starting and
stopping it.
So we'll examine these phases in the
remainder of
this video, since they raise some
interesting implementation issues.
We'll start at the very beginning, which
is a very good place to start.
When start is called on the thread object,
the Java virtual machine allocates
the resources needed to execute the
thread, then calls its run hook method.
Many steps occur at the Java middleware,
virtual machine
and operating system layers to make all
this happen.
Again, you don't need to understand all
these
details to program Java threads
effectively, but the
following discussion will help you
appreciate what the
Android software stack is doing on your
program's behalf.
Moreover, the source files containing each
implementation step
are shown at the bottom of each slide.
When a program invokes the start method on
the thread object,
it's actually invoking the start method of
the underlying Java thread
class, which in turn, calls
the VMThread.creat native method, which
triggers
several calls to other Java native
interface and dalvic internal methods.
That ultimately invoke pthread_create,
which is a standard Posix function.
It interacts with the Linux kernel, to
create a runtime stack and other pthread
resources.
For brevity, we skip these kernel steps in
our analysis.
The InterpThreadStart function is passed
to pthread_create, which then invokes
this function, in the context of the newly
created thread.
Interp thread start, calls the dalvik
internal DVM call method, which
subsequently
invokes, the thread objects run hook
method to execute user define code.
Of course, all these Android
implementation details are subject to
change.
For example, this link contains a brief
summary of the new android run time
called art, that provided as an
experimental
option in the android 4.4 release, art
replaces
the register based interpreter and dalvik
with
a head of time processing which bit code
is recompiled in the machine language
where
an application is installed on an android
device.
[MUSIC].
Now that we've covered how threads get
started and run, let's
cover the other end of the lifecycle,
where we bid them farewell.
Stopping Java threads is surprisingly
hard.
Just like the classic animated film the
sorcerers apprentice, which shows how its
often easier to set things in motion, than
it is to shut them down.
In particular, other than returning from
run, there's no built
in safe method for involuntary stopping a
java thread in android.
The stop method has been deprecated, for
the reasons described at this link.
Therefore, if a thread performs long
duration operations.
Programmers should ensure it can stop
itself voluntarily.
One way to instruct a long duration
operation in a
thread to shut down, is to use a stop
flag.
The my runnable implementation on this
slide.
Contains a volatile Boolean flag called is
stopped, that's initially set to false.
The Java volatile type qualifier, enforces
a global ordering on reads and rights to a
variable, so it can be used correctly in
a multi-threaded program, as described at
this link.
My runnable also defines a stop me method,
that sets is stop to true.
Finally, the run method periodically
checks is stopped.
To see if the thread's been instructed to
stop itself, and returns if it has.
Although this solution is lightweight, it
isn't integrated into the Java virtual
machine.
Therefore, it won't wake up blocking
operations, such as reads, waits,
joins, sleeps, or interruptible locks,
which will impede the shutdown process.
[MUSIC].
Another way to stop a thread, is to use
the standard Java interrupt method, which
posts a request
to a thread, asking it to stop what it's
doing and do something else, as described
in this link.
For example, the main thread shown on this
slide creates and starts a new
thread T1, who's run hook method performs
several types of processing in a loop.
When the main thread wants T1 to stop, it
calls T1's interrupt method.
For the job of thread interruption
mechanism
to work correctly, code running and thread
T1.
Or a method called directly or indirectly
by code in T1, must
check if it has a pending
interrupt request and handle the request
accordingly.
There are two ways for a thread to check
and handle interrupt requests.
If a thread frequently calls blocking
methods such as wait, join, sleep
and lock interruptibly, as well as IO
operations on a interruptible channel.
These methods internally check if they've
been interrupted,
and if so, they automatically throw the
interrupted exception.
Which can be caught and handled in the
appropriate context.
Conversely, threads who computations don't
invoke methods that thread
interrupted exception, must periodically
call the thread interrupted method.
Which returns True if an interrupted
request has been received,
thereby allowing the program to return or
throw an interrupted exception.
Despite the name, Java thread interrupts
don't behave like traditional operating
system interrupts.
In particular, they aren't delivered
asynchronously and preemptively.
Instead, thread interrupt just sets an
internal flag, that must be
tested for explicitly by calls to thread
interrupted, which clears this flag.
This link examines the java thread
interruption mechanism in more detail.
Both solutions we examined for stopping
threads,
require the threads to cooperate, by
checking periodically
to see if they've been instructed to
stop and voluntarily shutting themselves
down if so.
Although this approach can be tedious to
program, it's the recommended way
of stopping threads in Java and Android,
as described at this link.
[MUSIC]
In
summary, Java threads are implemented
using various mechanisms provided
by the lower layers of the Android
software stack.
Although the implementation details of
Dalvik differ
a bit from other Java virtual machines,
the features of the Java threads in
Android should be familiar to experienced
Java developers.
This link provides more information on
Dalvik and summarizes
characteristics that differentiate it from
other standard Java virtual machines.
However, due to the programming
level similarities between Androids
implementation
of Java threads and other Java virtual
machines, you might consider
reading some good books on Java
concurrency, to learn the
key patterns and best practices of
programming multi threaded Java software.
These books will help you to master
creating, managing, and
using Java threads on a range of platforms
including Android.
[MUSIC]