[MUSIC].
Welcome to the next part of the
introduction section.
In this part we will continue our
discussion of
patterns and frameworks outlining how they
are used through our
Android to improve the structure and
functionality of the concurrency
and communication in middleware used by
its applications and services.
Androids concurrency and communications
frameworks.
An applications to these frameworks are
designed, implemented, and integrated
in accordance with many Gang of Four and
POSA patterns.
The most essential patterns used in
Android's frameworks appear in the POSA
books, which isn't surprising, since these
books document fundamental concurrency and
communication patterns.
For example, the monitor object
pattern synchronizes concurrent method
execution to
ensure that only one method at a time runs
within an object.
It also allows an object's methods to
cooperatively
schedule their execution sequences, as
described at this link.
Android applies this pattern to implement
the LinkedBlockingQueue class in the
java.util.concurrent package.
Which provides a synchronized list of link
nodes that enqueues
and dequeues elements in first in first
out or FIFO order.
The thread specific storage pattern allows
multiple threads to use one logically
global access point to retrieve an object
that's local to a thread.
Without incurring locking overhead on each
object access, as described at this link.
The Android looper class applies this
pattern
by using a Java ThreadLocal object, to
ensure only one looper is created per
thread, as described in these upcoming
videos.
The command processor pattern packages a
piece of application functionality as
well as its parameterization in an object
to execute it in another
context, such as a later point in time, in
a different
process, in a different thread, et cetera,
as described at this link.
The Android hammer framework applies this
pattern to
enable code in a background thread, to
post a
runnable command that's enqueued and
processed later in the
user interface thread, as described in
these upcoming videos.
Android also applies this pattern to it's
intent service, which handles asynchronous
requests, expressed as intents on demand
in a background thread of a service.
[MUSIC].
The active object pattern defines the
units of
concurrency on a component to be request
for service.
These service requests are processed in a
different thread then the
client thread that invoked the request, as
described at this link.
The Android hammer framework applies a
variant to
this pattern to enable a client in one
thread to send messages to a handler
running
in another thread, as covered in these
upcoming videos.
Android also applies this pattern by its
binder communication framework,
which uses messengers to enable message
based interactions across processes.
The Half-Sync, Half-Async pattern
decouples asynchronous and synchronous
service processing in concurrent systems
by introducing two layers.
One for asynchronous service processing
and one for synchronous service
processing.
These layers communicate via one or more
synchronized queues and simplify
concurrent programming without unduly
reducing
performance, as described at this link.
The Android AsyncTask framework applies
this pattern to allow one or
more background threads to block
synchronously while processing long
duration operations.
And then pass the results by a queue to
the user interface thread which
only performs short duration, non blocking
or
asynchronous operations, as discussed in
these upcoming videos.
The broker pattern connects clients with
remote
objects by mediating invocations from
clients to these
objects, while encapsulating the details
of the underlying
interprocess communication mechanisms, as
described at this link.
Android applies the broker pattern to
support object oriented remote
procedure calls between activities and
services running in different processes.
The broker pattern is actually a pattern
language.
It applies many other Gang of Four
and POSA patterns, as described in these
books.
[MUSIC].
Although the Gang of Four patterns don't
focus on concurrency and
communication per se, these patterns are
applied in many object oriented
frameworks.
Including the Android concurrency and
communication frameworks.
For example, the template method pattern
provides a skeleton of an algorithm
and a method deferring some steps as
subclasses as described at this link.
The Android HandlerThread class applies
this
pattern to allow subclasses to create
their
desired handlers by overriding the
onLooperPrepared hook
method as shown in this upcoming video.
The strategy pattern defines a family of
algorithms, encapsulates each one and
makes them
interchangeable, so that clients and
algorithms can
vary independently as described at this
link.
The Android AsyncTask framework applies
this pattern to configure which
type of executor is used to run async
tasks, which
can be serialized or run in the thread
pool, depending
on the designated strategy, as described
in this upcoming video.
The factory method pattern provides an
interface
for creating an object, but leaves a
choice at the objects concrete type to a
subclass as described at this link.
The THREAD_POOL_EXECUTOR class in the
Android AsyncTask
framework applies this pattern to
designate the
subclass of ThreadFactory used to create a
thread whose name encodes the unique
AsyncTask number.
Which serves as debugging aid as shown in
this upcoming video.
The frameworks in Android are built using
some of the Java concurrency
mechanisms in the java.util.concurrent and
java.util.concurrent_locks
packages covered in an upcoming section.
In addition to the patterns outlined
above, Androids concurrency and
communication frameworks and
the underlying Java mechanisms upon which
they
are built also apply many other patterns.
Such as monitor object, proxy, guarded
suspension, thread safe interface, future,
bridge, adapter and iterator as discussed
throughout this movie.
[MUSIC].
In summary Android applies many POSA and
Gang of Four patterns.
To help improve the structure and
functionality of it's concurrency and
communication
frameworks, as well as the applications
and services built using these frameworks.
These techniques, tools and methods codify
software design and architecture
best practices in the form
of systematically reusable implementation
artifacts.
Some of these patterns and frameworks
focus on Androids
middleware layers, whereas others focus on
writing applications and services.
Regardless of their scope these patterns
and frameworks help developers
in the Android platform be more productive
and write better
quality software, by allowing them to
focus on their business
logic at whatever layer of the Android
stack they deal with.
Rather than wrestling with low level
tedious
and error prone concurrency and
communication details.
A great deal of the success of the
Android platform stems from
it's pattern-oriented, framework-based
architecture.
Since Android is largely available as open
source, it's an ideal environment
for learning about and experimenting with
these powerful forms of systematic reuse.
I therefore strongly encourage you to
download
the Android source code available at this
link.
We'll analyze many examples from this code
base throughout the rest of this MOOC.
[MUSIC]