[MUSIC].
Hello, my name is Doug Schmitt.
And I'd like to welcome you to our MOOC on
programming mobile services for
Android handheld systems, which focuses on
a
range of Android application and
middleware programming topics.
Including threading and concurrency
control mechanisms, background
service processing, local inter-process
communication, and application security.
This is the second course in our
specialization on mobile cloud computing
with Android.
Which is the first trans-institutional
sequence of
MOOCs taught on the Coursera platform by
myself, Professor Adam Porter at
University of
Maryland, and Professor Jules White at
Vanderbilt University.
Before we delve into techniques, tools,
and methods associated
with the program and concurrent
applications and services on Android.
This section gives an overview of the
entire
specialization in general, and this MOOC
in particular.
We start by outlining how the MOOCs in our
specialization built upon
and codified decades of research and
development we've conducted together and
separately.
To provide you with an integrated learning
experience that blends coverage
of software design and architecture,
human computer interaction, accessibility
and useability.
Java programming language features and
idioms, communication and concurrency
patterns and
frameworks, database design and
programming techniques,
cyber security, automated testing and
more.
Next, I'll explain the course
organization, assignments and assessment
methods.
As well as outline the main topics in each
section.
Since teaching and taking MOOCs is
different from traditional face
to face courses, I'll also explain this
course's prerequisites and expectations.
As well as provide some tips on how to
leverage online resources to
master the material we cover in the
videos and successfully complete the
programming assignments.
Finally, I'll present an overview of
patterns and frameworks.
Which are topics that underline most
material in this MOOC.
Throughout this MOOC, we'll analyze dozens
of pattern-oriented Java and Android
applications.
Some of which we've developed.
And others that reside in Android's
middleware, class libraries
and packaged applications which apply many
patterns and frameworks.
These examples showcase the pattern
[UNKNOWN]
software architecture techniques, tools,
and methods you
need to successfully develop your own
concurrent mobile applications and
services on Android.
[MUSIC]