[MUSIC].
Welcome to, the next part of the module on
Android concurrency.
Now that we've described the structure and
functionality
of Java threads, we'll motivate the need
for Java's
synchronization and scheduling mechanisms
to protect against data corruption,
due to race conditions, which arise when
an app.
Location depends on the sequence or timing
of
the processes or threads for it to operate
properly.
As described in this link, and ensure
threads execute in
the right order, to meet
their synchronization and scheduling
requirements.
To make the discussion concrete, we'll
motivate the need
for these mechanisms in the context of two
examples.
The first example, is a program with two
Java threads.
That attempt to communicate, by passing
messages via a shared queue.
The second example is a program with 2
Java threads, that
attempt to alternate printing ping and
pong on the computer console.
Even if you have a lot of experience
developing
concurrent software, you might want to
skim through this video.
Since we'll revisit these examples
throughout the rest of
this module, to illustrate key Java
synchronization and scheduling mechanisms.
[MUSIC].
Our first example is a simple concurrent
producer consumer program.
It attempts to pass messages via an object
whose interface is
modeled loosely, on the Java util
concurrent array blocking queue class.
Described in this link, whose put and take
methods, NQ, and DQ, elements in a
synchronized manner.
This UML sequence diagram, shows the
design of the program,
which has a main entry point method that
creates an instance
of buggy queue, and then creates and
starts producer and consumer
threads, whose run methods called Buggy
Queues Put and Take methods.
To pass messages concurrently from the
producer to the consumer.
To showcase a common synchronization
problem, we'll examine the
buggy queue implementation, which is
available at this link.
The elements in the queue are stored in a
resizable Java
array list, described at this link, that's
instantiated with a string.
Buggy ques, put and take methods, and and
remove strings from
the tale and the head of the underlying MQ
list respectively.
The main entry point method of this
program, creates and starts two threads.
Whose run hook methods, called
BuggyQueue's, put and
take methods, to produce and consume
string messages concurrently.
So far the implementation seems straight
forward.
However, the important question is what
output will this code produce?
Depending on various factors, such as
the underlying hardware and software
infrastructure.
The answer most likely will be scrambled
output, or
an index out of bounds exception due to
race conditions.
The problem with BuggyQueue, is that
it's implementation doesn't prevent
critical sections
in the put and take methods from being run
by multiple threads concurrently.
The array list documentation at this link
clearly states, that its implementation is
not synchronized.
Therefore, if multiple threads access an
array list instance
concurrently, and at least one of the
threads calls Remove
as we do on this example, it must be
synchronized
externally or the list can be corrupted by
concurrent access.
These types of race conditions are harder
to detect
and debug, do to the inherent complexities
of concurrency.
Discussed in this earlier video.
For example, the behavior of this program
will vary
depending on factors like the number of
cores, or properties
that the underlying operating system
scheduler, which makes development
and quality assurance processes tedious,
error prone, and non portable.
We'll fix these problems, by applying
various Java
synchronization and scheduling mechanisms,
covered later in this module.
[MUSIC].
Our second example, shows how two Java
threads can be created and used
in an attempt to alternate printing ping,
and pong, on the computer console.
We use a Java console application, to
avoid
dealing with some Android multi threading
design restrictions.
Described at this link, until after we've
discussed
its user interface threading model later
in this section.
This slide shows a UML sequence diagram,
that depicts the design of our example
program.
The main, thread invokes the main, entry
point method of the ping-pong wrong class.
Which creates and starts two other Java
threads, whose
run hook methods implement, the ping pong
algorithm concurrently.
This link contains the code, we're about
to examine.
The entire example is implemented within
the PingPongWrong class, which contains a
static
data member that stores the number of
times each thread prints ping and pong.
It also contains a static nested class,
called play ping-pong thread
that extends the Java thread class and
runs the ping-pong logic concurrently.
The play ping-pong thread constructor
stores a stream
to print for each ping and pong operation.
The play ping-pong thread run hook method.
Contains a loop, that performs the ping
pong algorithm, which iterates for
the designated number of times and prints
some information to the console.
Note the lack of proper synchronization,
which we'll discuss shortly and remedy
later.
When the loop is done, the method and thus
the thread exits.
Here's the main entry point method of the
PingPongWrong class.
This method executes in the main
thread, and creates two PlayPingPongThread
objects, passing
in parameters that will indicate whether
to print a Ping, or a Pong, string.
It then starts both threads, which
triggers the
Java virtual machine to invoke their run
hook methods.
To execute the ping-pong element
concurrently.
Next, it calls the threads join methods,
and waits for both of
them to exit before wrapping up and
returning from the main thread.
This second example showed how to create,
start, run, and join multiple Java
threads.
Although these methods are used properly.
The results are incorrect, since there's
no synchronization,
to ensure the threads alternate their
output as intended.
In particular, the ping thread prints of
its output, and then
exits, before the pong thread even has a
chance to thread.
We'll fix this problem later in this
module, after we cover Java semaphores and
CountDownLatches.
So that the ping and pong threads
will alternate, putting their output to
the console.
As shown on this slide.
[MUSIC].
In summary, synchronization and scheduling
mechanisms are
important for multi-threaded Java
programs, such as
our buggy producer and consumer, and ping
pong program examples described in this
video.
The buggy producer consumer program,
showed how race conditions can occur if.
Critical sections, are properly protected
via synchronization mechanisms.
Once we fix these problems, we'll see that
there also scheduling issues to resolve.
Likewise, the buggy ping pong program,
show how results may
be incorrect, if threads don't execute in
the right order.
Our examples also have other design
limitations.
For example, they're hard coated and thus
hand
cuffed to work only and Java console
applications.
And can't be run without modifications in
Android, where
only the user interface threat can print
to display.
Our revised solutions covered throughout
this module, will
therefore apply various gang of four and
posso patterns.
To make these multi-threaded programs,
more portable, reuseable, and extensible.
[MUSIC]