[MUSIC]
Welcome to the next part of the
introduction section.
Which outlines the course prerequisites
and learning strategies.
In this part, we'll explain the
background, students
taking this MOCC are expected to have, and
provide
some tips to help students learn the
material
covered in the videos, and successfully
complete the assignments.
When we teach classes on mobile cloud
computing with Android.
At Vanderbilt University, and the
University of Maryland, we
can rely on the students having taken the
prerequisites.
In contrast, one of the challenges of
teaching a MOOC, is that we don't
really know what you know, and whether
you're prepared to master the topics we
cover.
We developed this MOOC, with certain
assumptions about, and expectations
of students who take this course, which
are summarized here.
To help align our expectations, here are
some things we'd like you to know.
To get the most out of this MOOC.
First and foremost, it's essential for you
to have a good understanding
of object oriented programming in general,
and the Java programming language in
particular.
For example, you need to understand
Java features like classes, inheritance,
dynamic
binding and generics, so you can follow
along with the examples we cover.
It's also important to understand core
Android programming elements, such as
activities, intense,
and user interface components, as well
as the Eclipse Android development tools
environment.
If you're rusty on these topics, we
strongly
recommend you leverage resources available
on the web.
Starting with those summarized
at this link.
[MUSIC]
In addition to being proficient with Java,
it's also useful to understand
fundamental object oriented design
concepts, such
as encapsulation, abstraction,
polymorphism, and extensibility.
Object oriented design is a method of
planning
a system with interacting objects to solve
software problems,
by specifying crisply defined conceptual
boundaries, that combine
methods and data, to hide information
likely to change.
Thereby minimizing rework.
As requirements and environments evolve,
as described at this link.
Likewise, knowledge of class and sequence
diagrams, defined by the Unified
Modeling Language, or UML, will help you
understand the structure and interactions.
Between key elements of the Java and
Android examples, we analyze throughout
this MOOC.
You don't need to be a UML expert to make
sense of these examples, but we recommend
you read the material
available on UML available at this link,
and on other websites
and books, so you'll understand the
notations used in our diagrams.
Finally, it would be helpful, if you're
familiar with common systems and network
programming concepts
and mechanisms, such as event loops,
multi-threading, multi-processing,
synchronization, scheduling and local and
remote interprocess communication.
You don't need a deep background in these
areas.
Since we'll review them as needed
throughout this MOOC.
However, if you're interested in learning
more about these topics, section
one of the 2013 POSA MOOC, provides an
overview at this
link.
[MUSIC].
This MOOC covers a lot of material, and
some
requires a lot of thinking and practice to
master.
Even if you've successfully completed
Professor Porter's MOOC.
To help you learn all this material, here
are
some strategies you should consider, when
taking this MOOC.
First, watch the lectures carefully,
perhaps multiple times.
And at different rates of speed, to fully
comprehend the topics that we're covering.
Many topics are technically deep,
especially
concurrency, interprocess communication,
and application security.
Although we can't possible address all
aspects
of this material in our limited time
together.
You may benefit from learning more about
these topics, either during, or after this
MOOC.
Therefore, many slides contain links to
articles, documentation, and
source code that you can read as time
permits.
However, no quiz questions relate to this
material,
so feel free to read it at your leisure.
Additional tips for learning the material
in the videos, appear at this
link.
[MUSIC].
Although reading the freely available
material
online is helpful, more comprehensive
information,
can often be found in the recommended
reading list, that appears here.
On the POSA MOOC home page.
I encourage you to read these books, to
gain even
more insights into the material we cover
in the lectures.
I also urge you to seek out Coursera
meetup groups in your area, which are
summarized here.
Where you can get together face to face
with fellow
students, and further immerse yourselves
in the topics we cover.
Another way to make this MOOC feel more
like a face to face course, is to attend
virtual office hours, where we'll answer
your questions, and
lead impromptu discussions live, via
Google Hangout and YouTube.
All virtual office hours will also be
recorded and uploaded to the
POSA website, so you can watch them at
your convenience, as described here.
Even if you aren't able to join us live,
we encourage
you to participate in the online
discussion forums, where you can interact
with other students, post questions, give
answers, clarify points of confusion,
and learn who else is wrestling with the
same challenges as you.
We regularly monitor the forums, and we'll
provide tips
and pointers, to mentor you through the
learning process.
However, there are only a handful of us,
but tens of thousands of you, so please
read
our policies on the forum postings at this
link, and be respectful of fellow students
and staff.
[MUSIC]
In summary, our goal on teaching this
MOOC, is to help as many students
as possible, gain access to a world
class education, on mobile cloud computing
with Android.
However, the topics we cover are
technically deep, and take time to master.
So, we encourage you to leverage multiple
sources of learning,
many of which are listed in the FAQ at
this link.
I strongly encourage you to read the
entire FAQ, since it
provides a wealth of information to help
you succeed in this MOOC.
If you're inspired to learn more about
mobile cloud computing with Android,
and associated topics like patterns and
frameworks, I recommend you check out the
digital learning resources available at
this
link, which provide dozens more hours of
videos and screencasts on object oriented
design and programming with Java and C++.
Patterns and frameworks for concurrent and
network software,
and Android middle ware and systems
programming mechanisms.
[MUSIC]