[MUSIC].
Welcome to the module on Java Concurrency
Mechanisms.
At the core of Android's concurrency
infrastructure, are standard Java language
and library
features that create and manage threads,
as
well as synchronize and schedule their
interactions.
This module presents an overview of these
Java Concurrency
Mechanisms, focusing on the core
properties of Java threads
and key Java synchronizers and scheduling
mechanisms, such as
Reentrant locks, condition objects,
semaphores,
and synchronized methods and statements.
It also shows many examples of applying
these
mechanisms in applications, and the
Android middleware, to develop
effective and correct concurrent software,
as well as demonstrating
problems that arise when these mechanisms
are applied incorrectly.
In addition, we discussed how Java
Concurrency
Mechanisms are enhanced by the application
of common
Gang of Four and posted patterns, such as
template method, strategy,
factory method, and monitor object.
[MUSIC]