[MUSIC].
Welcome
to the next part of the introduction
section
which provides an overview of Patterns and
Frameworks.
In this part, we will explain what
Patterns and Frameworks are
and describe why they are essential for
programming mobile device software.
Patterns and Frameworks are important
techniques, tools and
methods for leveraging proven design and
implementation experience
to enhance key software quality attributes
such as
modularity, flexibility and extensibility,
reusability, performance and resilience.
Before we discuss these topics in the
context of Android, we'll
first consider how experience is leveraged
in other domains beyond software.
Experts in most domains perform quite
differently than novices.
For example, professional athletes,
musicians, and dancers move fluidly and
effortlessly without focusing on each
individual movement as novices do.
When watching experts perform however,
it's easy to forget how much
effort and experience was needed to reach
their high levels of achievement.
Moreover, continuous repetition, practice
and mentoring
from experts was crucial to their success.
At the heart of all these activities is
knowledge and mastery of
patterns which are reasonable solutions to
common problems that arise in particular
context.
Naturally the context in this MOOC is
generally
the domain of mobile software development
with Android.
While knowledge of patterns provides
essential
design and architecture guidance, it also
helps to have implementation guidance
which
motivates the need for software
frameworks.
A framework is an integrated set of
components that collaborate to
provide a reasonable architecture for a
family of related applications or
services.
Patterns and frameworks are highly
synergistic.
For example, frameworks can be viewed as
concrete realisations of
patterns that facilitate direct reuse of
detail design and source code.
Likewise, patterns can be viewed as
abstract descriptions of
frameworks that facilitate reuse of
software architecture and design.
Patterns are generally described in
programming language independent ways
whereas frameworks are generally
implemented
in a particular programming language.
Android applies many patterns to implement
its Java concurrency
and communication frameworks, some of
which we'll outline next.
[MUSIC]
As outlined earlier, patterns leverage
proven software design and
programming expertise to provide
reasonable
solutions to common problems within
various contexts such as the domains of
mobile devices, aerospace,
avionics and automotive systems,
e-commerce, electronic trading and so on.
Patterns allow developers in these domains
to resolve key software quality
attribute forces such as need for
modularity, flexibility and extensibility,
and reusability.
These software quality attributes must be
balanced and
traded off against other forces such as a
need
to reduce end to end latency, or ensure
resilient
execution even in the face of failures or
cyberattacks.
Knowledge of patterns helps developers
navigate more effectively
through the tradeoffs of these domains and
design spaces.
Patterns also capture recurring structures
and dynamics among software
elements thereby enabling reuse of
successful designs and implementation
techniques.
For example, observer is a common pattern
that defines
a one-to-many dependency between objects
so that when one
object changes, other objects that depend
on it are
automatically notified and updated as
described at this link.
This diagram depicts the canonical
structure of
the observer pattern which has a subject
that's
associated with an abstract observer base
class
which in turn, is subclassed by concrete
observers.
These concrete observers override the
update method in
the abstract observer class to define
application-specified behaviors.
The subject maintains a collection of
observers
that can be attached or detached by
applications.
When a state change occurs, the subject is
notified which causes
to iterate through all it's attached
observers and invoke their update method.
These call backs should run quickly to
avoid starving
other observers and preventing them from
doing their processing.
The observer pattern can be implemented
and applied in
many different ways, in different
languages both object joined
and non object jointed, on different
platforms, with different
data structures and different domains by
different vendors, etc.
Regardless of these different
implementation
details, the underlying patterns roles
and responsibilities are essentially the
same thereby reusing valuable design
knowledge.
Historically, software developers learn
these types of design and programming
techniques, tools, and methods by
working alongside experienced developers,
as apprentices.
Although these mentoring relationships are
valuable, they're also labor-intensive,
and rely
heavily on identifying and motivating
experienced developers to serve as
mentors.
Likewise, they're also risky since a
mentor may decide to change
jobs or get hit by a bus as described at
this link.
Patterns often address these risks by
codifying expert
knowledge of time proven design strategies
and best practices.
So the developers need to learn them
solely
through human mentors or tedious trial and
error.
Android implements dozens of patterns that
guide the
design and implementation of its
mechanisms for event multiplexing
and dispatching, interface and component
partitioning and interaction, application
control, resource and database management,
and concurrency and synchronization.
This MOOC devotes several modules
to Android concurrency and communication
patterns.
Additional information about patterns
appears at this link.
[MUSIC].
Knowledge of patterns codifies experience
and
guides the design and architectures
decisions which
is essential for developing and sustaining
quality software on time and on budget.
But design and architecture alone is
insufficient for
many software professionals who also
benefit from implementation guidance.
To address this need, frameworks provide a
powerful and complimentary means to
redefine software
experience and patterns and tangible code
artifacts
that help improve developer productivity
and quality.
A framework that is an integrated set of
components that collaborate to
provide a reasonable architecture for a
family of related applications or
services.
There are several defining characteristics
of Frameworks as described in this link.
First, they provide inversion of control
also known as the Hollywood principle.
Rather than having an application be self
directed doing what it wants,
when and how it wants, a Framework owns
the main application event loop.
Applications register event handler
objects with the framework.
What events occur that an application is
indicated
[INAUDIBLE] in, the framework is
responsible for detecting what's
happened and then demultiplexing and
dispatching the events, to
hook methods defined in the registered
application event handles.
A hook method is a specified point
in a framework based program where
developers can
customize generic framework components
with call backs that
the framework invokes through an
application specific logic.
The second defining characteristic of
frameworks is their support for domain
specific structures and functionality
which allows
the framework to perform many common
interactions, guide the canonical flow of
control and enforce key architectural
constraints
so developers needn't rediscover,
reimplement, and
redebug them for each new application.
Some domains supported by frameworks are
application domains
such as social media, mobile applications,
or electronic trading.
Other domains supported by frameworks are
infrastructure domains such as
graphical user interfaces, communication
middle
ware and persistent database storage.
The third defining characteristic of
frameworks
is their support for semi-complete
applications or
portions of applications where the
framework provides
most of the canonical structure and
behavior
in the form of reusable interfaces and
classes and developers simply implement
hook methods
that customize and tailor the generic
framework
components for application or server
specific needs.
Android provides many frameworks that
manage activities, event notifications
persistent
content interact with the user and the
radio and application installation.
This MOOC devotes several modules
to Android concurrency and communication
frameworks.
Additional information about frameworks
appears at this
link.
[MUSIC]
While the overview of patterns and
frameworks
in the previous two videos, summarized
their essential
characteristics, the presentation was
intentionally high-level, and
only touched briefly on their relevance to
Android.
To make the discussion more concrete,
we'll now outline several applications of
patterns and frameworks in the observer
pattern, outlines earlier in this video.
Which has been used successfully in many
domains.
Android applies this pattern extensively.
For example, it's content provider and
resolver
framework applies this pattern to
automatically notify
content observers when rows in an SQL
lite database changes as described at this
link.
This diagram shows the UML notation that
maps classes in a content
observer based design to keep roles and
responsibilities of the observer pattern.
For example, the Android desk clock
application uses
the observer pattern to monitor user
display preferences
such as the use of 12 hour versus 24 hour
time as shown in this path name.
The Android Content Observable plays the
role
of the Subject in the Observer pattern.
Likewise, the Content Observer plays the
Abstract Observer role in the pattern,
and the FormatChange Observer plays the
Concrete Observer role in the pattern.
>> Android also uses the observer pattern
in
its intents framework, which is a powerful
mechanism
that activates and notifies activity,
service and broadcast
receiver components asynchronously, as
described at this link.
This email diagram maps the key
programming elements in the intense
framework to the observer pattern also
using the desk top application.
For example, broadcast receiver is an
abstract observer that's
extended by the desk clock application to
create an alarm
receiver that connects an alarm alert
intent receiver to
an alarm alert activity as shown at this
path name.
The Android Context object plays the role
of the subject which
notifies the registered alarm receiver
when an alarm alert event occurs.
Knowing that Android applies the Observer
pattern helps
application developers better understand
how these 2 different frameworks
behave and how to use them effectively
since
it reduces the surface area of the design
space.
Both these applications of the observer
pattern in
the Android also demonstrate key framework
characteristics such as
inversion of control, domain specific
structure and functionality, and
semi-complete portions of applications, as
discussed in the previous
video.
[MUSIC].
In summary, patterns and frameworks are
important techniques,
tools, and methods for developing and
sustaining quality software.
In particular, they enhance systematic
software reuse by intentionally creating
or
acquiring reusable assets and then
consistently using and evolving them to
obtain a high degree of reuse thereby
optimizing the ability to
produce quality software products rapidly
and effectively as described at this link.
If you program professionally, you may be
familiar with the
concept of opportunistic reuse which
involves ad hoc cutting and
pasting of existing code when building a
new piece of
software to avoid having to write it all
from scratch.
While opportunistic reuse is popular, it
yields many code forks that
are frustratingly hard to evolve and
sustain correctly and consistently over
time.
In contrast, systematic resuse is a more
rigorous method that
applies patterns and frameworks to reuse
design and code artifacts.
Design re-use matches problems to the
relevent
solution structures and dynamics in a
particular domain.
Code re-use reifies proven designs
within particular development environments
and platforms.
Together, reuse of designs via patterns,
and code via
frameworks avoids rediscovering and
rewriting solutions to many software
development problems, which saves time and
money as well
as produces better quality products over
the software life cycle.
We could devote an entire MOOC to discuss
all the nuances and aspects
of patterns and frameworks since they are
very powerful and deep technical topics.
However, this MOOC focuses on Android, so
we just covered the
sub set of pattern and framework topics
that pertain to it.
For broader and deeper coverage of these
topics, see the 2013 POSA MOOC archives
which have many more hours of videos
on pattern relationships, such as pattern
compounds, pattern
complements, pattern sequences and pattern
languages, much more extensive coverage
of frameworks that implement pattern
languages as well as more background
material on concurrency and communication,
and the operating
system and middleware layers.
[MUSIC]