[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO].
Welcome to the first module in the section
on Android concurrency.
This module summarizes key concurrency
motivations
and challenges to provide a conceptual
overview
before we delve into the numerous
details and examples of Android
concurrency mechanisms.
Frameworks and patterns in the rest of
this section.
The advent of multicore and distributed
core processors is increasing the demand
for practitioners and researchers who
understand
how to develop and deploy concurrent
software.
That takes full advantage of the
underlying hardware.
For example, many cell phones and laptops
have quad core processors, many desktops
and servers
have eight to twelve cores, and computer
devices with many more cores are coming
soon.
However.
Despite continuous improvements in
hardware during the past four decades,
it's frustratingly hard to develop quality
concurrent software for mobile devices.
This module explains why you should expend
the time
and effort learning how to develop
concurrent mobile device software.
We also explore common challenges that
you'll
need to understand in order to master key
accidental and inherent complexities that
arise when
you develop this type of software on
Android.
[MUSIC]