[MUSIC].
Welcome to the section on Android
Concurrency which explores the motivations
for, challenges
of, and techniques tools, and methods
associated
with developing concurrent software for
mobile devices.
Concurrent software can simultaneously run
multiple
computations that potentially interact
with each other.
To insure that interactions between
running computations occur in
the right order and don't accidentally
corrupt shared data.
Synchronization, and scheduling mechanisms
are needed.
This section focuses on the mechanisms
that Android provides to create,
control, and terminate multiple threads
that run concurrently within a process.
Some Android concurrency mechanisms we
cover.
Are based on standard Java features such
as threads,
synchronized methods and statements,
[UNKNOWN]
locks, condition objects and semaphores.
We also cover several Android concurrency
frameworks, such as its handlers,
runables and messages or hammer framework,
and it's asynced tasked framework.
Throughout this section, we'll illustrate
by
example how concurrent Android
applications and
frameworks are developed by applying many
Gang of Four and POSA patterns.
Such as template method, strategy,.
Factory method, command processor, active
object and monitor
object, half synch, half asynch and
thread-specific storage.
You not only learn what goes on at the
surface of the Android application
layers, but you also learn what goes
on underneath, inside the Android
middleware itself.
We examine a lot of Java programming in
this section so you may want to
download the Android open source code
available from the Poso moot website, and
follow along.
[MUSIC]