[MUSIC]
Welcome
to the second part of the module on
concurrency, motivations, and challenges.
In this part, we explore key challenges
that you need to understand, to
cut the Gordian Knot of complexity,
related
to developing concurrent software for
mobile devices.
Some of these challenges are called
accidental complexities, which arise from
limitations
with the tools, techniques and methods we
commonly use to build software.
For example, concurrent programs are often
written using low
level application programming interfaces,
written in languages like C.
And debug, using tools that aren't well
equipped to detect common hazards of
concurrent programming.
All too frequently, these problems are
self
inflicted, because we don't always have to
use these tools, techniques, and methods,
it's
often just conventional wisdom, or common
practise.
Other challenges are called inherent
complexities.
Which arrives from fundamental problems in
the domain
of concurrent software, such as deadlock,
scheduling, and synchronization.
[MUSIC]
These inherent complexities constitute the
rocket science of the domain of
concurrent programming, and require deep
thinking and analysis to get right.
A common accidental complexity is the
use of low-level Application Programming
Interfaces, or
APIs, which are tedious, error-prone, and
non-portable
when used to develop a concurrent
software.
For example, consider the pthread's
concurrency API.
It's available in Unix, including the
versions of
Linux using Android, as shown at this path
name.
A number of accidental complexities are
associated with
using the pthread API to write concurrent
software.
First, it uses low-level and error-prone
data types, such as
pointer dysfunctions that are passed when
a pthread is created.
Likewise, type caster needed to pass a
data structure
as a void pointer when a thread is
created.
As well as the cast the void pointer back
to whatever structures you
use, to pass data between he caller and
the callee in the pthreads environment.
Casts disable compiler type checking,
which allows
subtle layers to creep into your software.
Another problem is use of quasi type
thread
handles, which are error-prone, since
compilers can't provide
effective type checking, if the wrong type
of
handle is accidentally passed to a pthread
function.
Finally, since we're programming to the
pthreads API explicitly, this code
won't be portable to non-POSIX platforms,
such as Windows or VxWorks.
Lest that you think that we're unfairly
picking on pthreads, most operating
systems today
have these kinds of problems, when
low-level
C APIs are used to write concurrent
programs.
Some other accidental complexities
associated with concurrency, stem from
limitations with our debugging
environments, and our debugging tools.
A well written and properly functioning
concurrent program, is a thing of beauty.
But what happens when something goes
wrong?
What tools enable you to drill down, and
look inside of your
software to figure out what's happening,
and then take the appropriate remedial
action?
There are a number of challenges here.
One problem, is that the behavior you see
in the
debugger, doesn't necessarily reflect the
actual behavior of the deployed software.
Which is often called a Heisenbug, since
the act of observing
a system inevitably alters its state, as
described with this link.
For example, you may use a debugger
to single-step through some code in one
thread.
While other threads are running, but the
execution sequence, and the execution
times, may differ if the program was
running outside of the debug.
This divergence makes certain types of
scheduling hazards and timing problems.
Hard to identify and hard to rectify.
This link describes some multithreading
debugging techniques,
that may be helpful in addressing these
problems.
Another problem, stems from race
conditions that
occur, when multiple threads
simultaneously crash into
unprotected data structures and corrupt
them, which
yields defects that are often hard to
detect.
Until your program is deployed in its
target environment, as described at this
link.
Many debuggers have poor support for
detecting
race conditions, during the development of
concurrent software.
To handle these types of problems, you
need advanced
methods and tools, such as static or
dynamic analysis.
These links describe some relevent
technologies and
tools, some of which are targeted at
Android.
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Some common inherent complexities of
concurrent
software relate to synchronization and
scheduling,
which deal with the order and/or time in
which operations are performed.
Synchronization ensures that multiple
concurrent
threads, don't execute critical sections
of
a program at the same time, and thus
corrupt shared resources.
Synchronization also occurs in our daily
lives.
For example, air traffic controllers must
synchronize access to a runway, which
is a shared resource, to ensure airplanes
don't collide on takeoff or landing.
Likewise, Android needs to synchronize
access
to the SQLite Contacts Database, to ensure
that applications running concurrently on
the
device, don't corrupt the raw contact
entries.
This link contains more information on
synchronization.
Scheduling insures that threads processes,
or data
flows are given proper access to system
resources.
For example, air traffic controllers need
to schedule the
arrival and departure of airplanes, based
on limited resources.
Such as gates and runways, likewise,
Android
scheduler must ensure that an emergency
call
isn't missed, just because the user is
playing the Angry Birds game on the phone.
Getting all this right is hard, since
there're many
states to manage in concurrent programs,
and it's hard to
keep track of them all to insure that the
software
does the right thing, under both expected
and unexpected conditions.
This link contains more information on
scheduling.
Another inherent complexity is deadlock,
which
occurs when two or more competing actions
are each waiting for the other to finish,
and thus, none ever do.
The diagram on this slide shows a deadlock
where thread T1 owns lock
L1, and needs to acquire lock L2, while
thread T2 owns lock L2.
It needs to acquire lock L1.
This circular wait or deadly embrace,
blocks the threads indefinitely.
Identifying, detecting and removing
deadlocks is an
inherent complexity of developed in
current software.
For example, you wouldn't want the Android
Gmail application to
deadlock on resources held by the Calendar
application and vice versa.
This link provides more information on
deadlock.
[MUSIC]
In summary, several types of complexity
can make
it hard to develop and assure concurrent
software.
As covered in the POSA2 book, and more
generally in
the classic, No Silver Bullet paper,
described at this link.
Accidental complexities arise from
self-inflicted wounds, such as
limitations with low-level application
programming interfaces written in C.
If you follow this link, you'll learn
more about accidental complexities and
developing concurrent software.
As well as some tips on how
patterns and frameworks help to alleviate
these complexities.
Inherent complexities arise from
fundamental challenges in particular
domains, such as the domain of concurrent
software.
Solving these hard problems, involves deep
thinking, and
may require applying sophisticated
analysis methods and tools.
The book at this link describes many
algorithms
and mechanisms, for addressing inherent
complexities of concurrent software.
As concurrent software becomes more
pervasive in mobile cloud
computing systems, and, as users
increasingly rely on mobile devices.
For mission-critical and
lifestyle-critical tasks, such as
security, e-commerce, geo-positioning, and
transportation, it's essential
to understand the challenges described in
this part of the module, and resolve them.
So you'd be better positioned to slay the
dragons of complexity.
A key part of the solution, that
we'll explore throughout the rest of this
section.
Is how Android codifies time-proven
experience, in
the form of reasonable patterns and
frameworks,
that help overcome key inherent and
accidental
complexities of developing concurrent
software for mobile devices.
[MUSIC]