[MUSIC].
Welcome to the next part of the
introduction section.
We will explain the organization of and
topics presented in this MOOC.
This part summarizes the structure of the
course, describes what assignments we'll
have and
how they'll be accessed, and outlines the
main topics, covered in the course
sections.
Once we're done with this brief
introduction section, the remainder of
the course is organized into three
sections, which focus on Android
concurrency mechanisms and frameworks,
Android
services, interprocess communication
mechanisms, and application
security, and software patterns for
concurrency and inter and intraprocess
communication.
Each section is composed of modules, which
focused on a group
of related topics, such as Android
concurrency frameworks, or interprocess
communication patterns.
Each module is composed of multiple parts,
which cover a
particular topic, such as Java semaphores,
or the Android AsyncTask framework.
Each part is presented as a single video,
roughly five to 15 minutes in length.
Each part is composed of segments, which
are short one to three minute video clips.
The focus on one aspect of a topic, such
as starting or stopping java threads.
An in video quiz will periodically pop up,
so you
can check if you've mastered the material
covered in the video.
If you download the videos and watch them
locally on your computer however, these
quizzes won't appear,
but some of the questions may show up on
the weekly stand alone quizzes, which
we'll discuss shortly.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC].
[BLANK_AUDIO].
There will be roughly a half dozen
programming assignments, all written in
Java, using Eclipse.
Though you can use other environments as
long as you can support them yourself,
or with help from other students on
the discussion forums, as described in the
FAQ.
All Java and Android source code for
assignments and
examples can be downloaded from my GitHub
repository, available here.
The programming assignments will provide
you with a range of
experience developing Android
applications, services,
and frameworks as discussed here.
The first several assignments will give
you experience applying and developing
concurrency mechanisms.
For example, you'll implement simple
Atomic Long
and Semaphore classes using Javaa
ReentrantReadWriteLock, randrant
locks and condition objects and then test
them in the Java console environment and
Eclipse.
In the next several assignments, you'll
implement part
of a multithreaded ping-pong application
that applies gang of
four patterns to develop a framework that
simplifies porting
the application between Android and
console configurations and Eclipse.
The final assignment, is an integrative
project that will give
you experience applying pattern oriented
concurrency mechanisms and Android
concurrency
and communication frameworks and security
mechanisms to the iRemember application,
introduced in Professor Porter's MOOC as
described at this link.
Quizzes will be entirely auto graded.
And programming assignments will be
assessed by a combination
of auto-grading, and peer grading, as
discussed in the FAQ.
If you're taking his MOOC to get a
statement
of accomplishment, or a verified
certificate, then you're required
to do the quizzes and or the assignments,
which
we'll evaluate using the grading criteria
described at this link.
Naturally, if you want to take this MOOC
solely to learn the material
and expand your knowledge, you don't need
to submit any quizzes or assignment
solutions.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO].
Now that we've explained the overall
course
organization, we'll outline the contents
of each section.
Section one, covers Android concurrency,
which exports tools techniques
and methods associated with developing
concurrent software for mobile devices.
After briefly covering the motivations for
and challenges of concurrency.
This section focuses on concurrency
mechanisms,
frameworks and patterns that Androids
applies and
provides to create control and terminate
multiple threads run concurrently within a
process.
Some Android concurrency mechanisms
discussed in
this section are based on standard Java
features such as threads, synchronized
methods and
statements, reentrant locks, addition
objects, and semaphores.
We also cover key Android concurrency
frameworks such as its handlers,
runnables, and messages or hammer
framework, and the async task framework.
Throughout this section, we'll illustrate
by
example, how concurrent Android
applications and frameworks
are developed, by applying many common
patterns documented in popular books and
websites.
These patterns focus on general
object oriented software decomposition and
composition
techniques, as well as concurrency,
synchronization, and communication
mechanisms and protocols.
Many patterns appear on the pattern to
software architecture or POSA book, and
design patterns, elements of reasonable
object
writed software, or gang for a book.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC].
[BLANK_AUDIO].
Section two covers Android's services,
inter-process communication and
application security.
Although the activity components covered
in week two
of Professor Porter's MOOC, provide a
visual interface for
interactions with the user, Android also
defines service
components which run on separate
background thread or process.
Services don't interact with the user
directly, instead, activities use services
to
perform long duration operations or access
remote resources on behalf of users.
Such as downloading files from a server in
the Cloud.
This section examines several types of
Android
services, including started services that
usually perform a
single operation, and bounce services that
allow
clients to conduct longer conversations
with service implementations.
Activities and services interact via
mechanisms that are
optimized for inter-process communication,
within a mobile device.
We cover several Android inter-process
communication mechanisms
in section two, including intents, which
are passed
when an activity or service is started,
and
messengers, which enable message based
communication across processes.
We also cover the binder object oriented
remote procedure call mechanism, and the
Android interface definition language that
simplifies Java
application access to the binder
communication capabilities.
Section two also focuses on Android
application security.
Where we first describe Android security
model,
and explain some of its risks, and
limitations.
We then discuss various tools, techniques,
and methods, for building more
secure Android applications, which is a
particularly important topic these days.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC].
[BLANK_AUDIO].
Section three covers patterns for
concurrency and inter
and intra process communication, that are
applied in Android.
The patterns we cover all come from the
pattern oriented
software architecture books, which
document
fundamental concurrency and communication
patterns.
For example, Android applies the monitor
object pattern to implement
the link blocking queue class in the Java
util concurrent package.
It applies thread specific storage pattern
to
ensure only one looper is created per
thread.
It applies the command processing pattern,
to enable code in a background thread to
post a runnable command that's in queue
and processed later in the user interface
thread.
Android also applies this patter to
its intents service, which handles
asynchronous
requests expressed as intents on-demand in
the background thread of a service.
It applies a variant of the active object
pattern to enable a client
in one thread, to send messages to our
handler running in another thread.
It applies the half sync, half async
pattern to allow one
or more background threads to block
synchronously, while processing long
duration operations.
And then pass the results via a
synchronized queue to the
user interface thread, which only perform
short duration, non blocking operations.
Finally it applies the broker pattern to
support object oriented
remote method calls, between activities
and services running in different
processes.
Naturally, these fundamental patterns are
not
limited to Android or mobile device
programming.
So, learning them will not only make you
more fluent,
with the topics we cover with the mobile
cloud computing
with Android specialization, but they'll
also provide you with a
solid foundation for programming
concurrent
and network software in other platforms.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC].
[BLANK_AUDIO].
In summary, the topics in this MOOC cover
a
range of Android concurrency mechanisms
and frameworks, services and interprocess
communication mechanisms, and application
security models, as well as patterns
that guide the design of Android
mechanisms, frameworks, and applications.
After watching the videos, completing the
assignments and participating
in the online discussion forums, you
should be able to
recognize the inherent and accidental
complexities involved with developing
a current software that communicates
securely between processes and threads.
Likewise, you'll understand how pattern
oriented software architecture and
framework techniques can, and cannot help,
to alleviate these complexities.
You'll also learn how to apply patterns
and frameworks, to develop reusable and
resilient concurrent applications and
services, using
Java programming language features, and
Android middleware.
Finally, if you follow up on all the
links referenced in the slides, you'll
know where to
find additional sources of information, on
how to
program mobile applications and services
on Android handheld systems.
We analyze lots of Android software
throughout this MOOC.
So you'll need a solid understanding of
Java to follow along.
Much of this code comes straight out of
the
Android open source release, which is
available at this link.
This link also provides several pattern
orientated applications that
demonstrate key Java concurrency and inter
process communication mechanisms and
frameworks, which we analyze in detail, to
showcase the
applications of patterns and frameworks in
the Android development environment.
[MUSIC]