[MUSIC]
Welcome the first part of the module on
concurrency motivations and challenges.
In this part we explore key
motivations for developing current mobile
device software.
These days, a prime reason for using
concurrency
is to leverage advances in hardware and
software.
Multi-core processors are becoming
ubiquitous to the point where it's getting
hard to buy a computing device that just
has one core.
This link describes a wide range of quad
core Android phones.
Operating systems like Unix, Windows and
VxWorks are optimized to
exploit these multiple cores efficiently
via threads, which are the
smallest sequence of program instructions
that can be managed independently
by an operating system scheduler, as
described at this link.
Likewise, middleware such as Java virtual
machines, web servers, Android .Net, DDS
and Corba can take advantage of multiple
cores as described at this link.
Knowledge of concurrency is therefore
necessary to program
multi-thread and multi-core systems
effectively, and improve various
software quality attributes such as
simplifying program structures,
to avoid overly complex entangled event
driven software architectures.
Increasing performance by overlapping
communication and computation
to run in parallel, and improving
responsiveness
by processing user interface operations in
a
different thread in other background
processing operations.
The rest of this video explores each of
these motivations in more detail.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC].
[BLANK_AUDIO].
Hardware and software advances can help
improve the way programs
are structured to avoid overly
complex, entangled event driven software
architectures.
Historically, the GUIs and early versions
of Windows, Mac OS
and Unix were structured using an event
driven programming model.
Where a single event loop processed user
interface events and
initiated file and network IO operations
in one thread of control.
This link provides more information on
event driven programming.
Programming purely event driven software
is hard however, since the structure
of its control flow is obscured in both
time and space.
In particular, any time a program might
block, such as when it
performed a read operation on a network
connection, it had to post
an event on a message queue and handle the
operation later in
its event loop, which was awkward to
program and hard to optimize.
This link describes the pros and cons of a
pattern called the reactor, it's common in
event driven programs.
Now that modern middleware, operating
systems
and hardware have better concurrency
support, more
effective ways of structuring application
and
system software have emerged, based on
multi-threading.
Which enables blocking operations that
detangle event
driven programs as described at this link.
For example, Android provides several
concurrency
frameworks that enable multiple threads to
perform long running computations in the
background, which maps efficiently onto
multiple cores.
Moreover, these background computations
can block
independently of each other and the
user interface thread, which allows
developers
to structure their software more
cohesively.
Using these Android frameworks effectively
requires knowledge of
concurrency patterns, which are described
at this link.
To illustrate one common Android
concurrency model that uses so-called
worker threads, here's a snippet of code
from an application
we'll explore throughout this MOOC, that
enables a user to
download an image from a remote server
across the network.
The structure of this code is based on the
half-sync, half-async
pattern described at this link, and
covered later in this section.
This example has a click listener, that
handles button pressed on the Android
touch screen.
When a user presses the Download button,
this code starts a worker
thread that runs in the background and
blocks while downloading an image.
After the image is downloaded and
processed,
it's displayed via the User Interface
thread.
If you look carefully at this code
snippet, you'll see how concisely
structured it is.
In particular, the image download and
display logic
is cohesive in time and space rather than
being scattered throughout the code, as
would be
the case in a purely event driven
solution.
This link describes the Android worker
threads concurrency
model, which we'll cover later in this
section.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC].
[BLANK_AUDIO].
Hardware and software advances also
allow software developers to increase
application
and system performance, which is a key
motivation for using concurrency.
In particular, performance can be
accelerated
via parallelism as described in this link.
Android accelerates performance by
parallelism in several ways.
One way is to overlap computation
and communication operations via it's
multithreading mechanisms.
For example, in the image downloading
application we
examined earlier, the background threads
that download images
can run in parallel with each other, and
with a thread that interacts with the
user.
This link provides more information on
Android multi-threaded mechanisms.
Another way to accelerate performance on
Android,
is to use the render script framework,
which
paralyzes work across all processors
available on a
device, such as multicore CPU's, GPUs or
DSPs.
RenderScript is targeted at applications
performing image processing, computational
photography or computer vision as
described at this link.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO].
Despite advances in the hardware, not
every
computing platform in use today supports
multiple cores.
For example, you may have an older device
with just one core or there
may be other constraints that make it hard
to take full advantage of parallelism.
Concurrency can still be useful however to
improve perceived response time, such as
ensuring
the user interface doesn't ignore input
from
users while other operations are being
processed.
For example, the Android user interface
thread can interact
responsively to user gestures and other
input, while worker
threads concurrently execute long running
computations in the background,
and perform blocking operations on the
file system and network.
This link provides more information on
responsiveness and computing systems.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO].
In summary, there are several motivations
for developing concurrent software for
mobile devices.
It helps developers effectively leverage
technology advances,
such as Moore's law and other means
by which commoditized hardware and
software gets
better, faster, and cheaper at a regular
pace.
Concurrency also helps developers meet the
quality
and performance needs of their
applications and
services, by going beyond what's provided
by
the lower level infrastructure's software
and hardware.
For example, concurrency allows developers
to structure
their software so it's more responsive to
user
interaction patterns, as well as easier to
understand and evolve over the software
life cycle.
[MUSIC]