[MUSIC]
Welcome to the first part of the
Introduction section, which provides an
overview of our mobile cloud computing
with Android specialization.
Everyday millions of people around the
world, use handheld smartphone
and tablet devices, that are increasingly
based on the Android platform.
As shown at this link.
These Android devices run software
applications, that direct users to
the places they want to go, securely
provide information about the
people, locations, goods and services near
them, and help them
interact with the people they care about,
and do business with.
These applications increasingly rely on
three synergistic
computing technologies, collectively known
as mobile cloud computing.
Where applications are designed to run on
smart mobile devices,
connected to elastic computing services,
that are accessible over wireless
networks.
Mobile cloud computing, represents the
confluence
of advances in multicore and distributed
core processors, inexpensive mass storage,
ubiquitous
wireless connectivity, and commodity
harbor platforms.
The demand for applications that run on
these platforms is
growing rapidly, which is motivating the
need for software practitioners
and researchers, who understand how to
develop concurrent and network
software for mobile devices, that connect
to powerful cloud platforms.
However, despite continuous improvements
in hardware and
software infrastructure, it remains
frustratingly hard to develop
high quality software applications, for
mobile devices
and computing clouds, on time and under
budget.
The impediments to success in this domain,
arise from various inherent and accidental
complexities, ranging
from self-inflicted limitations with
tedious and error-prone
techniques tools and methods used to
develop software.
To fundamental challenges of concurrency
and resilience that scale.
[MUSIC]
To help meet the needs and overcome the
impediments outlined earlier, I've teamed
up with professor Adam
Porter from the University of Maryland,
and Professor Jules White
from Vanderbilt University, to create a
Coursera specialization.
It covers many techniques, tools, and
methods, aimed at alleviating the
inherent and accidental complexities of
developing
mobile cloud computing applications with
Android.
Specializations are a new form of MOOC.
Aimed at fostering collaborations among
teachers and students, that span
traditional
inter and intra-institution and
disciplinary
boundaries, as described at this link.
The first MOOC in this sequence, the
University of Maryland's course,
Programming Mobile Applications for
Android Handheld Systems, taught by
Professor Porter, focused
on the design and implementation of
user-facing applications.
Covering the fundamental programming
principles,
software architecture, and user experience
considerations underlying handheld
software applications,
in the Android development environment.
The first lecture of week one of Professor
Porter's MOOC, presents an overview of the
Android platform, which you should watch
to
understand the key components in Android's
software architecture.
The second MOOC on programming mobile
services for Android handheld systems,
is being taught by me and Professor White,
from Vanderbilt University.
We focus on a range of Android application
and middle work programming topics.
Including threading and concurrency
control mechanisms, background
service processing, local interprocess
communication, and application security.
This MOOC builds upon and extends the
user-facing applications, covered earlier
in Professor Porter's MOOC.
Diving deeper into the guts of Android's
powerful middle work platform.
For example, we focus on how Android
combines
advances in hardware and software
infrastructure support for concurrency.
Together with pattern arc software
architecture and framework techniques.
To improve the performance,
responsiveness, security
and structure of mobile applications, so
they
are more efficient, resilient and easier
to evolve over the software life cycle.
[MUSIC].
>> Hi, I'm Jules White, and I'm teaming up
with Doug Schmidt to teach the
third MOOC in the mobile cloud computing
with Android specialization.
Entitled, Programming Cloud Services for
Android Handheld Systems.
This MOOC rounds out our coverage of
mobile cloud
computing, by focusing on how to connect
mobile devices
to cloud computing and data storage
resources, turning a
mobile device into an extension of
powerful cloud-based services.
We'll extend the handheld systems topics
covered in the first two
MOOCs, to focus on architectures for
communicating with the cloud using HDP.
Server side processing of mobile data,
using serverlets and the Java spring
framework, in scalable storage of data,
using no SQL databases and other
platforms.
Since building a slow or insecure mobile
cloud application is unacceptable.
This MOOC will not only show you how to
program handheld program systems
that talk to the cloud, but how to do it
securely, scalably, and efficiently.
This speciation has three MOOCs, plus a
Capstone project.
Signature track students, who receive a
verified
certificate with distinction in three
MOOCs, can combine
what they've learned to build a complete
mobile cloud computing application, from
the ground up.
[MUSIC].
>> The material covered in our MOOC
specialization,
is based on experience we've gained during
the
past several decades researching,
developing, and applying concurrent
and network software, written in C++ and
Java.
The software we've developed has been used
by thousands of projects around the world.
Often, for mission critical systems, where
the right
answered delivered too late, becomes the
wrong answer.
We're delighted to have the opportunity to
share
the key techniques and practices, we've
devised and learned
over the years, to help you become more
effective, at developing software for
mobile devices and clouds.
In our experience, the principles,
methods,
and skills required to develop such
software.
Are best learned by attaining mastery of
patterns and frameworks.
A pattern describes a reasonable solution
to a common problem that
arises within a particular context, which
can be as broad as
the domain of mobile cloud computing, or
as narrow as ensuring
Android smartphone users, are informed
when their battery levels are low.
A framework is an integrated set of
components, that collaborate to
provide a reuseable architecture, for our
family of related applications or
services.
Frameworks can also be viewed as concrete
realizations of pattern,
that facilitate directory use of detail
designs and source code.
We look forward to interacting with you
over the next several months.
To help you learn and apply these patterns
and frameworks in your own work on mobile
cloud computing with Android, just as we
do
at Vanderbilt University, and the
University of Maryland.
You'll not only become more productive,
but you'll also have a
lot more fun, and look at the world in new
ways.
[MUSIC]