[MUSIC]
Okay.
Any questions about the broker?
So now you know more than you ever
possibly wanted
to know about the broker, and how Android
works, with respect
to the binder and AIDL, again believe it
or not we've
just only scratched the surface of this
very, very rich topic.
So, if you're really into this if for some
reason you're
working for a company that has to go in
and modify
parts of Android in order to get its
requirements met for
its customers and users, you're going to
have to dive down even deeper.
But at least now you kind of know how
things are put together and it'll help
to focus your attention on the part that
matters for what you are trying to do.
Okay, the next thing I'm going to talk
about, and
this will really be the last set of
patterns on
these topics unless I get really inspired
and think of
one more between now and Wednesday which I
probably won't.
We're going to talk about something called
the publisher, subscriber pattern.
And we're going to describe first what the
pattern is, and kind of how it works, what
problems it solves, and then we're
going to talk
about how it's implemented in the context
of Android.
So here's, here's a way to think about the
need for this pattern.
There's a bunch of system-related status
information that's kept on your
behalf by Android that is often useful to
applications in one way or another.
For example, the Android middleware and
the
lower level drivers and system services
keep
track of the battery levels, which is
a very important thing because if you're
running
low on battery you probably want to know
about it so you can be
alerted and plug your phone in, or switch
the battery or do something like that.
The issue there is how do apps find out
that the battery is low?
Imagine you have the phone app, right?
You could be in the middle of a phone
call,
your phone app isn't busy doing anything
other than you
know, helping make sure that that call's
quality is good,
and managing things like three way calling
or caller id, right?
The phone app really shouldn't be sitting
there,
being tightly coupled to the battery
status module.
Right?
Why would the phone app need to know
about the details of monitoring the
battery level?
That would be, if you hard coded the phone
app to know about that, you would have
a very tightly coupled design that would
break
and be brittle as you try to make changes.
Likewise, having the app continually ask
some service, are you
running low on battery, are you running
low on battery?
Well, pretty soon, you're running low on
battery, because you're
spending all your time asking whether
you're low on battery, right?
It gets, it's like having your kids say
are we there yet, are we there yet, are we
there yet, because it's not making it go
any
faster, it's just getting to be a lot more
painful.
So, a polling based model isn't really the
right way to go, either.
So what we're going to do instead is,
we're going to define
a way to automatically publish an intent
to anybody who happens
to care about the status information that
Android's keeping track
of, like the battery levels or other,
other kinds of things.
You know, or, service, service quality,
you know, like your cellu-,
cellular signal strength.
You might have something that says, your
cell signal's getting weak or what not.
You move into an open area or whatever.
So whenever this information changes you
want to be able to notify
interested subscribers that something has
happened,
that they may be, concerned with.
So here's how this works.
In Android, we define these things called
broadcast receivers.
We've talked about them before.
And they have these on received hook
methods,
that get called back at the appropriate
time.
And you could register these things by
using a variety of means.
You can register them by register
receiver, you can register them using
things like the underline medafest files,
you know, whatever you need to do.
And what will happen there is that, that
tells
the underlying system, it actually tells
the activity manager services,
I care about these kinds of things so if
those kind of things occur, let me know
about it.
So, in this case a phone app might say
something
like, hey, I want to know if the battery's
getting low.
And then later when the battery service
through
some lower level means connected probably
to hardware device
drivers and that may actually pull stuff
periodically, when
it starts to realize the battery is
getting low,
it will go ahead and broadcast out the
battery
low option as an intent and that will
inform
anybody who happens to care about this
that the
battery is getting low and then each of
those
things can do whatever they need to do in
order to be able to handle this.
They can pop up a dialog, or they could,
you
know, shut down certain system services,
they could dim the screen.
They might drop your call it might, you
know,
change the speed at which you're
downloading a file.
You know, whatever it is you're trying to
do different parts
of the system might react to battery being
reduced in different ways.
And, of course, battery is not the only
resource that might get low right?
Memory can get low so you may have other
kinds
of things to keep track of memory
availability, as well.
Just as quick note, this example like many
examples have
a variety of patterns involved, so we've
got activators involved
here, we've got brokers involved here,
typically we've got proxies
involved here, there's all kinds of other
stuff taking place.
But the particular pattern we're going to
talk about here
that does this kind of magic callback
approach, when something
happens you're interested in, that pattern
is called the publisher-subscriber
pattern and this is a very, very, very
popular pattern.
It goes by different names we'll see that
in a second.
So, one name is publish-subscribe.
The publish-subscribe is really dealing
with the actions or the verbs.
Where as publisher-subscriber is dealing
with the nouns, the things
and most patterns are described, many
patterns are described in terms
of the nouns like adapter or bridge, not
the actions, adapting,
You don't have the adapting pattern you
have the adapter pattern.
So here we call it the
publisher-subscriber pattern.
And the intent of this pattern is to
notify, event handlers,
which could be subscribers, or observers,
or broadcast receivers, or whatever you
want to call them, when something
interesting happens based on publishers,
or observables or subjects or whatever you
want to call these things.
When somebody's state changes, when
something involves, like the
battery becomes low or someone notices a
battery becomes low.
So, when an interesting state change
occurs, you want to be
able to notify interested subscribers that
something has taken place.
There's also a gang of four pattern that's
very
similar, although not identical to
publisher-subscriber, that's the observer
pattern.
And the intent of the observer pattern
is to define one-to-many dependency
between objects
so that when one object changes state, all
the dependents are notified and updated.
So they're very similar to each other.
In my, in my mind, the observer pattern is
very,
very, very commonly used, if you're within
the single address space.
You have a listener or something,that
gets, you know, a bunch
of listeners that get dispatched
when something occurs, and the
publisher-subscriber
pattern is typically used more when you're
trying to go across
ad, address spaces, although that
distinction is somewhat a bit artificial.
Take a look here for more information
about observer.
So, let's talk about when you might apply
the publisher-subscriber pattern.
So, one way or one time to apply it is
when an abstraction has more than one
aspect, two aspects.
One of them depends on the other, right.
So, in our example here, we had battery
voltage, or battery level, that was one
thing.
And then we had things who depend on
battery level,
like the phone app or something else on
the phone.
So there's, there's multiple aspects and
one depends on the other.
The behavior of some services or some apps
may depend on the state of the battery.
Likewise, when a change occurs to one
object, like
to the battery level, we want to tell
potentially many others.
Might be zero, might be one, might be n
where n could be very large.
So we don't, and we don't really
necessarily know how many there are.
At least the guy who is monitoring the
changes doesn't know how many there are.
So you may have to notify an unknown
number of things so we
have to notify a number of things and
those things may need to change.
And something else just to make it
interesting, not every
object is always interested in every
change by every other object.
So there may be some need to be able
to filter or widow down the number of
interested
subscribers that need to be informed when
some publisher
decides it wants to tell people that
things have happened.
So those are the conditions under which
you would typically apply this particular
pattern.
So here are some of the structure of
participants.
As always this maps just beautifully onto
the stuff that you find in Android.
There's something called an event, which
in android is an intent.
That's easy.
There is something called a subscriber,
which is
a thing that consumes events, in Android
that's a
broadcast receiver, among other stuff,
there's other things besides
broadcast receivers like content observers
and stuff like that.
There's a way to filter, so that every
subscriber does not receive every event.
That's done through something called the
intent
filters, there's various ways to define
those.
You can define them programatically,
dynamically, you
can define them statically through
manifest files.
It's up to you, what you want to do.
You have a publisher, which is used to
create,
the events in the first place, or the
intents.
In Android that's typically a service or
an activity.
And then finally you have something that
serves as
the mediator, the traffic cop that routes
the information,
the intents, the events from the publisher
to one
or more subscribers if their filtering
criteria is satisfied.
That's what's called the event channel.
And in Android that's handled by a variety
of things, the context, working in
conjunction with the
activity manager service so those are all
the
different pieces mapping, the concepts of
the pattern to
the pieces of Android and that should be
helpful because once you understand how it
works in
Android pretty much every other intent
system and
event system has a lot of things in
common.
Here's a quick summary of the dynamic
interactions in this pattern
starts out by having the subscribers
register with the event channel.
Some systems require the publisher to
register,
as well, but it's, that's more optional.
It's almost always the case subscribers
register.
And the event channel keeps track of that
stuff.
When the publisher detects something
that's changed, that it thinks other may
be interested in, it then goes ahead and
notifies, it publishes the event.
That goes to the event channel, the event
channel says there are all these
different subscribers, let me see which
one
actually care about this particular type
of event.
Maybe it goes to everybody, maybe it goes
to
some select few, maybe it goes to some
quorum.
Lots of different alternatives there.
Those things get pushed along and
eventually
they get delivered to the actual
subscribers
themselves, who will then go ahead and
consume the event in one way or another.
Any questions about that?
Pretty, pretty conventional thing to do.
You'll find this used all over the place.
Probably too much, actually in, in
practice.
So there's a number of benefits
and liabilities of using the
publisher-subscriber pattern.
On the good side it allows publishers and
subscribers to vary independently.
You can have different the publishers
don't have to know about the subscribers.
The subscribers don't have to know about
the publishers.
They just have to know about something in
common which is the event channel.
You register.
You get notified.
You don't really have to care about that
kind of stuff.
Think about services that you might use or
you
might be aware of that might work this
way.
Twitter is a good example.
If you want to follow Lady Gaga, why you'd
want to do this, I don't know.
But if you want to follow Lady Gaga, or
Miley Cyrus because
you like to see a train wreck unfolding in
real time, you know.
Then you can subscribe to their, their
Twitter account.
And they don't really know who you are.
They don't really care who you are, by the
way.
They just want to know that you're a fan.
And so as they go about the crazy things
they do
in their lives and tweet about it, you'll
be informed, right?
So it's this sort of the anonymous
communication.
Then can, in fact, it doesn't even really
have
to be could be them, it could be their
handler out there just trying to patch
over a
rough spot to make it look good or
whatever.
So the publishers and subscribers can vary
and be different.
You can add any number of subscribers you
may want.
So you might have one, you might have
zero, you might have a
gazillion, and the different subscribers
may choose
to treat the data in different ways.
So, you know, some people when they get
the tweet of, of, Miley Cyrus's
latest, you know, music award thing, they
may immediately rush out and watch the
video.
Other people may call the network to
complain.
Other people will, you know, take a shot
of, of vodka, you know, whatever they do.
Different people can react in different
ways
to the information that's coming out their
way.
And so you can customize the behavior.
So those are some really powerful positive
things.
And what you end up with when all is said
and done by using Publisher-Subscriber or
event based communication of
this form, is you end up being able to
have
a loosely coupled connection between
different parts of your system.
Some things are more evolvable, they are
more customizable.
They don’t have to all variant lockstep.
And there's more, even more sophisticated
things you can do here.
There's some down sides though.
One of the problems you can get into is
you can end up with, because
the publishers and subscribers don't
really know
about each other you can end up in
situations where you have a storm of,
of communication taking place that nobody
really realizes
they're propagating and because of the
aggregate
effect of this the system becomes wildly
overloaded.
There was a great example, if you take a
look at E-mail storm on Wikipedia
there's a bunch of examples of E-mail
storms and there's a great example of
Microsoft
where they pretty much melted down the
Microsoft exchange server, 15 years ago or
so
because they, people hit reply all and
they
didn't realize that everybody kept hitting
reply all.
The story I always like to tell is, back
in the early
days of e-mail when I was first starting
out as a grad
student in the late to mid 80s, people
weren't as, they weren't
as, as accustomed to getting lots of
unwanted e-mail as they are today.
I mean, let's face it, anybody these days
who gets upset about a piece of spam is
probably picking up, you know, probably
focusing on
the wrong thing in life to get upset
about.
You know, you get, you get a email you
weren't expecting.
You don't just blow up and go ballistic.
I mean, those people in Nigeria really do
want
to give you all that money for god's sake,
right?
So, so the, the point is we're kind of
accustom to it.
Way back in the day that wasn't the case.
And so what happened was funny.
You be, you'd end up on mailing in list
that maybe you
didn't know you gotten subscribed to
somehow, or you'd forgotten, or you
weren't expecting to get something and
somebody would send a posting out
that was a little bit off topic, or you
just didn't know
why you were on the mailing list and
rather than just doing
what you did today where you just ignore
it and delete it,
instead what people would do is they would
reply back to the
mailing list and say please stop sending
irrelevant emails to this list.
And of course that would be broadcast to
everybody on the list too.
And everybody else would start chiming in,
why
am I getting all this email I don't want?
You know, before you know it, every person
is sending responses back to every other
person.
So it becomes this, this sort quadratic
explosion of emails.
And the whole system bogs down and the
internet
comes to a, to a screeching halt and so
on.
That's an example of an email storm.
And that occurs because you don't really
realize
that you're actually broadcasting your
messages to everybody.
You think you're just replying to one
thing
but it's actually exploding it out into
multiple places.
Another problem you get into and, and you
probably
also get this with mailing lists you may
be on.
You end up getting a lot of stuff that you
don't really care about.
People just sort of send it out to, you
know, let's say you subscribe to
the red zone channel and so you're
going to
get informed every time someone scores a
touchdown.
Well maybe you only care if your team
scores a touchdown
and you don't care if other teams you
don't like score touchdowns.
In fact it might even irritate you to find
out that
certain teams are scoring lots of
touchdowns so you might want
to be able to have some way of winnowing
out the
stuff you care about from the things that
you don't care about.
So if you're not careful you can end up
with lots of extra data that you don't
really want.
Some good examples of known uses pub
sub middle wear uses these patterns
pattern galore.
Things like web services notifications,
date of distribution
service, java messaging service, the
corporate notification service.
All kinds of things in that space do this
pattern.
And the more sophisticated ones [SOUND]
really go off the deep end in terms
of being able to have sophisticated
support
for quality of service and other
capabilities.
And then there's, the smart phone event
notification systems, like we have in
Android.
So they, things like the, the intent
service and the binder framework and all
the other things, broadcast receivers,
those are
all examples of this pattern as well.
So, the bottom line here, is that
publisher subscriber
helps you avoiding hard coding
dependencies, between publishers and
subscribers.
So, this things change in a [UNKNOWN] You
have less re-work to do.
In order to take advantage of changes that
may occur, in terms of numbers of stuff.
What they do and response to stuff, and so
on.
And also, subscribers and publishers can
come and go, and new types can be
introduced to the system, often times
without
having to make changes to what's already
there.
And that's one of the powerful features of
advanced pub sub middleware.
It's very change resilient in a lot of
ways.
And the other nice thing is you don't end
up having to pull stuff.
You get informed when things happen, and
you don't have
to sit there and repeatedly ask questions,
ask questions, ask questions.
Chewing up valuable resources including
your time without
really knowing about anything until it
actually happens, right.
So, so those are basically the, that's
basically an overview of the publisher
subscriber pattern.
Any questions about the pattern?
In terms of what it's intending to do?
[MUSIC]