[MUSIC]
Today we're going to continue with our
discussions relating to
threading and synchronization in Android
and what we're going to
do now and for the next class is start to
discuss some of the patterns that underlie
the Android concurrency.
Idioms and mechanisms that we've been
talking about things like handlers,
messages, runnables, a sync tasks and
other capabilities like the looper.
So speaking of looper, looper we're
going to start off by talking about
looper's.
So you may remember in one of
the discussions we had fleetingly in last
class
I mentioned how a looper is, there can
only be on looper per thread in Android.
And if you take a look at the
documentation, it explains that fact.
If you poke around, by the way, on Stack
Overflow, you'll see a lot
of people complaining about there only
being
one looper in Android and running across
problems.
So, if you ever run into problems with
loopers, uh,be aware that other people
have run
into them as well, and Stack Overflow has
a lot of good discussion of this topic.
So, it's an interesting question.
How might you go about ensuring that
there's only one looper per thread?
It's certainly a worthwhile design
exercise to think about briefly.
And, if you think about it very long, your
first temptation
might be to try to design some kind of
looper registry.
So, as I show in this example here, we
have a, looper
registry, which is a static hashmap that's
nestled inside of our looper class,
and when the prepare method is called, the
prepare method is the
method that checks to see whether or not
there's more than one looper.
What we could do, is we could go ahead and
synchronize on
the looper class, because this is a static
method we can’t use this.
We’d synchronize on something that we know
would be there like the looper class.
And then, we would go ahead and we would
look up on the hash map
to see whether or not we already have a
looper registered with this thread ID.
So in this particular case, we have a
hashmap that maps.
Thread ID, which is along to looper.
And if we get back something from this get
operation and
it's not null, then that means someone has
already registered a looper.
And that's a, that's a no, no.
So we can't, we can't do that.
We have to quit first.
We have to get rid of this.
So, in that case we're going to throw a
run time exception.
And bail out say, hey only, only one
looper can be configured per thread.
If we don't find a looper pre-registered,
then we go ahead and we add our looper
we make a new looper and we stick it in
our looper registry under the thread ID.
And then we release the lock in the
synchronized block.
Okay.
Any questions, any comments about that
particular solution?
So arguably it will work in the sense of
it'll tell us if we have more than one
looper.
Whoops.
Let's fix this problem.
Yes, sir.
So, as this looper's getting messages?
Uh-huh.
And it's processing them, is it doing work
on itself?
Or on the other thread that passed
[UNKNOWN] I don't understand.
That's a really good question.
So, keep in mind a couple things.
First of all you can have only a single
thread
in your, in your whole activity, in your
whole application.
And so you can do work, and if you have
something that's going to take
a while to run, or you'd like to have it
run at some later point.
You can go ahead and, and post that or
send that
and that'll end up going back into your
own looper thread.
So that's how you kind of defer things
till
future processing so that's one way to do
things.
And if you're really gung ho on not having
threads that's kind of how you program.
That's a little tedious of course and and
it means, you can't do anything that
blocks for
any length of time because otherwise
you'll get
the, the dreaded application not
responding exception, or dialog.
The other approach, which is what we've
been talking about.
And we'll, we'll actually talk about this
further next class, is
the concept of having multiple threads,
the background threads, if you will.
And they're doing stuff, and they can
block.
And when they're done, they're going to
pass messages from
themselves in separate threads back to the
main UI thread.
And the way they would do that, there are
various ways to do that,
but one way they'd do that is they would
take a handler that would, was
created in the UI thread so it had to have
been created in the
UI thread and that's because we want it to
be associated with the UI thread.
And well actually, that's another example
of what we're about to talk about is if
you take a look at the handler
implementation,
it, it knows the thread that was created.
It keeps tracking it and its constructor.
Depending on which constructor you'll use,
of course.
So in this case, other threads are doing
work and their hand being the work through
messages or intervals off to the looper
thread,
the, to the UI thread, which wants a
looper.
And, that uses under the hood.
We haven't really talked about this in
detail.
But under the hood uses some kind
of inter-process communication mechanism,
that goes and uses
low level descriptors and so on in order
to move data from one thread to another.
So that's typically how that works.
So think about it like this.
There's various ways to think about this,
we'll talk at length next class about
the active object pattern, which is a
variant to what's used in this whole
affair.
But basically, you can think about a, a
chef at a, at a fast food restaurant
where people, people like clerks or
cashiers give the chef orders to fulfill.
And so the chef might have a, a list of
orders or a queue of orders, a queue of
pending orders.
And so the cashiers would be responsible
for taking the orders.
Imagine, like a Wendy's hamburger
restaurant or something like that.
The chef, the, the cashiers will be
responsible for taking the orders.
They're so, so, like, the, the handlers,
if you will, or the threads,
and they go ahead and they use the queue
interface, which might be
as simple as taking a piece of paper and
sticking it onto a
revolving merry-go-round, like, mechanism,
so that the
chef knows what things to handle next.
We'll talk more about that when we talk
about active object.
Okay.
Any other questions about this particular
approach?
So the downside with this particular
approach-
I was just [CROSSTALK].
Yeah.
Is it supposed to say ensuring one looper
per thread?
Yes.
[INAUDIBLE].
Whoops.
Does it say on?
Yep.
Oh.
[LAUGH]
Let's change that, that's the kind of
thing I would forget.
All right.
So any questions about the particular
issues of the design?
So the downside with this approach of
course, is that we've got synchronization
taking
place, so we could end up with a, with a
bottleneck at least in theory.
If you had lots and lots and lots of, of
threads running loopers.
They'd all be kind of coordinating here
and that could end up being inefficient.
So, the question is, what's a better
solution to do?
So the solution we're going to talk about,
which
is actually what Android does, so it's not
just
a good idea, it's actually what's done in
Android,
is to apply something called the thread
specific storage pattern.
And this is realized in Java through
something called the Thread Local Class.
And this basically gives you a up
seemingly global object, when in
fact the implementation of the object is
specifically to every thread of control.
So, it looks like a global object to the
outside world,
but when you access it, you're actually
accessing thread specific state.
So, here is an example of how this works,
we'll,
we'll look at, a more of this example
later when
we come back after talking more detail
about how the
pattern is specified and how the
implementation of Android works.
Basically the looper contains a
thread-local object,
which is a generic that's customized by
looper.
And as you can see here, what prepare does
is it goes
in and says, ha anybody stored something
into thread specific storage yet?
And if the answer is yes, then we're in
trouble because we've got already gone
through and initialized ourselves.
If the answer is no, this returns null and
so we're okay.
And then we go down here and we create a
new looper and we set it into thread's
local storage.
And what's interesting about this as we'll
see shortly
is that there's no locking operations
required anywhere here.
So all the locking operations are moved
outside
of the thread, and so there actually is
no synchronization overhead at all, even
though it
looks at first glance very much the other
example.
Right.
It looks like you got an object and you're
accessing it by calling get.
In this particular case, what you're
accessing is actually getting to
thread-specific storage.
So we're going to talk about that.
It's a really interesting pattern.
It's a very cool.
Not very well understood and should be
used
sparingly of course, for the reasons we'll
discuss.
So take a look at thread local HTML page
on the Android site and it
will talk to you more about what thread
local is and we'll talk more about that.
Okay, so this is not just a random
assortment of class and methods.
This is a particular instantiation of a
pattern,
the pattern appeared in the posting into
book.
It's called thread-specific storage.
The intent of this pattern is to allow
multiple threads
to use one logically global access point,
object for example.
To retrieve instances of objects that are
local to a thread,
stored local to a thread, without
incurring locking overhead on every
access.
So you don't have to incur the overhead
of locking, but you're getting stuff
that's thread specific.
And there therefore, capable of being used
without having to worry about intention.
And this pattern is used very, very widely
in Dewey frameworks and threads, and
threading frameworks.
If you take a look here.
It's in the post in the 2 book, but
you can also look here and find the
pattern online.
And it's quite interesting, it's
documented using C plus,
plus, but it applies quite nicely to Java
too.
So when would you want to use this thing?
Well you want to use this thing if you
want a concurrent program that is
both easy to program and efficient, which
is sometimes kind of hard to do.
And of course, efficient means different
things to
different people but in this particular
case is.
What we want to be able to do is make it
easy to program, so it doesn't require
all kinds of special purpose programming
tricks, but we
don't want people to have to know anything
about locking.
You just want to be able to access this
stuff and
have it be magically thread safe and
atomic, and so on.
Often in life, there's trade-offs, right?
So they always talk about good fast cheap.
Pick two of three, right.
So here's a case where we're going to get
simplicity of programming and efficiency.
You don't always get that.
Now, there are some limitations to this of
course, but we'll talk about that later.
The original reason why people came up
with thread-specific storage was kind of
interesting.
The original reason was people have a lot
of legacy code that they'd written, which
only had
a single thread of control in it and that
code accessed global resources without
passing parameters to functions.
And what that meant was, when people
started to try to use this
legacy code in modern multi threaded
systems,
they had a problem in certain places.
And we're going to talk more about this
particular
problem when we get to the known uses
discussion.
But one of the classic, classic examples
where this
is a big issue is in the context of errno.
Does anybody know what errno is?
You'd have to be sort of a C or C plus,
plus programmer to really.
No error known.
And you'd have to be sort of a systems
programmer.
Yeah.
So then the integer that holds the last
error number returned by some operation?
That's right.
So, historically, so what errno, it's a
value that
stores the last reason why something
failed if something fails.
And historically it was stored as an int,
and it was a global int, and so if
you wanted to access errno, you just sort
of said extern int errno, and there it
was.
There's a huge problem when you start
trying to use things
like errno in concurrent programs,
however, and this example illustrates
this.
So, imagine we have two threads, thread T1
and thread
T2, and one comes along and does a receive
operation.
And for whatever reason that receive
operation
can't make progress because, it's flow
controlled.
And so it gives back the, a minus one
with the error no value set to
ewouldblock, which
says it would block if we were to, to
actually wait on this thing, so it's flow
controlled.
Okay, and between the point when we return
from receive and check the value of errno.
Another thread comes along also calls
recv, which is a system call and for
whatever reason that, that got interrupted
so it got the E enter errno value set.
Well, what happens here of course is if T2
is preempted and T1 starts to run again.
T1 will say, uh-huh, I have a minus one
value for received, but my error value is
E enter.
And be completely confused.
Because it's trying to access a global
that
is not protected by any kind of
synchronization mechanism.
Now how might we, how might we fix this?
Well we might fix this the same way that
we tried to fix
the stuff earlier while I was showing you
about the, the registry for loopers.
But that is horribly broken, just
hideously broken.
Number one, it would require everybody to
put locks
around errno and number two, it really
wouldn't even work
because even if you, you'd have to put the
blocks around the point where you made the
receive call.
And when it returned, you'd still have to
hold the lock, and then you check errnos,
so you'd have unbelievable, contention in
your program,
and it would just be a big mess.
So, instead of doing that kind of stuff,
people use thread-specific storage, and
that way, each specific thread gets its
own specific version of errno, and so it.
It can set it and check it at its leisure,
never
having to worry about contention or race
conditions on that particular variable.
So, we'll talk more about that later.
Okay, here's the structure and
participants of this particular pattern,
and it's kind of interesting, because
there's a bunch of tool
kits that give you building blocks of some
of this stuff,
but they're somewhat unsatisfying if you
don't do the whole pattern.
So I'm going to talk about the different
pieces in a term.
The first piece we're going to talk about
is the thread specific object proxy.
The purpose of this particular interface
class element module and
so on, role a better word, is to try to
give
people a nice high level way of accessing
thread specific storage
so you don't have to take care of low
level details.
Some framework, some programming languages
make this easy, other frameworks, other
programming languages make it less easy,
Java is somewhere in the middle.
C is very much at the low end, you have to
build all this stuff yourself.
Java kind of gives you an intermediate
thing, the thread
local class is the thread specific object
proxy the ace
framework, which we'll see later, has some
really cool support
using C plus, plus delegation operator,
we'll look at that.
So that's one piece of the pie.
There's also something called the key
factory, and that's used to
make the ways to identify each of the
threads specific objects.
We're not going to talk much about that.
It doesn't really show up in Java.
It's kind of hidden from you by the thread
local class.
The next thing which is really the key
workhorse
here is something that's called the thread
specific object set.
This is a map or some kind of data
structure that will take a key which
corresponds to
the object that you're dealing with and it
will
give you back a pointer to a
thread-specific object.
And we'll talk about how that works later.
In the case of Android and Java,.
It's threadlocal.values, that's the thing
the
data structure, that keeps track of this.
Yeah.
Is it a lot similar to the registry idea
that you were talking about?
It is, absolutely.
The difference, that's a great question.
So, the question is isn't this sort of
like the registry we're talking about?
Absolutely.
The difference is that that registry that
we saw was shared by all threads.
And therefore you have to lock it.
The thread-specific object set is either
logically or physically local to
a thread, so it's a map, but it's only in
one thread.
And each thread has one typically.
We'll, we'll talk about different ways to
implement this in a second.
Yeah, that's a great observation.
There's a thing called thread.local
values,
and we'll look at that momentarily.
And then the last piece of the puzzle is
the thread-specific object.
This is actually the thing that, that does
whatever it does, right?
It's something that you're going to store.
And for that specific storage.
And a particular example we're going to
talk about here of course, is the looper.
So that's what we're going to put inside
specific storage.
But of course, you could put other things
into that specific storage as well.
Okay.
Here's the dynamic view.
And there's, there's a whole different
variant, I'm, I'm
just focusing on a piece of this whole
thing.
If you read the pattern description it'll
give you more details of this.
So typically what happens is here, you
come along, depending
on how powerful your thread-specific
storage interface is, and your language.
And you invoke some method on an instance
of a thread-specific object proxy.
Now, the goal of this is to make it look
like to the application developer.
That you're just making a method call on
an object.
They shouldn't have to know what's in
thread specific storage and what's not.
They should just want to make a method
call and leave it
up to the implementation to ferret out
where the actual stuff resides.
And we'll see how that works in a second.
So you make a method call under the scenes
that goes and figures out what thread
you're in, figures out what key your
associating
this particular method call on the object
ID.
And it goes and it looks up in the object
specific thread-specific object set and
it gets you back at thread specific object
and it returns it back to the proxy.
And in certain cool implementations like
in C plus, plus and like in ACE.
Then it goes ahead and it, it
automatically delegates the method
call to the thread-specific object without
you having to do anything else.
So it just kind of magically forwards to
the call.
And then you get the result back.
So that's kind of how things work.
So you invoke a method on a proxy.
It gets the underlying thread specific
object, and
then it automatically invokes a method on
the object.
You'll see that Java doesn't quite go that
far because Java doesn't really have
anything quite like
the delegation operator in C plus, plus
but
I'll show you that also it's, it's pretty
cool.
All right.
So how does this actually work under the
hood?
What's the, the technique?
So, there's a couple things you gotta
think about.
First thing you gotta do is implement some
kind of thread-specific object proxy, and
this is the
guy that mediates the access to the
underlying framework
that keeps track of all of these moving
parts.
And, essentially what you're doing is
finding an interface for a variable.
They look just like your regular variable
object, but
each instance of it is stored in a
thread-specific way.
There are a couple different ways to do
this in, in ACE, we do it
by having a template class that's
parameterized
by the type you want to make
thread-specific.
And it uses the C plus, plus operator
arrow, which is the so called delegation
operator.
And I'll show you the implementation in a
second.
Other technologies work a slightly
different way.
But you need to define it somehow.
The next thing you need to do is implement
the thread-specific object sets.
And as sharp pointed out, there's a couple
different ways to do this.
One, one way to do this which is typically
the way things work if you use
thread-specific storage that's actually
implemented as part of
the run time system of your, your
threading library.
Right.
So if your, your using like Java Threads
or your
using PASIC-P's Threads or something like
that has this built in.
And what they'll particularly do is that
they'll reserve some space
or a pointer to store some space in each
thread control block.
So every application thread, or every
thread you have has some
space that it's used to hold the thread's
specific storage map.
So that goes back to what you're asking,
each
thread has its own map as opposed to
sharing them.
So that's one way to do things.
And that turns out to be very efficient,
for a variety of reasons.
The other way to do it is to have thread
external, thread specific object sets.
You would typically do this if you were
trying emulate
thread-specific storage in an environment
that not, that's not natively supported.
For example, some earlier implementations
of embedded operating systems
like early versions of Ex Works lack
Thread-Specific Storage.
Other implementations of things like
windows.
Have really goofy thread-specific storage.
Where you only get a very small number of
thread-specific
storage objects per thread like 32 or 64
some small number.
So in those environments you may have to
emulate this.
In that case, you would have some kind of
data structure and then you would mediate
access to it.
This is obviously less desirable though
because
you end up with some locking overhead.
Then you have to figure out these data
structures that, that map
things appropriately and it's sort of two
things that you gotta think about.
One is, how do you map the keys to thread
specific objects?
And the other is how do you map the thread
IDs to thread-specific object sets.
So there's two parts of this thing.
So typically what you do, the most common
way to do
it is you have this data structure on a
per thread basis.
And if you have a fixed number of
thread-specific objects
per thread, you might have an array of
these things.
So you might have an array of 64 or
32 thread-specific slots you can store
thread-specific objects in.
The nice thing about that is it's super
fast, because it's just an index.
The key is just an index into that table
or array or vector.
If you want to support a much larger
number, then you're
going to have to use a data structure
that's capable of expanding.
And the most common thing to use there is
some kind of hash map.
So that's another way that you could do
it, you could store a hash map and
so you would look things up and find
the thread specific object that was stored
here.
So, leaving aside implementation details
from logical
point of view, each thread specific
object,
or each thread specific object proxy
corresponds
to a row in a two dimensional table.
And each thread corresponds to a column in
this table.
And when you have a particular object in
a particular thread access, a particular
key, that
will, that two pull will get you to
a pointer or reference to the
thread-specific object.
Now what's interesting about this, is that
the
object itself could actually be any old
object.
So the object isn't necessarily thread
specific it's
the access to the object that's thread
specific.
Now 9 times out of 10 or 99 times out of a
100.
The object you're accessing is only
accessed by that thread.
But if you really want it to be perverse,
you could make
a pointer to some global object and stick
it in this thing.
It would be a bad idea because it
would defeat the purpose of having
thread-specific storage.
But it's not really the object that's
thread-specific It's
the access to the object that is being
thread-specific.
So it's, it's that combination of things.
It's, it's the thread ID, it's the
particular object,
it's the key, it's the proxy, it's all
these things.
That collaborate to get you to the
specific object that you care about.
All right.
So let's take a look and see how this
particular pattern is actually
implemented in Android, now that we've
sort of talked about the various pieces.
[SOUND] So, there's this class called,
thread local.
And that implements a thread-specific
storage pattern, or a variant of it.
The main difference is that in Android, it
doesn't give you the full blown proxy.
So in the C plus, plus versions we were
talking about with delegation
operator, you have a full blown proxy, you
invoke a method on that proxy.
It goes in under the hood, grabs the
thread specific object, and then
re-delegates to it.
In Java you can't quite do that.
So what you have to do is you first have
to call a get,
on the thread specific object proxy which
is really more just like a wrapper.
It's not really a proxy at this point.
It's just an interface or a class with
some methods, put and get.
That goes behind the scenes, get's the
underlying thread-specific object it
returns it to you
and once you've got that thing then you
make a method call on that thread-specific
object.
So notice you have to do two calls here in
the Java model.
Where is in the full blown pattern, all
you have to do is make
one methods call it gets the thing for you
and it delegates it automatically.
I will show you how to implement that in
just a second just so you'll know.
All right.
So, so that's, that's one part of it.
And if you take a look at the Thread Local
header file, you'll learn more about that.
So, all threads share the same
thread-local object.
So, thinking about our looper example that
we had before.
You're going to have the looper and it's
going to have the, The get method on it.
So you go get the looper, and what that's
going to do,
is it's going to you know in this case it
would be the
thread local optic that we had defined
specially for our particular use
case or Android is defined specifically
for the use case for the looper.
And in fact let's just a step back here
and see what that was called.
That was called S Thread Local.
So, you come back here.
You know, so it's, it's really more
like sthreadloca: [SOUND] That's a little
bit more like what it's actually doing.
I'll come back and fix all that up later.
Well what that says is that the that's the
particular thing that's playing this role.
And then [SOUND] Each thread calls the get
method.
Is actually going to get back a different
object.
So, one thread versus others is actually
going
to get back a different looper for
example.
So internally, I'm going to look at the
implementation here in a second.
The way it works is that there's, this
data structure called values.
It's a strut, or a class.
There's an instance of this thing called
local values.
And every thread has that.
And so that's used to actually keep track
of the thread specific data.
And it uses a hash like mechanism, which
we'll look at in a second too.
And then the last thing is why you put all
those together, it'll find you the looper
that we want.
Okay, so if you actually look at the code,
it's kind of cool.
And I'm going to show you the code here.
well, first of all, tell you about the
code.
Then we'll go look at it.
So, thread-local.set figures out what the
appropriate values map
is, in other words, the one that's for
that thread.
Based on the current thread ID, so if you
look here it says what thread am I in?
I'm in the current thread and it goes and
it looks up
in the current thread and it gives back
this list of values.
And assuming it's not null, then it goes
ahead and
it does a put operation on that
particular, values array.
Storing the value that was passed in here
under this for
this particular object that's its, it's
going to be its key essentially.
All right?
And notice there's no synchronization.
If you look through this code, there's no
locking in it, at all.
That's the beauty of thread-specific
storage.
So let's go over here and take a look at
the code.
It's somewhat instructive to do this.
All right.
So let's take a look at set.
So here's this is just the code we just
looked at.
Here's the code for set.
You can see what it does.
If you take a look at things like what's
values.
So what values does, oops, that's
initialized values.
So what values does is it goes and it
takes a
look at the thread and it says, give me
your local values.
So if you take a look at thread.
[SOUND] So there's thread, the thread
class's local
value's data member is a thread
locals.value object.
And if you go back over here.
And you look for values, here is values.
So it's a per thread map of thread local
instance values, the whole thing is kind
of strangely recursive.
And you can see that they start out
picking an initial
size, sixteen always to the power of two,
and there's something called.
Tombstone, which I think they use for
deleted,
when items get deleted they, they,they
recycle them.
And then if you look down here, there's
just a bunch of code that does various
things.
But this is basically how all the
different implementation parts work, and I
think if you take a look here there's a
method called put or.
There we go.
Here's put.
So put takes a thread local key, which in
this case was this.
And a value, which is whatever we're going
to store like, the looper for example.
And it basically goes ahead and, does some
operations to store things into the, into
the map.
And there's a whole bunch of different
things
that they do and there's also stuff that
they do which you'll see in a second in
the case of the other operations to find.
Okay, so that was set and then there's
get.
So get's a little bit different it's a
little bit more complicated.
It uses the same technique of basically
you figure out
what thread it's in going and getting the
thread local.
map, if you will from that particular
thread.
And then it's got some more stuff that's
going on.
Let's go take a quick look at that.
Basically, if you see here.
Let's take a look at, get.
So, get is optimized for the fast path.
As you can see, it tries to look some
stuff up
and see if it's already available in some
kind of cache.
And if it's there it just goes ahead and
indexes to it so it's very fast.
If it's not there, then it's got this
method called get after miss.
And this is more complicated it has to do
more things.
So you can see this is going to search
through
the table so it takes longer to do that.
So, basically it kind of has this optimize
for the common case or the pattern
of, you know, trying of locality of
reference, or, things that have been
accessed recently.
We want to cache those, we can get back
and get them quickly.
So that's why you might find it you have
lots and lots of thread-specific objects.
They might perform differently over time
if you run.
Okay.
So that's the thread local implementation.
Now how does this stuff get used, well
this
goes back to what we looked at before you
can
see that the looper class uses a thread
local object
in order to make sure that there's only
one looper.
We looked at that before.
The locking overhead that goes on there.
There's also a bunch of helper methods
that are part of this implementation.
That are used to get the tread-specific
loopers.
So this is a kind of an interesting one.
This is one that's called myLooper.
And myLooper gets used in various places
in the looper implementation.
So you can see in the looper
implementation.
And this is odd, I think I know the reason
why
they do this and we'll see if you guys
know too.
They have something called message queue,
which is a data
member in the looper you can see it right
here.
And then the loop method, remember loop is
what actually runs the event loop that's
the thing
that sits there and waits for incoming
messages on
the message queue and dispatches them to
their target.
The first thing it does is it goes ahead
and says.
My looper.
Which goes and gets the thread specific
looper that this guy's associates with.
And if it checks to see if you've even
been initialized, if you've never
initialized a looper at
all, you haven't called prepare, for
example, and then
you try to run loop, it's going to blow
up.
And then look what it does.
It goes ahead and it takes the thread
specific looper, that fish out of thread
specific
storage, and it grabs that guys messages
queue
and stashes into this local message queue,
all right.
So, this is weird.
This is message queue up here, that's
whats being access here.
And then we go ahead and we cast that into
a local message queue.
Does anyone speculate why we do that.
And then the rest of the looping
operations are done after that.
[LAUGH]
I think it just locality reference moving
things into closer variables that can be
optimized better, and so on and so forth.
If we take a look over here at the code
for this thing [SOUND].
So here's, here's the looper.
Here's the looper's loop methods.
It grabs that guy.
It goes and stashes it away.
And then it just sits there and blocks in
that particular place.
Don't show me this message again.
Thank you.
Okay.
So this is the looper.
Take a look at my looper for example.
You can see where it gets used.
Basically, any time you want to refer to
the looper then it calls my looper.
And my looper as you can see just goes
ahead and fishes the data out of
thread-specific storage.
And we use that all the way though
whatever we
have to refer to the current looper that's
being accessed.
This also allows us of course to use
static methods because we
can fish out the thread-specific looper
because it doesn't live in an object.
It lives in a thread.
Not in a specific object.
I had mentioned earlier that there's also
the handler stuff.
As well, Let's see.
I thought the constructor.
Yeah, check this out.
So, you can see here that the handler
method-
Remember, that this goes back to what you
were asking on.
So, handlers when they're created based on
this constructor.
There's a couple of different constructors
that they have.
But, like the, the default handler
constructor.
Notice what it does, is if you don't do
anything else, it
goes ahead and it says, hey looper, give
me back my looper.
So that's going to get you back the thread
specific looper.
So if you call, if you create an object
handler in a thread.
It's going to live, it will be owned by
that thread.
And its constructor makes sure that that
happens.
So make sure you're careful where you
create your handlers.
Make sure you create them where you want
them to live and not some other place.
Okay.
So that's basically the way it's done in
Android.
There's a source code so let's talk about
the pro's and con's of this particular
pattern.
So the good news is, it's efficient in the
sense that you
don't need to have locks in order to
access the state, the data.
It's relatively easy to use.
As you can see here, it's pretty much like
programming regular Java code.
It's instructive at some point in your
life to try to figure out how to program
thread specific storage using the low
level C
POSIX P thread API which is unbelievably
convoluted.
We'll see a little snippet of it in a
second.
And you'll see why it's much better to
have wrappers and proxies to save your
life.
Speaking of wrappers, you can combine this
pattern with wrapper facade, which is
a pattern, it's another post of two
pattern, we'll talk about it later, in
order to be able to get portable access to
low-level system call APIs, which
makes your code more portable, makes your
code more reusable, so that's a benefit.
Java does that.
All the Java class libraries are wrapper
facades.
There's some downsides, however, probably
the main
downside with this approach is it ends up.
Encouraging people to use globals even
though
their thread specific globals they're
still globals.
And that has all the common down sides
with globals.
What, what's a good example of a common
down side with a global?
What are things why are globals considered
bad?
Why do they make you go like this?
Coupling.
You end up being coupled to a particular
context, and so, when
you try to move your code, you can't just
move a piece of
it, you have to move the whole thing, and
everything that the
globals, that accesses the globals, have
to come along with the other parts.
So it makes things much more tightly
coupled.
It also means that when you change stuff
that's related to a global, you run the
risk of breaking a lot of things, because
they depend on it in an implicit way.
It obscures the structure of the system.
So it hides things.
It's like fog or a smoke screen or
pollution or something like that.
You can't see as clearly what's going on.
That's, that's kind of another way
of looking at coupling and unwanted
dependencies.
And of course if you have a really
inefficient implementation of looking at
your thread specific objects.
Then, it might not actually be any better
than grabbing a lock.
Although, it might scale better if you had
lots and lots of threads.
So that's, that's an implementation
consideration.
But if you have really, really inefficient
things like you know, linear search
through
the list of thread specific objects, that
could slow you down quite a bit.
Okay.
So there's a bunch of known uses.
The best example of known use in my mind
is errno.
Which once multi-threading became popular
was, widely implemented as a
macro that caught, that turns into a call
to thread-specific operations so that
you don't have to worry about the race
conditions that would,
otherwise, occur if you were sharing
global error no variables between threads.
And, you can read more the Wikipedia link
about what error know is.
And, it's just interesting to know I
should
probably show the implementation of it's
kind of cool.
[SOUND] ACE has a really cool
implementation of this pattern.
Not surprisingly, because we wrote the
pattern
on originally what we were doing in Ace.
And, found other known uses to make a
pattern.
So it defines a class called ACE_TSS.
And ACE_TSS converts, it's a template, and
converts its parameter
into something that is easily accessible
in a thread specific way.
And it also, of course, provides nice
portability to different platforms.
If you read the paper here, it talks about
the ace implementation.
The way it works under the hood, is it
uses this really cool.
C plus, plus operator called operator
arrow, the so called delegation operator.
Can anybody explain the delegation
operator?
Does anybody know how it works?
So, anytime you say whatever on the left
arrow some method.
It will actually go in and execute your
code first.
If you can actually start training it if
you
return something that's not [INAUDIBLE]
but also over and operator.
Yep.
So, so it's really subtle.
And when you first see it it makes no
sense
what so ever but I'll break it down and
show you.
So here's a little snippet of code from
the HTS class this is the
most important piece this is the operator
arrow method, this is the delegation
operator.
You can see that this thing is a template
class it returns a pointer to
the type it's parametrized with and what
it's
called these are the those hideous low
level.
See style thread specific storage APIs
which nobody in
their right mind wants to program against
by the way.
So what it does, is it comes along and it
would have cached this key
underscore in its constructor somewhere
that, that
uniquely identifies the specific object we
care about.
And it says, hey, is there any data?
Is there a pointer that's previously been
initialized
for this particular key in this particular
thread before?
And if the answer is no, then it goes
ahead and makes a new one.
It creates a new thread sp, specific,
a new thread-specific instance dynamically
of type
type, and then it says go ahead and set
that thing into thread-specific storage.
So it dynamically allocates the type if it
doesn't already exist, if the object
doesn't already exist.
And it stores it in that thread in its
thread specific object set.
And when it's all done, it returns the
pointer to the allocated object.
So, either you allocated it this time or
this is the, a subsequent time through
this
particular code and so it just returns a
reference or a pointer to it at that
point.
So what comes back from operator arrow is
a pointer.
To an object that resides in thread
specific storage.
And then what you typically do is, as
Kristof
correctly noted, when you call a method
like this.
Let's say, that we have a class called
request count, that's just
going to keep a count of something, and
this is not thread safe code.
We create an instance of ACE_TSS called
request
count, so that's a variable of type
ACE_TSS.
Parameterized with this particular class.
And then we you say request_count arrow
increment,
it first calls this method here which is
the
delegation method which gets you a pointer
by
hook or by crook to the thread specific
data.
And then it returns it.
And then C plus, plus automatically
delegates to the
increment method, and so that goes ahead
and calls it.
So it looks like just a regular function
call, but in
fact it's actually accessing data that's
stored in a thread specific way.
So, it's very cool, very powerful.
All right, so to summarize this, Android
implements Thread-Specific Storage
via the Java Thread-Local class which
doesn't give you the whole
full blown mechanisms that you've got in
the thread specific
storage pattern but it gets you most of
the way there.
And Android uses this in order to get
access
to in order to insure you only have one
looper.
It also is used for the handlers as we
were talking about before.
All right.
Any questions?
[MUSIC]