[MUSIC]
So today, we're going to talk about the
last part of our Concurrency section, and
we're going to be describing the
Half-Sync/Half-Async Pattern,
and explaining how this gets applied in
Android.
So, what we're going to start out by doing
first, and you'll see I've changed the
format of my
slides a little bit, as I think about how
I'm
going to film these things eventually for
the Coursera Class.
I'm trying to keep each of the modules
down to about 20 minutes, and this stuff
is
starting to get about an hour long, so I
split it up into a couple of parts.
So we're first going to start off by
talking about what the
Half-Sync/Half-Async pattern is, and then
we're going to talk about how you would
implement
it, and apply it in the context of
Android.
I will also, as we discuss the pattern,
I'll
use Android as the running example to
motivate this.
But a lot of what I'll talk about is not
specific
to Android, which of course is the entire
point of patterns.
We use them to help see the generality and
design solutions, and the fact that
we're going to learn how they apply in
Android is kind of icing on the cake.
But what's important are the general
concepts.
So here's the context for this discussion.
So you often have concurrent systems that
have to perform both Synchronous
and Asynchronous communication, and these
things
have to communicate with each other
somehow.
So a good example of this and, and you're
got a
little taste of it now, and we're going to
do more
of it as we move along, is this kind of
threaded
download activity, or this threaded
download application that we're working
on.
So you've got some parts of the code that
are going to be interacting with the user,
by the,
the activity part, by the, the widgets and
so on,
and some other part that's going to do
some downloading.
So you have two different parts of the
code, at least two different parts.
Now if you think about it, when you
actually do the downloading
part, which is what you guys concentrated
on for this last assignment.
You're going to write some code that's
going
to end up blocking for some period of
time.
And that period of time, of course, is
going to be a function of a couple things.
It's going to be a function of how big the
file is
you're trying to download, and it's also
going to be a function of
things like how slow the network is, or
how fast the network
is, how loaded your computer is, and so on
and so forth.
So, you have to prepare yourself to avoid
the
dreaded application not responding
exception in dialogue that you'd have.
You have to prepare yourself to allow each
thread that's downloading to block.
Now again, there other ways of doing this,
but for this particular example we
want to be able to make it possible to
have the download thread block.
And for that, to be able to have
the simplicity of synchronization, we
don't want to have
to require the code to know a lot
about the more complicated interactions
with the asynchronous part.
because this code should be simple,
straightforward, easy to write, easy to
understand.
We also want to be able to allow
these Synchronous and Asynchronous
portions of the software
to be able to run efficiently and
correctly,
without making it too hard to program,
number one.
And number two, without having to require
the software
to be very inefficient from a scalability
point of view.
For example, what we're going to end up
doing here, is were going to have a user
thread, and then we're going to have
background
threads that are actually going to do the
work.
Now think about what you did for your
implementation, the way you wrote it.
What you did in your implementation for
now for
the, the runnable stuff, and for the, the
messages stuff.
Is every time a user wanted to download
something, you went ahead and just kicked
off a
thread, and that thread was spawned kind
of
on-demand as a sort of thread per request
model.
Now, you know, depending on how you do
your user interface, it
would take people pushing buttons really
fast to, to cause a problem.
But you can imagine a scenario where you
would launch lots and lots
and lots of threads, you have an unbound
number of threads being launched.
And eventually those threads start to cost
you something,
in terms of run time resources on your
device.
So you might not want to just let
unbridled use
of threading to be the way that you do
things.
So what we're going to do to address this,
is we're going to decompose the software
into two layers.
Now sometimes you even leave these as
layers, sometimes you just
think of them as two different
partitionings of the software solution
space.
And one part of the software's going to be
used to handle the Asynchronous
part, and the other part's going to be
used to handle the Synchronous part.
So you can see here for example in our
context of Android, the part that's doing
the user
interface interactions, is going to be
listening and waiting
for, for data to show up from various
things.
Like from a looper, or from people doing
touch events, or other kinds of
interactions you might have through
various kinds
of interface modalities, and those are
Asynchronous.
And they're Asynchronous in the sense that
we're
not really going to block while they run.
They, they need to run in a way that
doesn't block.
Non-blocking might be better term than
Asynchronous, but the point is
that they don't, you don't want to block
that thread of control.
And then we're going to have a bounded
number
of threads that are going to run in the
background,
and they're going to be given the actual
work to
do from the one thread in the user
interface part.
And then those background threads are
going to go ahead and do the processing.
And they're going to download the file,
and then report the results back
when they're finished, or any incremental
progress that may occur, along the way.
And to mediate the interaction, the
communication between the Async part and
the
Sync part, we're going to define a queuing
layer that sits in the middle.
Now there's a whole bunch of different
ways to do this
queuing layer, and we're going to look at
a couple of them.
We're going to look at a particular way of
doing
it in the context of the Async task
framework in Android.
But be aware, there's lots of other ways
to do this as well.
And when we talk about the known uses
of this pattern, you'll see that there's
many other
ways to implement this pattern that have
different
arrangements of queues and different parts
of the software.
Okay, so that's, that's essentially how
we're going to structure the solution.
In fact, that's essentially how Android
structures the solution
for some of the things we're going to talk
about.
So let's talk about this first as a
pattern.
And I guess what I should point out here,
and
let me just draw this to, to draw
attention to it.
This interaction that we're going to see
here, is actually the
Async Task framework, so that's how
Android actually solved this particular
problem.
So the, the pattern that is used to
document the way
in which these different pieces interact
with each other, is called
Half-Sync/Half-Async.
It's a POSA2 Concurrency pattern.
And the intent of this pattern is to
decouple
the Asynchronous, or Async portions of the
software from the
Synchronous, or Sync portions of the
software, by introducing
two intercommunicating layers, the Async
part and the Sync part.
And that allow, is going to allow us to be
able to simplify the programming without
throwing performance out the window.
because we're not going to end up trying
to spawn a thread for every piece of work.
We're going to spawn a pool of threads,
and then
use a queue to mediate access to that pool
of threads.
So that's how the pattern works, and we'll
talk later about, we'll talk shortly about
lots
of different known uses of this pattern,
as
it's applied to lots of things including
Android.
And if you take a look here, this is in
the POSA2
book, it's also in this paper that you can
get at my website.
So when would you apply a pattern like
this?
And as we talk through the applicability,
let's kind of relate it back to
what's going on in, in Android just to
make this discussion a bit more concrete.
So we want to be able to make performance
efficient and scalable.
But we also want to make sure that using
Concurrency simplifies our lives, as
opposed to complicating them more.
We really don't want the application
developers to have to
know about locking, for example, that
should be hidden from them.
We don't want to have the application
developers know about queueing
of messages on synchronized queues, that
should be hidden from them.
We don't want the application developers
to know
about spawning threads, that should be
hidden from them.
So we're trying to hide all
the complexities, the lower level
accidental complexities
of programming Concurrency, and we're
actually trying
to hide some of the inherit complexities.
We're trying to hide the scheduling, we're
trying to hide the synchronization.
Maybe even dealing with some deadlock
issues here, and so on and so forth.
We're trying to make those things as
transparent as possible for the
developers, so they don't have to worry
about that kind of stuff.
We also apply this pattern where there are
different kinds of operations,
that need to be able to run in different
ways and different contexts.
So you might have short duration
operations that don't
run for very long, like adding two numbers
together.
It might be overkill to do those things
concurrently, you're not going to
get any benefit, you might as well just go
ahead and do them.
There's also longer running operations,
like downloading a file, or
doing some kind of image processing, where
things may take longer.
So, you may want to run those in their own
threads of control.
There are also issues of blocking versus
non-blocking, and
polling versus waiting, and all those
kinds of things.
So there's different kinds of operations
that you may have,
and you want to be able to partition where
those
operations run, in a way that's easy to
understand and
doesn't get out of control, in terms of
the complexity.
By the way, this particular pattern is
very widely applied in operating system
kernels, as we'll see, and it's
also widely applied in user interface
frameworks.
And we've been talking about this quite a
bit.
So, what I'm doing now is I'm providing
you a more fundamental
grounding in the key roles or
relationships of the structure of these
solutions.
But you've already seen a lot of how this
stuff applies.
So let's talk a bit about how you design
things according
to this pattern, there's three layers as
you can see here.
There's the Async Service Layer, where
you're going
to do things that don't run for very long.
So short running operations would
typically run
in the Async Services Layer, and here
you're maybe going to, you know, get some
data, do a little processing on it.
And then when you're done with that
processing,
which is kind of what the user interface
thread does,
then you go ahead and you, you offer it,
you put it into some kind of queue.
And 99 times out of 100, or probably
99.999% of the
times out of 100, that queue is a so
called Synchronized queue.
So all of the stuff we've been talking
about
with regard to monitor objects, and
bounded buffers, and buffer
queues and blocking queues, and all that
kind of stuff,
that's the kind of queue that we're
talking about here.
So the queue here would be something like
the Android message
queue, or the blocking queue, or other
kinds of queues like that.
And then there'll be some number of
threads
that wait in a pool, in so-called a hungry
puppy fashion, because they're all waiting
to receive work
requests from the the Async part of the
world.
And they pull the requests out, and then
they go ahead and process
those requests, and because there are
separate
threads, they can afford to block
independently.
And if one of them blocks, not a
problem, somebody else can continue to
make progress.
Okay, so that's essentially the structure
of the solution.
And hopefully you can kind of see how this
maps onto the parts of Android.
And we'll come back later when we get a
little further along
in the discussion here, and we'll show you
how it works in Android.
Alright here's sort of a dynamic view of
what's happening here,
is to give you another flavor of what is
happening, so we
get the structural part that illustrates
the key three layers, and now
we're going to talk about the dynamics,
how they interact with each other.
So, we start out with data coming in from
somewhere in the case of
say an operating system kernel that
somewhere's
typically a device interrupt from a
hardware device.
In the case of something like Android,
that, that
input is coming in from some device
hardware, but
it's been abstracted by a bit, and it's
coming
into your application process, probably
through the event loop.
And the event queue that's managed by the
looper, we'll
look at that when we get to the
implementation portion.
However it gets in, you finally get the
data,
and you do a little bit of work on it.
In the case, for example, in your
programming
assignment, you might of done some URL
validation.
Might of said, is this URL valid or not?
Small amount of work.
And then you're going to go ahead at least
in the case of the Async task, and you're
going to say something like execute, or
you're going
to pass it, you're going to stick it
someplace.
And that will end up in queuing the work,
on
to a queue without blocking the caller,
and that's really important.
You have to make a decision about whether
you block the caller or not.
If the queue is full what do you do?
Do you fail?
Do you block?
Do you wait?
Do you wait for a period of time?
Those are all part of the implementation
decisions
you would make, if you were implementing
this pattern.
And we'll talk more about that.
And then somehow one of the other threads
that's running in the
background is going to learn about the
existence of the work in the queue.
And that's probably because whenever that
thread isn't doing anything, it's going to
go back and wait for work to show up in
the blocking queue.
And when work shows up, it'll pull it out
of the queue, and it'll go ahead and
process it.
And that request since it is running in
it's own thread of control, can afford to
run and block because they're other
threads in
the pool that are also able to do work.
Now this begs a whole bunch of interesting
questions, and when we
talk more about the implementation, you'll
see that in Java, they do
some really, really cool things under the
hood, as part of the
executor framework and the thread pull
executor framework to handle all this
stuff.
But in general, you've got a bunch of
different degrees of
freedom to play with here and I'll talk
about them later.
But real quickly, you have to figure out
how many threads you want
to allocate to be part of this pool, and
are they bounded or unbounded?
Can you keep spawning threads galore?
The more threads you spawn, the less it's
a pool, and more it's just thread for
request.
Then you also have the concept of the
queue.
How big is the queue?
Is the queue a fixed size, is it unbounded
size?
And, and obviously there's, there's a
trade off here.
Because if you're not careful you could
end up allocating way, way, way too much
resources, too many resources, and your
other
things will start to suffer as a result.
Okay, so keep in mind here that the
Synchronous services run concurrently,
both with respect to each other, and also
to the Asynchronous part.
So what that suggests is that the parts in
the Asynchronous portion, and the parts
in the Synchronous portion, should be
very,
very careful how they interact with each
other.
For example, they, they probably should be
extremely
careful not to try to access shared state
directly.
Because, if they do that, they either need
to lock it, which
could then run into problems, or they'll
end up with race conditions.
So, it's, it's often the case that things
in the Async layer, and
things at the Sync layer communicate
purely by passing messages back and forth.
And you'll get a bit more of a flavor of
that
when we take a look at how the Async task
framework
behaves, because that's kind of how it
works, it's hidden from
you by and large, but that's what it's
doing under the hood.
Okay, so, what I've been doing in the past
at
this point, is I've been showing the
implementation and applicability.
I'm going to defer that discussion, and
we're going to cover that next.
What I want to do now is sort
of talk about the consequences of applying
this pattern.
So here's a couple things to think about.
We, we've talked about a number of
patterns so
far, and this is actually a great quiz
question.
So, we've talked about thread specific
storage.
We've talked about monitor object, we've
talked about active
object, and now we`re introducing yet
another Concurrency pattern.
So these are a bunch of different
patterns.
You can argue that thread specific storage
is really
more of a Synchronization pattern than a
Concurrency pattern.
That's fine.
But we've got a bunch of different
ways of accessing information in
multithreaded programs.
And so, its important to understand the
pros and cons of each one.
Why would you choose to use one versus
another.
And this shows up in all kinds of
different
ways when you start designing your android
code, for example.
Because when you start designing your
android code, you have to make a choice.
Do I use the handlers and messages idiom,
which you did.
Do I use the handlers and runnerables
idiom, do I use
the async task idiom, which is the right
one to use?
And of course there's no one right answer,
it
all depends largely on what you're trying
to do.
So we'll talk more about tradeoffs between
the different approaches here in a second.
But first let's talk more about the
consequences of this.
So the basic idea is to simplify
things without throwing performance out
the window.
And what I mean by that is we, we don't
want to let the threads grow in an
unbounded way.
We don't want to make the whole program
threaded.
We don't want to have to make the GUI
thread for example.
The UI thread have to acquire lots to
do things that manipulate widgets of
various kinds.
We want to keep that real simple.
And, and efficient.
So, what we're doing there is we're
keeping the sync layer separate
from the async layer so that they can be
programmed in different ways.
Each for their own respective idiom.
Anybody here is a Monty Python fan,
there's
a bit on Monty Python about someone's
particular idiom.
I will look at this diagram a little bit
later.
This is kind of showing how the async
task framework behaves [SOUND] to these
different capabilities.
Another key issue here is separation
concerns, so
the synchronization policies in each layer
decouple from
each other in the, in the layer that's the
async layer, there is really no need for
synchronization as long as you're careful
not to
access any variables that are going to be
manipulated
by some other thread, so you, you just
take that problem out of the equation all
together.
In the sync layer, again, if you access
things you have to make sure you lock
them.
And it's possible to lock them because you
can block in that layer.
So there's different kinds of policies in
different layers.
And you don't have to have the same
behavior used in each place.
When we start taking a look at how
this pattern gets applied in more unusual
environments,
things that you are unlikely to ever run
across unless you become a systems
programmer somehow.
For operating systems, you'll see that
when people
program operating system kernels, there's
a very different
set of locking mechanisms that are used
inside
the kernel then there are in the user
space.
And that's because often in the Kernel
level,
you're dealing with things like hardware
interrupts, and
you have to be much more concerned about
interruptions and a-synchrony, and
signals, and so on.
Where as in the user level, it's
a simple little program, from an
application perspective.
Another thing you get, in this model, and
you see this
when you start playing around with the
android, it's very pronounced.
You can have this, sort of centralization
of communication between things.
You funnel, you often funnel stuff through
a particular
handle, or a particular handler with a
particular message queue.
For example, if you want to get work into
the
UI thread there's well other fine ways to
do that.
You do things like run on UI thread,
you, you pass things and that ends up
guaranteed
to come up through the main event pump
inside the UI thread to get the work done.
So there's very stylized ways, very
centralized ways
to talk back and forth between these
layers.
It's not a big mystery where to go to
communicate.
Although things are often somewhat
implicit which makes it confusing.
So those are the good things, there are
some downsides, much like with the,
the active object pattern implementation
that we talked about last time.
Whenever you start to communicate between
threads, there's going to be extra
overhead.
That you don't have if your within one
thread.
So for example, if you start trying to
pass messages between
threads, your going to run into issues of
synchronization, you're going to
run into issues of dynamic mem, memory
allocation, deallocation, you're going to
run into issues of context switching,
you're going to run into issues of
moving data between CPU caches, which is
more of a hardware level
thing or bus level thing, but it still is
a thing nonetheless,
and you know for people who really care
about that kind of
stuff that's crucially important to eking
out every last nanosecond of performance.
A lot of the application level stuff you
might do on Android probably doesn't make
that much difference but if you're not
careful
you could make software that runs really
slow.
So there is overhead here you just have to
be aware of it and you have
to think careful about what kind of
operation
you're going to want to run in this model.
Don't run long running operations in the
async part,
don't run short duration operations in the
sync part.
Its overcome.
Another issue that we have here is that
we're only using asynchronous
I/O for a portion of what we're doing, and
that's sort of
the, the lower layer part, so that the
things that are in
the sync layer might or might not be
actually benefiting from asynchrony.
And later when we come back and talk
in the next section about local
interprocess communication.
We start talking about the binder and the
AIDL and
all these higher level ways
of communicating between processes in
Android.
You'll see some other cool stuff we're
going to add
there to be able to do asynchronous
interactions between various parts.
And it's really cool, because now you can
make your entire program asynchronous.
And that's a whole different pattern
together.
That's more of the so-called proactive
pattern that we'll talk about.
And again, goes without saying, anytime
you start having
concurrent things happening, it's more
tricky to program and debug.
The good news is that if you follow
these very stylized frameworks, like the
async task framework.
Then you can put break points in certain
places.
You kind of know what's going to happen
when.
The framework has taken care of all the
synchronization.
For you under the hood, and so on and so
forth.
So it makes your life as a programmer much
easier, because you don't have to worry
about this stuff.
If you are writing this yourself, you have
to be more careful.
Next week at some point we'll probably
have a couple people that
did particularly interesting solutions to
the
latest programming assignment, present
their solutions.
And one of the things you'll see is, is
the amount of trouble they went through,
to make sure that the rules for their,
their concurrency framework, that they
developed are properly followed.
Checking to see the threads are running,
all the
user interface threads, if that's what
their supposed to do.
Checking to make sure that they're running
in the
background thread, if that's what their
supposed to do.
So, you'd like that not to have to be the
concern of the programmer.
The application programmer.
You want that to be concerning to the
infrastructure developer.
The person writing.
The async task framework for example, not
the person who's using it.
Okay, so let's talk about some of the
known uses.
So this pattern is actually something I
discovered, back in 1994-95 time frame
when
I was a professor at Washington University
and I was teaching an operating systems
course.
And we were talking about, how the opening
system Kernel worked.
And at the same time, I was, I was doing a
couple things at the same time.
I was teaching an opening system course, I
was developing
some software that had to run in an
ex-Windows environment.
Which had the same quirk that most user
interfaces do,
where the main thread of control had to be
single threaded.
The, the widget's access from the main
thread had to be single threaded.
But we had to be able to do long running
downloads of
images so we had to be able to do threads
as well.
So had that going on, I was doing some
consulting
work for some telecommunications
companies,
where they were building switches,
telecom switches, and I was also working
on an implementation
of,of KORBA, and playing around with
different implementations of KORBA.
So it was all these different things, and
as I
was looking at all the different stuff I
was doing.
I started to notice common themes, but the
place it
really showed up the most was in the
operating system.
Because if you read literature about
operating systems
from sort of the 80's and 90's, what
you found was that the operating system
kernel,
was developed quite differently from the
user level.
And if you take a look at this paper down
here you'll
get more than you ever wanted to know
about operating system kernels.
And what's really interesting about this
is that operating
system kernels are typically driven by
interrupts from hardware.
And so when networking IO shows up or when
keystrokes
arrive or when data's transferred between
different things, you know?
Reading or writing from a file system.
Or what not.
Those things turn into interrupts.
And, the way it's programmed,
historically,
this is changed a bit over time.
But it's still often the case inside the
operating system Kernel.
An awful lot of the process that takes
place there, is done by interrupts.
And if anybody's ever programmed
interrupt, different programming, say
in an imbedded system class, or in an
internship.
It is really, really nasty.
Because things sort of happen in somewhat
of random way.
You know, when the hardware, when the,
when the thing occurs, an interrupt
happens and you are not supposed to spend
very much time inside your
interrupt handler cause you can starve
out other things from getting, getting
responded
so that you would get that mas interrupts,
why you're in a interrupt handler.
And all the interrupts to be even more
important than
your interrupt then whatever you're doing,
get the chance to wrap.
So, typically, they program operating
systems kernels where there is sort of
only one thread and one stack and
everything is driven by interrupts.
Well if you think about it there's not a
heck of a lot you can do in that context.
So people invented various hierarchical
interrupt schemes.
And the long and the short of it is that
kernels are
driven by interrupts and it's very very
complicated to program software like that.
That's okay though because there's only
a handful of people doing kernel
programming.
And what they do is as soon as they
finally
get a unit of work that's completely
finished like they
assemble different pieces of buffers that
come in from a
network client and they put them into one
bigger reassembled buffer.
They then take that work and they stick it
into a queueing layer.
And in the operating system context things
for
UNIX kind of context that's often called a
socket layer.
So a socket layer is basically a queuing
layer
that's used to queue up the data that has
come
in from hardware devices driven by
interrupts in the kernel
to be reassembled, to be stuck under this
queue layer.
Now hence from that point onwards, life is
happy.
Because what happens is application level
developers run processes and
then they have multiple threads, and they
can afford to block.
And they can do all kinds of other
interesting things in those processes.
In user space, and they pull the work out
of
the, the socket queues, and then they do
their thing.
And when they're all done they go ahead
and put it
back in the queue and it gets sent out via
interrupts.
So the point there is that the low
level parts are interrupt driven, that's
the async part.
And the higher level parts are optionally
synchronous, because
you can afford to block, because you have
a
process or a thread abstraction or both at
your
discretion to keep track of all the
details for you.
So that was pretty cool, and looking at
the way that those things work,
we realize people broke the system up into
these different parts for a reason.
To keep the applications shielded from the
complexities of asynchrony, but to be able
to keep the Kernel programmers able to
make their software as efficient as
possible.
Because it doesn't really, do you much
good to have lots and lots and
lots of threads running around on the
Kernel because those make things really
slow.
And so that's one example.
Great example if you ever end up looking
inside things like BSD Unix which is
all open source or Linux, you'll, you'll
get a lot out of understanding that
pattern.
There's also patterns that show up a lot
in middle wear, things like
Korba where they do much the same thing,
you have some kind of
layer at the bottom that waits on a lot of
different sources of
input to get data from sockets, that's the
async part or the reactive part.
And then those things give the data off
into various queues.
Either one queue or multiple queues.
And then there are threads running in
those
queues to do the processing, that's
another example.
And then we have the Android Async Task
framework.
And we'll take a look in, in more detail
in
a second [NOISE] excuse me at the Async
Task framework.
And you'll see how and why that gets used
and
what that does to, to be a win in this
context.
Okay, so those are a bunch of different
known uses of the pattern.
This is one of my favorite patterns from
the POSA2 book because it's so powerful,
and you see it show up in the most unusual
places, as we're about to see.
Alright.
So to summarize, the half-sync, half-async
works to simplify your solutions, by
breaking
it up into three layers which makes things
easier to debug, evolve, understand.
We don't force people to asynchronous
stuff, where synchronous stuff makes
sense.
We don't force people to do
synchronous stuff, where asynchronous
stuff makes sense.
Everything is done where it belongs.
And the queuing layer makes it possible to
avoid directly accessing
state, instead you can pass it back and
forth in a queue.
Another cool thing, by the way, that comes
from
having a, a queue is you can re-prioritize
the work.
So the order in which things are processed
is not the same
order in which they have to have been
received in the first place.
That's not unlike the, the active object
pattern.
In fact, one not uncommon way of doing
this stuff is actually to put the
active object pattern on top, connected
with another pattern called a reactor.
We'll probably talk about reactors later
when we talk about
some of the lower level parts of, of Java
IO.
Alright.
So that's the end of the overview of the
pattern part.
With just enough discussion of Android to
connect it back to the class.
But keep in mind that this pattern really
is not at all beholden to Android.
We're just using it as an illustration.
What I'd like to do now in the rest of the
talk is show you how this actually gets
implemented in Android.
And so we're going to understand how to
implement the
pattern in general using Android as
examples of how it's implemented.
And then we're also going to look and see
how it, you can apply this pattern in
Android.
And the context for this whole discussion
is
going to be the AsyncTask framework so you
also as
a side effect, get to learn a little bit
more about how Async Task works under the
hood.
Which implements this pattern in a very
cool and sophisticated way.
It's not for the faint of heart.
There's a lot of moving parts inside Async
Task, but I'll try
to break it down for you so you can make
sense of it.
Okay, so the first thing you do.
If you want to implement this pattern you
got to figure out what your layers are.
You've got to figure out what the, the
async layer is, you gotta figure out
what the sync layer is, you have to
figure how you're going to communicate
between them.
So we're first going to start out by
looking at the, the async layer.
So that's the part that's going to be the
part where you're doing sort of short
duration things.
In the context of our examples that would
be the stuff that gets called back by
the Android activity framework when, or
the activity
widget framework, when you click on a
button.
So you get the, the view, the on-click
event
called back that you designated in your
manifest file.
And you get back the event that occurred,
and that's sort of the, the async part.
And for our particular example here, we're
going to look at
it as though someone were going to use the
async task framework.
So what they would typically do is they
would bundle up
whatever they got in, like a URL or
something like that.
And then you'd go head and pass that in to
the, the async task framework by calling
its execute method.
And you all remember execute is this, this
template
method that does a bunch of things for it.
So if you take a look at execute, here is,
here is execute from the source code.
we, we go and look on this in a more
detail in a second.
But, basically what execute does, is it.
Turns around and calls execute on
executor.
And it passes in, something called the
DefaultExecutor.
And we'll look at that in a second, too.
By default, it does things in a sort of a
single threaded manner.
But, it's easy very, very easy to do
multiple thread stuff.
And then execute an executor does the
following.
So, it turns around and it first does a
bunch of stuff and it goes onPreExecute.
So keep in mind, we are in the user
interface thread of control at this point.
We call, or it calls the, the execute,
executor method calls onPreExecute.
So, that's where that pre-execute hook
gets called back.
And then it takes the parameter that were
passed
in here, which are whatever you called
execute with.
And it sticks them into a data structure
and then it says exec,
which is this executor, execute, and then
it passes in something called a future.
And the futures going to be used, so that
the, the
guy who ends up running this thing in the
background
later can communicate back to the user
interface thread to
do things like give progress updates and
other kinds of stuff.
Okay, so that's, that's kind of the first
thing, and we'll
take a look a the source code here in a
second.
The next thing you want to be able to do
is you want to
be able to figure out what stuff is
going to run for long time.
So in the context of our particular
example,
that's going to be the, the downloading of
the file.
And the way that that happens of course in
the AsyncTask framework.
If you poke around here for a while.
When the constructor of AsyncTask is first
called
it creates something that's called a
worker, an
mWorker of type WorkerRunnable, and this
is basically
a future, it's a, it's, it's a callable.
It's a, it's a runable and a callable.
Is it kind of combines a bunch of things
together.
And its got this hook method on it called
call.
And this method is going to be called,
when
you're in the thread of control of the
background thread.
And as you can see what it's going to do.
This, this thing gets called in the
background thread.
And it's going to go ahead and call
doInBackground with the parameters that
you passed it.
So that's going to go ahead and run in the
background.
When that thing is done, it's going to
return the result.
And that result's going to get posted back
to the user interface thread.
And we're going to, we're going to look at
how all that stuff works in a second.
It's really cool.
Okay.
And then the last thing we need, is we
need some
way to be able to interact between the
Async part which
is kind of that front end part that does
the execute and
execute on executor part on behalf of the
UIThread activity logic.
And then get the data over to the
background thread and run it in the
doInBackground method.
So, how are we going to do that?
Well, the way we do that as indicated by
the
pattern as, as foretold by the pattern
like a soothsayer.
We're going to do that by having some kind
of BlockingQueue.
And as you can see here, what do you know?
It's called BlockingQueue.
So, if you take a look inside of the
ThreadPoolExecutor, which we'll
look at in a second, you'll see that the
ThreadPoolExecutor has a BlockingQueue.
And as long as you give something here
that's
a subclass of BlockingQueue, then it will
block properly.
And the right things will happen.
So, that's how we queue things up.
Okay.
So let's now go take a look and see how
all this stuff works.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So here's the AsyncTask file.
Lemme, lemme see if I can make it a little
bit
smaller without completely, making it so
small you can't see it anymore.
[NOISE].
All right, hopefully you can sort of see
that.
So one of the nice things about, about all
the Android code is it's all Javadoc.
So, everything you see online is actually
enclosed included in comments in the class
itself.
So, we can kind of skip that to adhere at
all the things.
So here you can see that we have
AsyncTask.
AsyncTask is an abstract class which means
you are
obligated to subclass it and fill in some
methods.
The methods are obviously ones like
onPreExecute, onPostExecute, and so on.
And then it has, it's generic class, so
you have to pass in some parameters.
You have to pass in the parameters that
get passed to execute,
which would be things like you know,
passing in a string or URL.
The progress variable, which is used to
call back when
you do the on, onProgressUpdate stuff or
the progress update method.
And then the result, which is what gets
returned from doing back call.
So, take a look here, you can see we've
got
a couple of things that are used to have
default size.
The, the thread pool, by default, the
thread pool will be 5.
You'll have five things running in the
thread pool.
The maximum size is going to be a 128.
They just decided, no more threads than
that.
It's probably not a bad idea.
There's this thing called a ThreadFactory
which can be used to
make threads and keep track of how many
threads we have.
There's this thing that's called the, the
BlockingQueue, as you can see the
BlockingQueue here is a
LinkedBlockingQueue, so its
our queue made out of linked list.
And I'm assuming that 10 here, probably
means the number of elements
that can be in the queue before the queue
is considered full.
We'll see how that figures in a, in a
little bit later,.
Now here's something interesting.
This is sort of the workhorse behind the
scenes that's doing the heavy lifting for
AsyncTask.
The workhorse for AsyncTask is some
kind of executor.
And we'll say that there's, there's two of
them that are typically there.
You are free to define your own executor.
If you don't like the two that come out of
the box, you can make your own.
But the two that come out of the box are
ThreadPoolExecutor and
SerialExecutor, which are actually related
to each other in an interesting way.
So ThreadPoolExecutor, when you call that
you give it
the, the default number of threads, the
maximum number
of threads you want, and some other things
like
the, the worker queue, the blocking queue,
and so on.
And that's going to create an object and
that's
going to spawn a bunch of threads in the
background.
And we'll see later how that, how that all
works.
But then we are also going to make this
thing called a
SerialExecutive, which is a new
SERIAL_EXECUTOR
which we can see down here.
There's, an InternalHandler that we use to
synchronize
communication back to the main thread, the
UIThread.
That, that, that's of course is done in
the UIThread, so that it's owned by the
UIThread.
We make the DefaultExecutor be the
SERIAL_EXECUTOR.
And then here is the SerialExecutor.
So, by default, an AsyncTask is a
SerialExecutor.
And when its execute method gets called,
that
turns around and calls this executive
method here.
And it's going to end up passing in a
runnable.
And you can see what we do here, is we go
ahead and we queue this runnable into
the thing called task, we have a, a queue
of tasks which is a, a deck of runnables.
And we stick this thing in here.
And, we put a runnable in this queue, and
then if there's nothing that's
currently active, which there won't be
when
we're first setting here, we call
scheduleNext.
And scheduleNext goes ahead and takes this
thing off
the queue, and then it executes it in the
THREAD_POOL_EXECUTOR.
But it's only letting one thing at a time,
be executed in the THREAD_POOL_EXECUTOR.
And when that guy is done, then, you know,
what will happen is, when the
run method is finished this guy will come
back and then schedule the next thing.
So we're basically building a linked list
of requests
and then they're being executed one at a
time.
So they're actually not running in
parallel.
Just one of them is running at a time.
That's what the SerialExecutor does.
The THREAD_POOL_EXECUTOR when you do it
with
the multi-threaded version is even more,
more cool.
We'll see that in a second.
All right.
So lets take a look at a few more things.
You can see you can set the executor to
something besides the, the default.
Here's the constructor.
When you, when you make an AsyncTask, when
you say, you know, AsyncTask A equal new
AsyncTask.
Here's what happens.
It goes ahead and it creates this thing
called a WorkerRunable.
Which is going to end up being stuck.
As we'll see in a second onto a queue that
gets passed to
a thread in the thread pool that the
executor's running in a background thread.
And, when it's called back, what this guy
does is it goes ahead
and runs the doInBackground method of this
task in the other thread of control.
And then we go ahead make this thing
called a
FutureTask, and you can see the FutureTask
actually holds the worker.
So the worker is the guy who's going to do
the work in the other thread.
The FutureTask then gets created, and this
FutureTask when this guy
is done, what he's going to do, is he's
going to end up getting
the result and posting the result back to
the main thread of
control, so that the onPostExecute method
gets called in the right context.
So keep in mind what these things are
what's
confusing about this if you're not really
a Java expert
is for making objects that have methods
that don't get
run until they get called back at the
right time.
So, this guy over here for example, his
call
method's going to be called back in the
background thread.
And when this done method gets called back
he's also going to
get call the background thread and he's
going to post the result.
So it ends up going back where it needs to
go.
Okay.
So there's a bunch of other little helper
methods.
Here's an interesting one.
This is an idiom you see a lot in Android,
by the way.
So a postResult let's see where this gets
called.
So take a look at postResult.
[NOISE].
So here's an example postResult.
When we ran the background, when we ran
doInBackground in the background thread.
When we were finished running in the
background thread it returned
a result, which was the, like the bit map
or whatever.
And it's going to post that result.
So we go here, postResult takes the result
and it goes ahead and then it says.
Hey, handler, that's owned by the main
thread of control, by the UIThread.
It says, make me a message please.
And it's going to be the
MESSAGE_POST_RESULT message.
And I want you to associate with this the
result that we just computed in the
background thread.
And then it's going to go ahead and it's
going to take that message, remember this
message comes out of the handler for the
main thread of control, the UIThread.
And then it's going to say message, send
yourself to this target.
So what it'll do is under the hood it'll
take the result that
was just computed, running in the
background, and it will stick it on
the message queue for the UIThread, and
the UIThread will then come along
and read that thing out of there and then
crack this request open.
And then do a callback which will then go
ahead and then display it in the right
place.
So if you take a look down here, here's
doInBackground you can
see that that's a, doInBackground is an
abstract method which means you have
to subclass it onPreExecute and
onPostExecute
are just virtual methods that are
not abstract so they, you can ignore them
and they will still work.
Here's onProgressUpdate, here's
onCancelled and so on and so forth.
Let's see.
Trying to think if there's anything else
interesting.
I should show you here.
Here's the execute method, we saw that
actually says execute on executive.
Here's execute on executor this guy goes
ahead and
does the onPreExecute, because it's in the
main thread control.
And then it goes ahead and executes the
future, and it passes it to the
background.
We'll look at that in a second and see how
all that works.
Lets see.
Oh, here you go.
PublishedProgress.
when you call publishProgress that's,
that's how
you, you publish data from the background
thread to show up if I had called to
onProgressUpdate in the foreground thread.
You can see what it does, is it goes ahead
and it gets a message from the handler
that's running, owned by the main threader
control, and
it says I'm going to pass the
MESSAGE_POST_PROGRESS message, please.
And then you can see it just goes ahead
and sends that to target.
So, it sends it right over there.
Notice it doesn't even cache the message
anywhere, it just chains it together.
It says sHandler, a ping message, send to
target.
It's almost like a list, it's kind of
chaining all the stuff together.
Here's the, the finish method, you can see
what finish does.
When finish is called it takes the result
and it calls onPostExecute.
So that's obviously how we're going to get
the result that
was computed in the background to run in
the UIThread.
Here's the InternalHandler, this is the
guy
that actually does the stuff in the
background.
And you could see that he defines a class,
and this is
another common thing that I, a lot of
people didn't properly handle the
memory leak issues, where you have to make
sure you have specific classes
not anonymous classes to deal with memory
issues that, that's a common problem.
Read that link that I sent in your,
in my chemistry solution for more
information like that.
So, whatever anybody sends these messages
from
the background thread to post the
progress, to
post the result that's the ends up coming
through here in the main thread of
control.
And what it does if it's is the
MESSAGE_POST_RESULT
it says go ahead and finish with the
result data.
If it's MESSAGE_POST_PROGRESS it says call
the onPostUpdate where the result data.
So those, those things are how we get
data from the background thread to the
foreground
thread to be called back appropriately on
the
appropriate hook method that, that's done
on the AsyncTask.
And then this WorkableRunnable class is a
callable that adds a bit of data.
Okay, so that's, that's kind of how
asynctask works.
Now the other thing I want to show you
here
real quick, is it's also quite
interesting, is the ThreadPoolExecutor.
And this is the guy that does all the
work.
So the AsyncTask is really just there, in
order to
be able to fill the framework obligations
of getting, doing
background work, running, running in one
thread, and on pre,
onPreExecute, onPostExecute,
onProgressUpdate; getting those
running in the other thread.
And then being able to pass futures and
work worker
objects back and forth between the threads
using the message mechanisms.
And a half sync, async pattern.
So that's what that things doing.
The guy that actually does the heavy
lifting to
run the stuff in the background is the
ThreadPoolExecutor.
And if you read this thing you'll realize
that they really thought this through very
very thoroughly.
My friend in colleague for gosh, almost 30
years, Doug Lee.
great, fantastic computer programmer,
researcher, academic.
He's the author of this stuff and it's
very, very sophisticated.
Basically, it's got a lots and lots of
different tweaks little,
little knobs you can turn to do all kinds
of different things.
Theres, he's the author.
And so you can, you can either have a
fixed number of threads or a fixed number
of messages.
Or unbounded number [LAUGH], an unbounded
number
of threads, an unbounded number of
messages.
You can, you can play with all these
different parameters, there's
a couple of different options they give
you, to start with.
A lot of this stuff is, is just low level
things.
Here's the blocking queue we were talking
about before, that's the thing that
does the synchronization, not unlike the
active object pattern that we talked
about.
We have some locks in here.
We have a hash set of worker threads in a
pool, so
we can look them up by their, their ID to
find them quickly.
What I really want to show you here was
the main
method, which is the guy that, that does
the work.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
There we go.
So here's, here's execute.
You call execute, you give it something
that's ultimately a runnable.
[COUGH] And, what this thing comes in and
it says.
It says, is the number of threads in our
pool, that's, that are
currently running, is that less than the,
the size we are allowed to have?
And if the answer is yes, it will try to
add a
new worker thread and then give the work
to that worker thread.
So that's one way it does stuff.
If there's already enough threads that are
running, it then says.
Can I go ahead and add this particular
command into the queue of commands?
Yes or no?
And if the answer is yes, then we are
fine.
If the answer is no because the queue is
full,
then in that particular case we may reject
the thing.
And then it tries to do some other stuff.
If you do the documentation you'll see how
the different.
Logic it tries to do to figure out what,
what's going to work.
For our particular case here we have, you
know,
five threads and I think ten items in the
queue.
And so as long as we don't exceed those
limits it's going to pre spawn
those five threads and as work comes in
it'll stick it onto the queue by offer.
And then if we take a look up here there's
a.
I think it's called take, yeah so.
There's a method called get task, and get
task is going to be called by
the background thread in order to get the
next chunk of work to do.
And it does a whole bunch of different
stuff to check it's state and context.
And then finally, it goes ahead and it
tries to get.
The next item out of the queue, using
timeouts or not.
Unless it's got that thing, it's got the
runnable that it wants to execute.
So if you take a look at the task, so you
can see the run worker thread.
Run worker thread is the actual method
that gets run in a thread and it
blocks waiting for there to be work to do,
it gets the next task to run.
It calls them the four execute hooks.
And then it goes ahead and says task run.
And in our particular case, when you call
task run,
that ends up calling the call method on
this callable thing.
And as you can see here, when the worker
thread running in
the pool by the thread pool executor runs,
it's going to go ahead and.
Call rar, which is going to call call, and
call is going to be, related, to this
callback.
And that's going to end up calling do in
background from
a thread in the thread pool to do it's
work.
And when it's done its going to post it's
result back to the main thread.
So, [COUGH] it's almost like watching a
game of pong or a game of tennis.
Things are going back and forth, and back
and forth through these cues.
But the key point is under the hood, it's
all working as a result of the half-async
of the async pattern, where the main
thread is
sending data to the worker threads through
a queue.
The worker threads are pulling data stuff
out of
the queue, doing the callbacks that do
during background.
And when they are done, then their
invoking methods that return the results
back to the queue that's owned by the main
thread of the control.
And so that's basically how things are
interacting.
All right, so that doesn't obviously cover
every last
thing there is to know about Async task
and
thread pool executor but it at least gives
you
a feeling for how it works under the hood.
So if we were to implement this in the
context of our example, we would have a.
A class might download async task, how
like you guys load, we extend async task,
we fill on string, integer and bitmap, and
then we define a do in background method.
And that's the guy who's going to download
the
thing in the background thread, so he can
block.
We're going to implement the async side of
things so of course.
Those are going to be the call backs that
we do to invoke things
in the first place like execute, as well
as stuff like on, pre-execute.
Which is going to go ahead and display our
dialog and on post-execute,
which is going to go ahead and do the
operation and dismiss the dialog.
So those are examples of the asynch parts.
They, they run very quickly, they don't
block.
So we want those running in the main
thread.
We want the other stuff running in the
other thread.
And the Async task framework make sure
that all things happen in the right place.
And then we have the queueing layer which
is
what we just looked at a minute ago where.
You're going to have this work queue and
the work
queue is going to be used to offer and
take the message,
the messages which are actually runnables,
which are actually futures
which can get called back to do various
things as callbacks.
So it's, it's lots of patterns all glommed
together.
This particular set of code has very high
pattern density, so
in addition to the half sync, half async
pattern which is
kind of structuring the overall
interactions, we've also got, you know,
futures running around here a, you know,
other things that you've seen.
Factories and so on, and that should be no
surprise.
Doug Lee has been doing patterns for
decades.
And actually wrote the Forward to our
POSA2 book.
So he's very familiar with these patterns.
All right, next thing I'm going to is just
give you another view of all this stuff.
So I jus, I showed you how to implement
things.
But as you undoubtedly discover just
looking at source code is
often not sufficient to make sense out of
what the software does.
And that's because when you look at source
code.
You've got to build a mental model in your
head of who's calling what and when.
And unless you're extremely fluent with
these patterns, it's
easy to start losing track of what's going
on.
So how do we deal with this?
Well there's a variety of different means.
What I'm going to show you here, is a way
of using UML notation.
In particular, some concurrency notation
and some notation relating to interaction
diagrams to illustrate, illustrate the
sequence of flow of control here.
[COUGH] And, probably for the actual mook
I will animate all this stuff.
I didn't have a chance to do that yet but,
here's here's basically what happens.
So [COUGH] the, The UI thread gets a user
request, right?
How does that happen?
Somebody clicks a button, and you fill in
a text view.
And you, or, and edit text.
You, you click a button.
That shows up by some kind of click
handler, right?
That you wrote.
And you get that, you validate it, and
then you call execute.
And you give the URL that was part of the,
the data that was entered by the user.
So, [COUGH] let's say but for sake of
argument, we
set the ex, executor to be the thread pull
executor.
So, execute is called, execute as we just
saw turns around and calls on pre-execute.
That's the first thing it does.
So there's a hook method that gets called
back to your code
to do anything that's needed to run in the
main sort of control.
It then turns around and now keep in mind
this is all in the
UI thread like here, all the stuff inside
this dashed line is UI thread.
It then calls the execute method on the
executor and what
that guy does is he sticks this thing into
the blocking queue.
And I guess really strictly speaking I
should fix this because it's a little
confusing.
Somewhat strictly speaking, you know, the
worker threads are really
the guys who are running the separate
thread of control.
I will probably put this in a various
places.
[COUGH] Some sense it probably looks more
like that the boundary.
So when you call and execute, you call and
execute that's an object sort of half in,
half out,.
It's.
It's got a public facade for interacting
with it, that's called by a thread.
And that thing turns around, and sticks
the request into the blocking queue.
And then, one of the threads in the
background is going to
end up calling take, to take it out of the
queue.
And once it takes it out of the queue, it
then does this call.
Callback method in the background thread.
That will then call doInBackground, that
goes and runs over here, and, I'm sorry,
runs, and when it's when it's all done, it
will
go ahead and post the result, that ends up
coming back over
here, and this guy gets to run in the
other thread of control.
So the executor threads in the, in the
thread pool do all that work in the
background.
And under the hood the blocking queue is
what's really doing the, the
synchronization of interactions between
the half-sync and the half-async layer.
If there's flow control that occurs at all
here.
If, if you would happen to block in the
one sort of
control in, in a background thread that,
that's doing a download.
Not a problem.
Nobody else is affected.
Everything works just fine.
Okay.
So to kind of wrap things up, from
an android centric perspective, of this
pattern.
You kind of see here, this is, this is the
pattern, but now
we've replaced the generic parts with
specific things from the android toolkit.
So, we've got our external event source,
is
really coming at us, from the UI thread
looper.
That we looked at before.
Our activity is kind of the part that's
the Async part
is not blocking in there for any length of
time.
This will get the A and R exception.
And then we're offering stuff into the
blocking
queue which is part of the Async task
framework.
And then these background threads, they
are pulling stuff of the queue.
Processing it and then they're.
Eventually passing data back to the UI
thread through the, through the internal
handler
mechanism that's used to synchronize
messages between
the background threads and the foreground
threads.
So, this is actually, as, as I said, well
I'll get to that in a second.
So.
This encapsulates background thread
processing, it
decouples it from the UI thread.
You can also report progress.
The half-sync, the async task framework is
a very sophisticated implementation of
half-sync, half-async pattern.
And it's sophisticated because unlike many
instances of this pattern,
where data just flows from the bottom to
the top.
We have data flowing from the bottom to
the top, or from one side to the other.
It that's how you look at it.
And then there's also stuff that's coming
back the other way.
So we're not just having one-way
communication.
We, we're talking from the activity, to
the background thread.
And then from the background thread to the
foreground thread.
And, and sometimes, as is the case with
the post-progress stuff.
That happens multiple times.
You, you keep calling back and forth, back
and forth for the duration of the call.
So there's, there's multiple points of
interaction be, between background and
foreground threads.
Or UI threads.
Okay, [COUGH] any, any questions about
that particular.
Pattern or that framework.
So now hopefully you have a much better
understanding of a couple things.
You hopefully know a bit more about basic
task framework and how it works under the
hood,
you might see how it's implemented as a
pattern, which helps it easier to
understand the implementation.
And probably the most important thing you
learn is nobody
in their right mind would want to
implement Async task.
If they could use it from what's already
in Android.
So it's a great story about how patterns
and frameworks collaborate
to make your life easier if you're needs
match what it does.
[MUSIC].