[MUSIC]
So let’s talk now about, how you
would actually implement the
publisher-subscriber in Android.
And there’s a, a bunch of different ways
to do it.
So, we’re just going to focus on one part.
So first, let's talk about what it means
to implement the pattern in the first
place.
So, there's a bunch of steps that you need
to do.
One of which is you have to, input,
define or determine what the
publisher-subscriber mapping is.
How do, how do publishers and subscribers,
you know,
interact, what's the, what's the means by
which they communicate.
And, and of course in the context of
Android, this is done via an intent.
And as you all know at this point.
And keeps track of various things.
Optionally it keeps track of the name of
something, more likely in
the case of pub-sub like models, it keeps
track of the data.
It keeps track of the action.
It keeps track of the extras, the
category, et cetera.
Those are things you can, put into a, an
Intent data structure.
And then that information will get
distributed, by
some, magic cloud like thing, to the
various receivers.
If, you want to avoid this overhead, of
giving
everybody everything all the time, then
you need to come
up with some kind of filtering mechanism
to narrow, people's
interests in certain topics, or certain
parts of certain topics.
So in Android, this is done by, the
concept
of intent filters, and there's different
ways to define or.
Program implement intent filters, you can
do them dynamically by creating
an intent filter and then registering it,
when you call register receiver.
You can also use the manifest file like we
showed here,
to specify different things, different
actions, different data, and so on.
And then, you will only receive that stuff
that matches your filters.
So, it's kind of like a sieve and only
things
that pass through the filter or pass
through the sieve.
Are actually delivered to the end, end
result to the broadcast receivers.
Another thing you need to do, is figure
out how you're going to go ahead
and define and implement the subscriber
registration API
and there's a couple of pieces to this.
First, you're going to have to figure out,
how you're going to
let applications, which in this case could
be activities or services.
Go ahead and register broadcast receivers,
to get
called back and there's a couple different
variants here.
You can, you can have a register receiver
model where you pass in
the receiver you want called back and
optionally the intent filter, or not.
And then you can also give permissions and
you can actually
even in the second case, you can actually
give a handler.
Where you want the, call to take place if
you don't want it to
take place, on the thread of control
where the, broadcast receiver was
originally created.
So, you have a lot of flexibility in
Android
about, how you control where things are
going to run.
These subscriptions that you make, the
registrations you make at the
receivers are typically stored, in some
kind of internal data structure somewhere.
In the case of Android, there's a
very complicated means for doing this
called the
Activity Manager Service, which I
encourage you to
take a look at sometime, it's, it's vast.
It's, like, 16,000 lines of code or, or
more.
There's a method called Register Receiver
in there that's, that's non-trivial.
There's even longer methods we'll look at
in a second.
And basically what they do, is they build
some kind of hash map called, M registered
receivers which is going to, keep track of
whose registered, for which different
kinds of things.
So, when you call registered receiver, it
goes ahead and check
to see if this particular receivers
already registered for this stuff.
And if so, it adds it to a link list of
things, that are going to be registered.
And then it goes ahead and sticks it into
this hash map.
So you can end up with, multiple receivers
registered
for the same intent, and that is what's
used
to support this group communication, this
[COUGH] one to
many communication, that's the hallmark of
the publisher-subscriber pattern.
You can have, many things be dispatched
just
as you can have one thing be dispatched.
Then you also have to figure out how to
define and implement the, notification
API, this is the thing that, that the
publisher uses, to notify the subscribers.
And once again, there's a couple different
variants.
We have a way of being able to say, from
our application
point of view, from a publisher point of
view, send out this intent.
To all the notify, all the
registered broadcast receivers, or all the
subscribers.
And Android has a couple of different
variants of this if you recall.
One, is called send broadcast.
And that sends it out to everybody.
Kind of in parallel.
And the other, is called send ordered
broadcast.
Which serializes the way, in which the
dispatching takes place.
And there's a whole pile of variants of
send ordered broadcasts that do various
kinds of things.
So, I recommend you take a look
at the documentation, for more details
about that.
Under the hood, in the activity manager
service,
there's a bunch of methods that handle
this.
There's a method called, broadcast intent,
which is kind of
the entry point into the activity manager
service, and it
very quickly grabs a lock and calls
broadcast intent locked,
and broadcast intent locked is like, 350
lines of code.
It's, it's very, very nasty, hard to
figure out code.
But what it basically does, is it goes
ahead
and it takes the, the intent that's being
broadcast,
and it looks up to see whether or not,
that intent has been registered for an
Android Manifest Files.
Those are the static receivers.
And or, registered via calls to Register
Receiver, which is a dynamic call.
And it builds up, a set of receivers that
are going to handle these requests.
And then it goes on and does a lot more
stuff which
I'm not going to talk about here in
detail, but, if you look
at the code, you'll see basically what it
tries to do, it
tries to send out the registered
receivers, in other words, the dynamic
ones.
If it, if you're not doing an ordered
broadcast it tries to send them all out
concurrently.
So they all get sent.
It just goes through a wild loop going
send, send, send, send, send.
And those things get sent to all the ones,
that are, that are dynamically registered.
And that's because, the assumption is,
that those processes,
those activities, those services, what
not, are up and running.
Or could be up and running quickly and so
they
will get delivered the messages very fast,
the intents very fast.
All the things that are, actually
registered statically by
manifest files, however, are delivered one
at a time.
because you have to start up the activity,
or the service.
[COUGH] You have to start up the process
and then deliver the thing, to the
broadcast receiver.
And so, they don't want to start up all
these processes unnecessarily.
They do them one at a time, because that
takes more effort to do that.
So, it's very, very complicated code.
I've, I've read a number of times for a
variety of reasons.
And it's really fascinating to figure out
how it all works.
Okay.
So, that's basically, an overview of how
you might implement the pattern.
Now, let's talk about how this pattern
gets applied in the Android.
And to do this, I decided to dive down
into the
implementation of this pattern, in the
context of the battery service.
And the phone app which exists in Android
4.0.
So, Android 4.0, is where I got the
example from here.
Oddly enough, Android 4.1 has changed this
example slightly, and so I couldn't show
you the 4.1 version, because I haven't
figured out all the pieces there yet.
I'm not sure whether they still do this
anymore
in Android 4.1, but they still have to
somehow.
Anyway, what happens here is, is the
follow, the following.
When the phone app starts up, in part
of its initialization, before the onCreate
method is called,.
It goes ahead and it creates, a
broadcast receiver called phone app
broadcast receiver.
So, it makes an instance of this thing.
And then, in it's onCreate method, it goes
ahead and creates a bunch of intent
filters.
One of which is for, action battery low,
which is an intent.
And then it goes ahead and it registers
that intent filter, along with the phone
app
broadcast receiver, it takes all those
things and
it registers those, with the activity
manager service.
So, that goes inside of the, register
receiver callback that we looked at
before,
and that stashes all that stuff inside
that hash map that we were looking at.
At some point down the road, dot, dot,
dot,
the battery service, which is a system
service is running.
And when the battery service starts up,
its constructor, actually does something
really interesting.
This is a, kind of, cool example of, of
patterns connected to patterns, right, a
compound pattern, example here.
So, what it basically does, is it creates
something that's
a called a U Event Observer, for user
event observer.
And it creates this thing called an
M-Power Supply Observer.
And it goes ahead and it registers this
observer, with some low level mechanism,
this is, this
is the battery monitoring hardware, or
device drive,
or something that's lurking inside, the
Android device framework.
[COUGH] And then it, it goes ahead and
just, you know, waits for something to
happen.
So, this is an example of using the
observer pattern, at the
low level to wait for a notification, that
battery that voltage is low.
When
when the low level, driver discovers that
battery is low.
It calls back on the on U event callback
method, using the observer pattern and
that thing turns
around and calls the update method, on the
battery
service and the update method calls the
process values method.
And the process values method creates an
intent, which
is the action battery low intent, and it
broadcasts
that, to anybody who happens to care about
this,
and there is various things that care
about this.
In this particular case for the Android
4.0, this ends up being, sent to
the activity manager service, the activity
manager
service says, aha, who cares about this?
Oh, I know who cares about this, the phone
app cares about this and
then some other stuff that he cares about,
but the phone app cares about this.
So it turns around and calls the method
internally called form
receive which is a whole pile of things
and eventually goes ahead
and dispatches the on receive hook method,
on the phone app and
then that goes ahead and does something
that informs the phone application.
That the battery is getting low.
And there's, it's a bunch of call backs,
and very convoluted and so on.
But that's basically the path, to the
portion
of the Android, that's handling that kind
of stuff.
Any questions about, about that?
So that's an example of, the illustration
of publisher-subscriber pattern, in the
context of Android.
And all low and behold, it also uses the
observer pattern, at a lower level.
In order to be able to, wait to be
notified, when the battery voltage low,
lowness is detected.
That notifies the battery services, the
battery service turns
around and does a broadcast, to send the
event out.
So, what we're using is patterns, kind of
combining them together,
chaining patterns together, in order to be
have this call
back driven asynchronous, anonymous,
decoupled in time and space way
of being able to inform, interested
parties that something has occurred.
And if there's nobody who cares, you know,
if you
just decided, I don't care if my battery
is running low.
Doesn't bother me.
I'll just, my phone will just shut itself
down automatically.
Then there don't need to be a subscriber
here.
It'll just evaporate into thin air, so,
then nothing will happen at all.
Okay, so, Android implements
publisher-subscriber via
Intents and the Intents framework and it
does this to give you this nice, late
binding, effect where you can.
Make changes after the system is running.
For example, what I just showed you here,
takes place after the system is launched.
So, we're not doing what I just described
to you there, we're not
doing this registration in the manifest
files, instead we're doing it in the app.
So, the phone app, the phone app starts
up, it goes ahead and
it creates an intent filter that says I
want to hear about the activity.
For the action battery I want to hear
about the, intent for the action battery
low.
It registers that dynamically.
The battery service doesn't know about the
phone app, it
doesn't know about the status service, it
doesn't know about anything.
It just knows when it learns the battery
is
low, it's going to tell anybody who cares,
something is happening.
So, it's very dynamic.
You can come along and make changes.
The intent data in this case, is, is sort
of a passive descriptor, it's a
data structure, that keeps track of what
has
changed and is being announced in the
system.
So, something's happened, battery's low,
we tell everybody about that.
That's one use of intents.
There are other uses of intents as well,
where you say,
I want you to start this activity, right,
so start service.
That's another example of using intent to,
start something to be run.
The broadcast example, is when something's
happened and you want to
inform or notify others, of the occurrence
of something else.
[COUGH] And you can, in Android, you
can basically pass these intent objects in
various
ways, using start broadcast and start, oh
sorry,
send broadcast, send ordered broadcast,
send sticky broadcast.
There's a bunch of different ways you can
do, to pass this information around.
Okay, any questions about the publisher
subscriber pattern?
Any questions about the
broker pattern?
Again, just to kind of underscore the
point [COUGH].
As you, take a look at this stuff under
the hood, you'll often find out
that, that many patterns are used
together,
in order to implement this kind of stuff.
So, for example, you'll find brokers used
in both
publisher-subscribers,and, and, brokers,
that's pretty common in both systems.
You can go across address bases.
In some systems, people, layer
publisher-subscriber, on top of
broker, that's, that's one law, that's the
way that Corba
did it, the nice part there is that you
get
reuse, the downside is you get extra
layers of overhead.
Other systems that implement
publisher-subscriber,
do so without making a broker,
they just have publisher-subscriber kind
of as the, the native mechanism.
And there's all kinds of ways, you
can then layer brokers on top of
publisher-subscribers.
So, you, you can basically, take these
patterns, and you can take
implementations of these patterns, and
re-arrange
them in all kinds of interesting ways.
In real life, these days, more and more
people
tend to move towards, some kind of
Publisher-Subscriber, like model.
Because, you can do an awful lot of things
with it.
But, you have to be careful that you don't
end up,
falling into the trap of consistency, at
the expense of clarity.
So, not everything in life requires or
benefits from a, an anonymous group
communication mechanism.
Although many things do.
So, here are some examples right.
So, [COUGH] imagine that you want to, tell
all of your
friends, you just got into, I don't know,
Stanford for grad school.
Right?
So, how would you tell them that?
You would go ahead and post it on your,
your
Facebook page or something like that or
you'd tweet it, right?
And that would be a good example of, of
mass broad
communication, publisher-subscriber, you
publish, lots
of people find out, that's great.
If you want to, I don't know, invite your
parents over
or invite yourself over to your parent's
for dinner this weekend.
Are you going to publish that on Facebook?
Probably not, right?
You're going to pick up the phone.
You're going to say, hey, I'm coming home
this weekend.
Can I, can I bring my laundry?
Or whatever else you want to do.
And so, that's a good example of a point
to point communication.
Probably using, a publisher-subscriber
mechanism to
inform, you know, you're tweeting to
the world that you're going home to see
your parents this weekend.
un, unless your Oedipus or something like
that, just isn't very notable yeah?
[LAUGH] so, the point is, that different
things are usable
in different context, by the way, did
anybody get that?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay, good, all, all the, this is the
value
of liberal arts education, I just want to
point it out
to you right [LAUGH] [LAUGH] Everybody
who's, who's only like,
in pure engineering like, Oedipus what,
what the heck is that?
And, and why do we care if he's going to
see his parents?
[LAUGH]
so so anyway, the point is that, you
want to
pick and choose the mechanisms to use and
patterns, give
you a, language to describe that and of
course,
readable software like we find in Android
and other middleware.
Give us the vehicle for being able to,
implement it and re-use it more readily.
Okay, so that's it for this session.
Any other questions?
[MUSIC]