[MUSIC].
Welcome to the next class, what we're
going to be doing today is talking about
the Active Object pattern, and relating
that
to the various mechanisms at work in
Android.
So, what we're going to do first is we're
going to talk about what the Active Object
pattern is.
And how it's used to structure the
solution for concurrent software.
And then we're going to talk about how the
active object pattern can be applied in
Android.
And I'll give you a bunch of different
examples,
from some things we've already seen, to
some extent.
But we're going to look at 'em a little
bit differently now, in the context of
patterns.
And we're going to be doing this of
course, throughout the course.
I'll, I'll be talking about how android
works, we'll be talking about the classes,
we'll
be talking about the interactions between
the
classes, we'll be talking about the frame
works.
And then what I always try is, whatever
makes sense, to
relate the design choices that android
makes back to patterns, and the
benefit of doing that of course is not
only do you how
Android works a little better because you
can connect it to other.
Written literature that talks about the
solution in
a perhaps more abstract way than Android
documentation does.
But even more importantly you'll
understand how to solve similar problems.
So even if you're not programming an
Android.
If you're programming some other software
environment.
But you run across the same kind of
forces, that Android
ran across, you can know what patterns to
apply to your solution.
So it's, it's meant to give you both
something very specific, and also
something more general.
And it's worth pointing out that's one of
the beautiful things about patterns.
They help give you, immediate benefits.
And they also give you something that will
be fundamental and will last for decades.
Many of the patterns we cover here have
been
known for 20, for 30 years by some people.
And the goal of course, is to make sure
that you guys know them, as well.
All right, so, the particular context
we're going to
focus on here is a situation where a
client.
Wants to invoke methods, of an object
that's running in another thread of
control.
Or it wants those methods to run in
another thread of control.
Now, this of course is a generic issue
we're
going to talk about it primarily in the
context of Android,
but as we go to the pattern, you'll see
that the topics are much more generalized
than just Android.
In this particular context.
A client is any Android code, an activity,
a
service or whatever that wants to execute
a method.
So client, sometimes we think of clients
as being that.
Hardware that is used to connect to
servers.
And that's one way to look at it but the
more general way to look at
it is a client is whoever is invoking the
operation at any given point of time.
So for example we may have a situation
where
some background thread wants to be over to
invoke.
An operation like say send message, and
pass a message
to a handler that's actually connected to
another thread of control.
So that would be the context for this
particular discussion.
So you can see here we have a background
thread, and it says handler.sendmessage.
The handler of course is associated with
this UI thread, and
the handle message method gets called
back, and it does something rather.
That was requested or passed by the
client,
by the color which is a background thread.
More generally of course, we can have the
threads be any threads, they don't
have to be a background thread and a UI
thread that's one common use case.
But, in, in Android of course and more
generally, you can have any
threads that are running and they
want to invoke objects that, whose
implementations.
Residing in or want to execute in another
thread of control.
So we can generalize this point, same
pattern applies, same
structure applies just a slightly
different way of looking at it.
Slightly different mapping on to
mechanisms and, and
use cases in Android or some other system.
So some of the, the problems of design
forces that
we're trying to address here, we'd like to
able to.
Leverage the available parallelism on the
platform as transparently as possible.
We really don't want to require
application developers to
have to know a lot about locking and
synchronization.
Much the same sort of argument we, we
thought about when we discussed the.
Monitor object pattern, but there's a
little bit more to it here.
Remember when we talked about monitor
object?
What was the defining characteristic of an
invocation on a monitor object?
What's the main thing to, to think about
in that context?
Who ends up running that invocation?
When you call a method on a monitor
object, you, when you call
a synchronized method on a monitor object,
who ends up running that method?
>> You
do.
>> You being the?
>> The client.
>> The client?
>> Thread.
>> Yeah.
So, so, the client thread is what ends up
invoking it,
so basically in a monitor object
environment, as with a normal object.
You invoke a method on the object and, the
callee, the guy who's called.
Steals the thread of control of the caller
and it runs in that context.
Another thing we want to be able to do, is
ensure that if you
have long running operations that they
don't
block other things in the process from
executing.
This is primarily relevent if you're
trying to run
things in the UI thread or in a single
thread.
Solution and anyone control if it were to
block would cause
the whole process to hang and we don't
want that to happen.
That's another problem we want to avoid
here.
And then the last piece of the puzzle here
you want to make
access to these shared objects and
synchronized objects as, as simple and as.
Intuitive as possible, we don't want
people to have to know about
the low level details of conditions,
monitors, cues, all that kind of stuff.
They just want to make a method call, and
magic
happens, and that method is executing in
another thread of control.
So to do this, we're going to apply the
Active Object pattern.
The Active Object pattern is a pattern is
a pattern that's documented in the POSA2
book.
And it's actually, it's just later on we
talk about non uses.
It's actually a very widely used pattern
there's actual languages, there're
actual libraries as all kind of things it
implement this particular model.
And we use it to decouple the thread that
invokes.
On that thread, from the thread that runs
the method.
So we're do, and we're going to decouple
method and vocation from method execution.
And method invocation occurs in the client
thread, caller thread.
And method execution occurs in some other
thread.
However from a clients point of view, this
should look like just a regular method
invocation.
It doesn't look like you're doing anything
special.
You're not treating the data or the
invocations in any special way.
Just invoking a method and wallah
something magic happens
and the work gets processed in another
thread of control.
In particular that the client doesn't grab
any
locks, it doesn't use condition variables,
it doesn't
do any queueing it just says you know,
send message or invoke operation or
something like that.
So the active object pattern, the intent
of the active
object pattern is to define service
request on components or objects.
And make this be the unit of concurrency
in
the program, and then run requests for
these services.
In different thread or threads, then the
requesting client.
And then be able to enable the client and
the component to interact asynchronously,
to produce and consume results, that occur
as a result of invoking the service.
Now that, that may may seem like a bit
of a mouthful, but it's actually very very
straightforward, and
we'll, we'll talk about each of those
steps, each of
the pieces of the intent as we walk
through this.
In a nutshell, if you look at this picture
here.
What's happening is we have a client with
a client thread invoking some method on
some interface.
And some magic happens.
And then this thing gets turned into
some kind of, so-called objectified
service request, which
is a, a linearization of the parameters
and
the information that corresponds to the
method call.
And that thing then gets stuck into some
kind of
activation list or queue that is managed
by the active object.
And that guy runs in a separate thread, or
threads of control.
And when the request comes in it gets
stuck in the queue and
then at some point a scheduler takes the
request out of the queue.
And invokes an operation back on some
servant, which is the, the
implementor or the executor, executor of
the original invocation by the client.
So that's how the service request gets
invoked in the active object thread or
threads.
Yeah, Sean.
>> In a diagram you're calling method
one, but method two is eventually getting
called.
Is that
>> Oh that's, yeah that's a good point.
It should be method one getting called,
that's a really good point.
Have to fix that.
That's actually a.
A typo from some other, somewhere else
that I gotta fix.
There's a paper that talks more about this
that's on my website.
You could also take a look of course at
the POSA2
book which is where that, the full blown
pattern is, is described.
Okay so when would you want to apply this
pattern?
What would be the circumstances under
which this patter would make sense?
Well one circumstance would be.
When you want the methods of an
object's interface to define its
concurrency boundaries.
So much like with monitor object, when you
make a method call, you want
that thing to be the place where
the boundary of concurrency's going to be
managed.
You don't want people to have to acquire a
release lock explicitly, for example.
You should also do this when you want the,
the.
Object, to be able to do all the work
internally
and not make the client responsible for
any of the work.
And you also do this if the methods that
you call may need to block.
Maybe they have to download a big file, or
they have to grab a
lock, or they have to do some long running
computation that won't return right away.
So these are sort of three factors that.
Are important to consider when you want to
apply this pattern.
Then some other things that are important
when you want to be
able to have, multiple client method
requests running concurrently on a single
object.
Now this is different from the monitor
The monitor object only lets one method
run at a time.
It locks out anybody who's not.
That one method.
With, with active object however in some
configurations
you can actually have multiple method
request running simultaneously.
Subject to various synchronisation
constraints or scheduling constraints.
We'll talk about that.
And another thing you might have here is
you might want to be able to allow the.
Invocation order to differ from the
execution order.
So the, the order in which you invoke the
operations may not
be the same as the order in which the
operations are actually run.
And again, this has to do with scheduling
constraints, it has
to do with timing properties, priorities
and so on and so forth.
So we'll come back and talk a bit about
that.
Now, what's important to note here, and
we'll come
back and look at this a couple different
times.
Is to compare and contrast active object
with monitor object.
Some things are very similar, to stuff in
green here are essentially
the same motivations for why you might
choose to use monitor object.
You don't want clients to really know
that synchronization is taking place
explicitly its
implicit in the framework, run
implementation, you
would like to be able to have.
The method call interface be the boundary
for concurrency, and you
want to be able to allow things to block
without causing problems.
To some extent, monitor object can still
get you into
trouble if you block, so you have to be
careful there.
In fact, I'll tell you what.
Let me, cause this important, let's, let's
gray that one out.
That, that's really not a good, ex,
reason.
So, it's, it's those two reasons, and then
the others one are ones where active
object has.
Additional capability.
It allows things to run concurrently, it
allows
things to block without disrupting other,
other threads and
other behaviors, and it allows the
execution order to
differ in a, in a wider variety of ways.
We'll talk more about active object and
monitor object
here, a good quiz question at some point
will be.
Compare and contrast active object and
monitor object.
So make sure you understand these things
for the quiz.
But, of course, much more importantly,
make sure you understand the differences
because
they're important differences to
understand from
a conceptual and, practical point of view.
Alright, so here is the structure of the
active object pattern.
As you can see, there's a lot of moving
parts that are going
on here, and so, we're going to step
through them one at a time.
Now, when I, when I show you the example,
I'm going to do this in two ways.
I'm first going to explain it.
Actually, I'll tell you what, first I'll
explain it in terms of
every day experiences you may have had at
some point along your way.
And then I'll talk technically about
what's going on.
And so this may help you to understand
things better.
So I'll kind of go through this with a,
with a metaphor, so the metaphor is.
You're going to a fast food restaurant in
order to get lunch, or to get food.
Now as you all noticed, different kinds of
fast food restaurants,
there's the McDonald's style of fast food
restaurants, where at least historically.
They're bit changed a bit over time, but
historically, you went to McDonald's,
the goal, the goal in any fast food
restaurant is to get people.
To pay and out of the way as quickly as
possible.
Right.
It's about throughput.
Because that equals cashflow, equals
profitability, which all entrepreneurs
like.
Right?
[LAUGH] And so, what we want to be able to
do is find a way to maximize throughput.
So, if you go to McDonald's and you order
a Big Mac, fries, and a Coke.
At least in the early days, what they
would do is they would precook a bunch
things.
They'd have a you know, bunch of precooked
french
fries and they would be under a heat lamp.
They'd have a bunch of precooked Big Macs
under a heat lamp.
They might even have had some pre cor,
prepoured cokes that were sitting there on
the counter.
So when you say, you know, Big Mac, fries,
and
a coke, the, the cashier just sits there,
reaches back, grabs
the stuff that's been precached, right,
that's a good, that's a
good optimization technique, precaching,
and give you the stuff right back.
And typically that's a synchronous
transaction.
You stand there, you order the food.
As long as it's in the cache, you get it,
you go on their way.
They get their money, you get a
heart attack or you know, high, high
cholesterol.
And Christoph, now I'm going to get, get
sued by the food lobby for food libel.
anyway.
Bad things happen right?
But they got the money and everybody's
happy.
So that's one model.
That's not the Active Object.
Well we'll talk about that later.
That, that's called Synchronous two way
blocking.
That's kind like the monitor object
actually.
You can imagine you might have a monitor
to make sure that the two
cashiers are trying to grab a big Mac at
the same time or whatever.
So the Active Object is different and the
Active
Object model, lets use a different kind of
restaurant.
Let's talk about Wendy's.
So does anybody know?
What's the big differentiator that Wendy's
has compared to say, McDonald's.
>> They don't pre-cook their stuff.
>> They cook to order, it's on demand
right?
So imagine what would happen if they did
Wendy's like they did McDonald's.
You'd go up, you'd place your order for a.
Double Wendy's you know, cheeseburger or
something like that.
And then they would go pre-cook, they
would go cook it for you on demand.
Well it would take forever, right?
You'd be stuck there synchronously in that
transaction space.
It would take a long time, and people
would get upset.
Not some, well everybody behind you in
line would get upset.
The owner of the Wendy's franchise would
get upset.
Everybody would be upset, right?
Because they weren't getting throughput,
you weren't getting served.
So what did they do instead?
When you show up there, you have this
transaction with
the cashier, and the cashier placed the
role of a proxy.
So the proxy is sort of the one who's
going to take your order.
Its, its the ambassador or surrogate or
something that's actually going to do the
real work.
And when you place your order you say I
want to have you know, the special burger
with all the
fixings or something, then what they do is
they turn
around and they convert that into some
kind of future.
Right?
The future is the little plastic token
they give
you with a number on it, that's the
future.
They hand you something.
And then they turn around, and you don't
really see this anymore because it's all
done
in, through computer, but that turns up,
out to be a method request or a message.
That shows up in the cook's message queue,
or message list, right?
Of things to cook.
And so, there's a queue of those things.
Who knows how they're ordered, I, you
know, they're, let's probably
assume they're FIFO order, but they could
be ordered some other way.
If let's see.
Trying to figure who'd.
If BIll Clinton, Bill Clinton liked to eat
fast food, right?
So Bill Clinton comes in.
Chances are his order is going to get
moved to the front of the queue, so you
might rearrange the order of these things
based
on the importance of whoever is making the
order.
So that the, the, the requests are in the
queue, and
then the scheduler, which in this case
would be the cook, would
take the requests off one at a time, take
a look
at what they were, and then would start to
cook the meal.
And when the meal is done then they need
to deliver it back to the recipient which
is the,
the this acto so cooking the meal is done
by
the cook when it comes to them from the
schedule.
Says Okay this is what I want you to cook
now so
the cook meal is the operation on the
servant and when you're
all done you then have to give this back
to the person
you place the order and there's a couple
ways to do this
and the way to do it is essential is to
pass this
information back to the caller to the
future and as all you
know in fast food restaurants like Wendy's
there's one way to do
this, one way is to have you periodically
go up to the pick
up window with your little plastic token
in hand,
your future and say is item number 42
ready yet.
That's called polling.
So you poll for your results, the other
approach is for you to
go sit there and read a paper, browse the
web, talk to your friends.
Whatever you do, Make a phone call.
And then when it's done, the person, the
runner or the or the cat
the crook or somebody will come out and
deliver the food to your table.
That's the call back model.
So there's a polling model and a call back
model now, of course, you could just stand
there
by the pickup window, you know, just like
a
hungry puppy waiting for the food to show
up.
That's possible.
That's sort of a blocking future
transaction.
But that's probably not the best way to
spend your time.
And by the way, the other thing that they
do
in these restaurants, another form of
optimization, is they have.
Customers do some of the work, right?
So, they don't fill your cup for you.
They give you a cup, and then you go and
fill up your cup, right?
And, and, sort of the way it works is
they price the drinks where you'd have to
drink, like,
10 gallons worth of soda to, to make up
the
difference in what you just paid for that
soda, right?
Because it probably cost them.
Ten cents and and you paid a dollar 50 for
the
thing so you have to drink a lot of stuff
before
you make up the difference so anyways
that's the active object
pattern described through a fast food
metaphor and then we also
talked about the varies elements and we'll
talk about them again
in a more tactical way next, OK any
questions so that's
that 's kind of thing the other I didn't
really explain
as I was talking this is the mapping on
android so.
You invoke an operation on a handler,
which is a proxy-like thing.
And there's another way to use a, a
handler as a future.
We'll talk about that when we talk later.
The method request in Android out of the
box is essentially a
message that gets stuck into a message
queue, which is the activation list.
There's something we've seen before called
the looper, which plays
the role of the scheduler in conjunction
with the message queue.
And then whatever handler you define at
subclasses from the default
handler class and fills in the handle
message method, that's the servant.
And of course the client is whoever
invoked this thing
in the first place which is like some
activity, perhaps.
Okay, so that's the static view.
There's also of course a dynamic view,
which
isn't much different from what I just told
you.
because we spent a lot of time talking
about the metaphor.
So the client invokes a method call on a
proxy.
And the proxy converts the method call
into a method request, or a message.
Passes that to the scheduler, and returns
a future to the proct, to the client.
The scheduler sticks the method request
onto
some kind of activation list or queue.
At some point later, based on various
properties, the scheduler
takes the message off the queue and then
goes ahead and.
Despatches it on the servant.
Oops that should be pointing over here.
So the servant is the guy that actually
does the work and when he is done
then the client gets the result either by
polling or by some kind of callback.
Okay, so that's, that's basically the
steps
involved from dynamics in the active
object pattern.
Okay, so let's talk about how, what you
need to do to implement this pattern.
Now I'm going to talk about the
implementation in general, and then
I'm also going to show you ways you could
implement this in Android.
Keep in mind that Android, the things
we're talking
about in Android, don't implement the
full-blown active object pattern.
If you want the full blown active object
pattern, you'd have
to devise a little bit thicker wrapper
around a couple of pieces.
But it's, it's pretty darn close.
When we talk later in the course and
we start talking about the Android binder
framework and
the Android interface definition language,
AIDL, you'll see how
you can implement the full blown active
object pattern.
As a variant of the so-called broker
pattern.
And we'll talk about all that stuff
probably, maybe starting next week.
Maybe starting the week after.
Okay, so the first thing you need to do
from an
implementation point of view is you
need to implement the invocation
infrastructure.
Now keep in mind what we're trying to do
here.
We're trying to come up with a way.
To convert a method call from the client,
say from an activity or whatever, some
client thread or somebody who's making a
call, into a method request or a message.
And that thing is then going to be stuck
onto a queue or an activation list.
So that's what the proxy's role is.
So the proxy is basically this surrogate
that
looks like the actual target of the
request.
But instead is just doing some minimal
work to convert a
method call into something that can be
queued for later processing.
Now, when we talk about more
complex environments, when we talk about
communicating
between address spaces on an android
device, when we talk about communicating
between.
An Android device, and a server in the
cloud or a data center somewhere.
We'll see how proxy plays another very
important role.
So we'll talk more about proxy later.
If you don't have the deep fullest
understanding of proxy don't despair.
We'll cover this as a, as its own pattern
later.
That pattern appears in the gang of four
book.
It also appears in post of one book.
You can pick it up online.
So that's basically what the proxy is.
Or actually let me do something here.
Probably want to, clean that slide and add
proxy.
If you take a look online, you'll find out
the proxy, pattern is described.
On Wikipedia so you can find what it looks
like.
Ok so, so that's basically what the proxy
is.
If you take a look at the handler at Java
file you'll
see it defines the proxies in the form of
these methods called
send method or message so there's a cup of
variations as send
message as you can see send message turns
around called send message delayed.
Send message delayed, turns around and
calls send message
at time, and send message at time actually
does something.
And what that something is, is it
basically converts things
into a message that's going to be stuck
into a message queue.
So that, that's the way that the proxy
works.
And this variant of the pattern applied to
Android.
It, it's a very simple, kind of stripped
down version.
The proxy and method request
implementation for
the Android handler, are not as
sophisticated as
the full blown pattern, but they're good
enough for our purposes to make the point.
So, the message gets turned into something
that gets stuck into a queue.
Okay, the next thing you need to do is you
need to implement the activation list the
activation list is
the thing that keeps track of these method
requests which
remember a method request is a
objectification of a method call
so it's going to basically store the
information dealing with
the perimeters and other information
that's necessary to identify what
method hat invoked and so you need to be
able
to insert and remove these method request
into some kind of.
Data structure which in this case is
accorded activation list in the pattern
nomenclature.
Typically not always but typically this
list is implemented as
some kind of synchronised buffer where you
can have one thread,
or more thread, more than one thread
putting request method
request into the buffer simultaneously in
a synchronised thread safe way.
And then one or more threads, taking
things out
of that buffer in a synchronized and
thread-safe way.
So what would that kind of thing look like
in Android?
Well, that kind of thing in Android would
be something like the message queue.
The message queue is defined as part of
the
core kind of OS framework portion of the
Android middleware.
And it has methods like end queue message,
which you give a
message and a, and a time when you want
the message to run.
And then it also has ways of dequeuing
things from the message queue
using methods like next which will block,
then we have to go ahead and
implement a scheduler of some kind, so in
this particular case in you can
look at the schedule a couple different
ways but in the contexts of patterns.
The scheduler is basically our so called
command processor and let's say I guess I
to be fully, to be fully pattern compliant
and cross reference enabled.
I should mention command processor pattern
URL here, so the command processor.
Pattern is a pattern, which we'll talk
about later, which you can
use to pass command objects between
address spaces or between threads of
control.
And so the scheduler basically implements
this
pattern, and you in queue things into the
message the activation list, and then you
get it out in another thread of control.
And the scheduler figures out when it can
retrieve.
The request from the activation list.
And there's a bunch of different variants.
The, the simple one is just to have the
activation list
be a FIFO queue and have the scheduler
simply do FIFO scheduling.
Whatever's next in the queue, you take it
out.
There are all kinds of other variants.
You could have a priority queue.
That was the example I gave, where, where
Bill Clinton
wants to order a Big Mac, or a Wendy's
hamburger.
So we, we prioritize, presidents get
special preference over other people.
You might also have situation where you're
going
to, to queue things up based on delay.
So things don't get de-queued until a
certain amount of time passes.
So you might invoke a bunch of operations,
but give them different delays.
And then they'll show up coming out of the
que
in the order of their earliest deadline
first, in the que.
And there's other variances as well.
You can have more complicated
synchronization guards, where you
could check to see if more certain
conditions were satisfied.
And if so, then the scheduler would get a
chance to execute or deque those, those
method requests.
In the android case it's pretty simple.
We have this message queue and things get
queued up based on the order
that they appear and or the time at which
they are supposed to run.
And so it's basically a timed delay, time
based queue.
And so, basically there's the looper and
the looper
sits there waiting to pull stuff out of
the queue.
And it pulls stuff out of the que and then
it goes ahead and dispatched
it so that's the scheduler and then we
have the servant servant is actually the
guy who does the work who implements
the application specific behavior when it
receives work
from a client in general servants can be
implement in all kinds of different ways.
One very common way to implement the
active
pattern is to have the proxy and the
servants
have the same methods with the same
signatures
and that way it looks just like an object,
you know when you invoke a method on
an object, the implementation of that
method is, is
the same name it's got the same signature,
the same [INAUDIBLE] in fact it's the same
thing.
In an active object environment you have a
couple of choices.
One choice you can make is to have a
mirrored relationship, between the name
of the method you invoke and the name on
the servant that gets called back.
Another approach, which is the more way
Android does it is
we have a method we use to pass the
request there,
called send message, then we have a method
with a slightly
different name called handle message, that
actually retrieves the requested processes
it.
Probably the most obvious reason for doing
that is if.
They called both methods send method or
send message you'd have a,
an overload ambiguity problem because
handler
needs to support both these things.
It needs to be able to support send
message to get the data to the handler.
And it has to have some kind of call-back
hook to do the work.
So that's probably why they did it that
way, but there are other alternatives.
So in the case of Android handle message
is the thing that actually does the work.
It's the servant and you implement it by
sub
classing from handler and filling in
whatever you want.
So here we have a worker handler with
a handle message method that does
something or other.
And then the last thing you have to do is
figure out how you're going
to get the results, if any, back to the
original client who invoked the operation.
Now, a lot of times with Android, when you
do a send
message call on a handler, you're not
really expecting anything back in return.
For example, imagine you have some
long-running computation.
That's downloading a file in the
background thread and when that background
thread
is done it wants to send the result back
to the UI thread.
Well in that case all it does is it simply
says send message and then voila handler
message gets called back in the UI thread
and
the UI thread does something to display
the result.
So in that case there is no communication
it's just a one way invocation.
There other scenarios and we'll look at
some
in a second where there's two way
communication.
And, so if there's two way communication
you have to
have a way to get back to your original
caller.
And there's a whole bunch of different
ways to do this.
One way to do this, which we show here, in
Android.
Is to pass as part of the original message
to the to the active object
to the handler you contain in the message
essentially the reply handler the
the handler of the guy who set the thing
in the first place so
you can see here in this particular
example which we'll look at more detail
later.
We get the message, we go ahead and we
crack
it open, and we get some arguments that
were passed in.
And then we go take a look at the
args.handler field, and we, that,
that's the handler of the guy who sent us
the message in the first place.
And we obtain a, we'd use obtain message,
which is
a factory method that's used to get back a
message.
And then we go ahead and fill
in some results and then we say
reply.sendtoTarget.
And sendtoTarget is simply a, a little
convenience method that says Send Message,
this.
It basically sends a message back to
itself.
So this guy's going to be used to send a
message back to, the original client.
And I'll show you this in a second to make
it a little more clear.
[SOUND] Okay.
So that's kind of, the implementation
steps.
Now what I'm going to do is I'm going to
show you a really
cool place in Android that implements
this, and, we're going to look at this
example later on in the class, and you may
get a chance
to play around with it and use it for one
of the assignments.
But for right now, I'll kind of show you
how it works under the hood.
It's really cool.
So there's something in Android that's
called an AsyncQueryHandler,
and AsyncQueryHandler is used in, in just
a few
places in Android but one of the places
it's
used, is in the MMS implementation for
various things.
AsyncQueryHandler is a little helper
class, [SOUND] that is used to, invoke
calls on, content revolvers, which I'll
talk more about in a second, in such a
way that they don't block synchronizely
for the content resolution operation to
complete,
so what is a content resolver does anybody
remember what a content resolver is.
Chad, [LAUGH].
>> it, handles the results from the
content provider.
>> Right, and what's a ContentProvider
[LAUGH].
>> A way of sharing information?
>> Right.
So the ContentProvider is basically a, a
facade, or a proxy, to data that's often
stored persistently, most commonly using
SQLite Database implementations.
You can use other things, too.
You can use FileStar.
But basically, it's a way of getting
access to some persistent data.
And, out of the box.
[SOUND] if you use the ContentResolver.
You'll do the following, you'll have an
activity, and you'll call an
operation like say query, there's other
operations to insert, delete and so on.
But you can call query on a
ContentResolver, and
by default, the ContentResolver will go
out and get
the data and return it back to the caller
but the, caller thread blocks until the
caller returns.
So that's what's called a syncronis two
way operation.
Now as you may imagine, there's all kinds
of downsides.
What's, what's one of the main downsides
with this, in the context of Android?
>> You couldn't do anything to UI.
>> The UI thread will be blocked while
this is
taking place, and if you're doing a very
complicated query.
Then, you could end up with the dreaded
application not
responding dialog popping up and then
you'll have problems right.
So what AsyncQueryHandler does, is it
implements the Active Object.
It actually implements the full blown
Active Object.
Well a, pretty full blown Active Object
here, in order to be able to.
Decouple the invocation from the
processing, from the reply.
And here's essentially how this works.
So, the activity invokes an operation on,
a subclass of
async handler called my async handler,
which you would create.
We'll talk about why you do that in a
second.
You do that so you can get the results of
the, operations when they're done.
And you, you do an operation with the name
start.
Like start query.
Start, insert.
Start, delete, and so on.
And start, goes ahead and kicks things
off, but it returns right away.
It, it doesn't block.
It's an async.
It, it starts things off, and returns
immediately.
And what happens is that, the start query
method creates a message.
And, it does a send message, to a worker
thread,
it's a worker handler that's running in,
in the background.
So it's a background thread that's started
up
when the whole thing starts, and it,
continuously runs.
And, the send message calls also returns
right away, but the first thing
it does is it converts the arguments into
a, method request or a message.
Sticks them onto the worker handler's,
message queue or
activation list, returns right away, so
that doesn't block.
And then, the worker handlers handle
message call gets invoked
in a separate thread of control, and that
guy goes off.
And he does the blocking, call on the
ContentResolver.
So the original worker, the original
activity thread is
off doing whatever the activity thread
wants to do
with this point, waiting for more, input
from users,
and there's work taking place in the
background, in the
background thread and the worker thread,
and that guy
is querying, the actual ContentResolver,
he's blocking what he can
afford to block cause he's not blocking
the UI
thread so that's perfectly, perfectly
calls you to do that.
[COUGH] When, the handle message in the
worker thread, returns.
I'm sorry, when the query operation in the
handle worker, thre, worker
thread returns, that guy then turns around
and does a send to target.
Call on the actual, reply handler that
corresponds back to this thing
that was originally used to invoke the
operation in the first place.
My Async Query Handler.
And that asynchronously sends the results
back and
returns right away so he can process other
request,.
And then this guy's handle message, method
gets called.
And he turns around and dispatches, the
callback hook that is defined
as an abstract method in AsyncQueryHandler
that does the completion processing.
So when you invoke, say, an async query,
when
the query is done, you get the result of
that
async query, which typically come back to
you as
a cursor which has the data that was
requested that
match your query, that comes back as a
cursor, back in the activity thread or the
incur thread and that comes back with a on
query complete
call back cut and so un query complete is
a an abstract
method to find a query abstract query
handle.
You sub-class that, fill it in, and that
guy
gets called back after the query has
returned asynchronously.
So you can kind of see it's a really nice
example, of the
active object pattern because we're
decoupling
the end vocation of an operation.
In other words you know, run a query.
From, the processing of that operation,
and then we get
the result back at some later time through
a call back.
In this, in this case it's a call back, on
a, on a future that was, dispatched.
Really, really, really cool stuff that,
query handler stuff is described here.
Oh I guess I should also, probably add
path name for a sync
[SOUND] createhandler.java so you can look
at the codes and it's really
cool to watch how it works and, if you
don't know the active Java
pattern and you don't understand all the
things we've talked about.
it's a little bit difficult to figure out
what the code is doing, once
you understand the pattern is just a
breeze you're like oh yeah, that's this
piece, that's the proxy, that's the
scheduler,
that's the activation list and what makes
it tricky of course is that these
are things that appear in multiple places,
right.
It's not, self contained the the handler
file has some pieces of it, the looper and
handler parts of Android have some other
pieces of it but the pattern is what.
Pulls all this stuff together, [SOUND] and
knowledge of how that pattern works
help make it a lot easier to understand
how to use this particular mechanism.
I remember over the summer we were doing
a, a project with some folks here, and
we were trying to decide do we use
AsyncQueryHandler do we use cursor
loaders, and I think
one of the things that made,
AsyncQueryHandler hard
at the time was just really knowing how
all
the pieces fit together, right, so once
you
know the pattern, it makes it a lot
easier.
Okay.
internally, the AsyncQueryHandler uses a
subset of the Active Object pattern.
So as you can see, we start the query.
That turns into a, creates a message.
We call the worker, handler thread, send
message call.
That goes over here to the worker
handler, object and its thread, through
its handler.
And this guy has a looper.
And he pulls the request off, does some
processing
and then they get called back, and so on,
and there's, there's more parts to it than
I'm
showing you here but these are the basic
pieces.
There's the, there's the source code.
I can get rid of that.
[SOUND] Comment over here.
We actually don't need to do that.
[SOUND].
Let's see if there's anything else we need
to cover there.
[NOISE] So, anyway, it's, it's definitely
worthwhile to take a
look at that code and sort of puzzle
through it.
Once you understand the pattern, all the
pieces make a lot more sense.
And you find this, through and throughout
Android, through and throughout Java.
The people who, implemented Java, the
people under, who implemented Android.
Really understand patterns.
So you'll see a lot of recurring,
approaches over, and over, and over again.
And it's, it's almost, you know, paint by
number after awhile.
There's certain other idioms we'll talk
about later, when
we talk about services that use command,
command processor pattern.
And they do the same thing every time.
Okay, so let's talk a bit about the, the
consequences of this pattern.
So, the good part about this pattern is,
it enhances concurrency.
And simplifies, synchronization
complexity.
And, the reason that it enhances this
stuff is because it
allows us to have, client threads and
method invocations run, concurrently.
You, you invoke an operation and it was in
another thread.
Multiple threads can invoke operations.
They'll run in those, in the other thread,
or threads as we'll see in a second.
You can have a scheduler that can
be used to evaluate various
synchronization restraints.
If you have multicore, processors on your
platform,
and you, have the stomach to make sure
you're.
Servant code is thread safe.
Then you could actually spawn a pool of
threads.
Typically, roughly around the same size as
the number of cores, give or take.
Typically, give, you have few more threads
than there are cores.
Maybe if you have four cores, you might
have eight threads in the pool for various
reasons.
And, so, in that case, when you invoke
these operations,
you could have multiple threads or one
thread invoking multiple operations.
And all of these operations without one
concurrently,
so you can transparently speed your,
program up
assuming a; that there's work that could
be
paralyzed which is always tricky and that
you've
done a proper job of doing locking and
other things in your code, and once you
understand monitor objects once you
understand, the basics
of synchronization with Java that becomes
tractable certainly.
Another interesting thing is the, method
of invocation
order and the method execution order can
differ.
Now, this is true for the pattern in
general but
in the case of Android if you, put the lay
operations.
If you know, take a look here you can see
we have these delay calls.
When you invoke a message, you can, get a
delay time, you can either
give it an absolute time, or you can give
it a time that's relative to
the current time of day, there are
different method calls for each one of
those things, and that will affect where
the method, goes and when it gets run.
And so, they store things in a way so that
they're
queued up and running at the right time or
the appropriate time.
There are of course.
There's very, very rarely there's a
totally free lunch in a, software design.
So there are some, liabilities or
downsides to this particular pattern.
So one of the things you gotta be very
careful of, is that you don't end up.
Running into an additional over head, for
al the different parts that are
needed to make the Active Object work
properly and let's, let's talk about
where those over heads come from so one
the things you got to
do when you do active object is
you typically have to delicate the
dynamically.
Because the thread that, invokes something
is
different from the thread that, executes
it.
And therefore you have to allocate,
typically you have
to allocate dynamically, because they
can't share buffers easily.
And the minute you start allocating things
dynamically, there's a bunch of issues.
The code maybe, somewhat slower, because
you have
to allocate stuff and go out to the heap.
You typically have to acquire a lock to
lock the heap.
And in languages like, like C++ and
C, where you have, don't have garbage
collection.
You have to de-allocate stuff and that
requires things, and it, does heap
memories, all kinds of stuff that is
potentially downside if you allocate
memory dynamically.
In Java, you don't have a lot of choice
most of the time, but in other languages
you do.
Another consequence is whenever you, put
these things
on and off the queue that involve
synchronization operations,
and synchronization operations are pretty
fast, but they're not,
complete free now days good
synchronization, operations that are
implemented in the hardware probably
running at the
order of nano seconds or tens of nano
seconds
or maybe you know, micro seconds or
something like
that they're really fast but it's more
then nothing.
The real kicker is the context switches
when you start
moving things between, threads or between
processors cords on a machine.
Then, it typically takes a while to switch
contexts and that
can start running in, you know, thousands
of instructions to do that.
There may be, I know tens or
hundreds of microseconds of overhead for
context switches
which is, we're getting faster and faster
all the time but it's still not for free.
And another tricky thing, if you start
running, in multi-core environments or,
shared memory
environments, where you move data between
different
processors, that can involve various
low-level CPU cache.
Overhead.
From moving, flushing caches, and, dealing
with cache lines, and all kinds of things.
That's kind of a hidden, overhead, because
it
doesn't really show up at the software
level.
But it's all part of what the, underlying
bus and memory hierarchy and
memory system is doing to actually
implement the stuff, down in the hardware.
So those are some things that can make.
The overhead be more, that would be the
case, just make a normal method call.
Now, when would this matter, when would
this not matter?
If you're going to run an operation that
runs for a long time,
you're going to invoke an active object
method that's going to run for, a minute.
The fact that it took.
A couple of microsecond to, to switch
contexts and
synchronise and allocate memory, is
completely in the noise.
If you're going to run, an operation that
adds to numbers
together and returns them, these overheads
really start to add up.
So think carefully about how long your
operations
run, before you decide to use active
object.
Don't just go crazy and put active object
everywhere,
because it will guarantee to slow your
system down.
Another tricky thing is, and this is
almost always
a liability, when you're starting to do
with concurrency.
Just at anything you do that runs
concurrently is going to be tricky to the
bug, because you got multiple things going
on, there's challenges that we talked
about
before, the accidental complexities,
crummy debuggers, changing
in terms of the order in which
things run, changing the time, duration of
which things run, those are all but
subtle.
And tricky issues.
And so, there's non determin, determinism
issues.
Your program may not execute the same each
time
you run it, so debugging can be more
difficult.
That's just a problem in general.
>> [COUGH].
>> People sometimes use subsets of Active
Objects to make this more tractable.
A very common subset of Active Object is
to kind of simplify the proxy,
kind of simplify the service, and kind of
pass messages back and forth using.
Using queues.
If you think about, what I showed
you with Android, it's kind of somewhere
in between.
It's not the full-blown Active Object, but
it's not just a message queue, either.
It's got some additional, flare on either
side of that.
So, it works more sophisticated.
But it's certainly an example, a nice
example, of Active Objects.
There's lots of, known uses of this stuff.
There's a, bunch of programming languages
that are
based on the so-called actor model, which
is
a, mathematical model of computation,
concurrent computation, and
it basically does what we've just talked
about.
If you read the Wikipedia article about
the
actor model, it sounds like the active
object patter.
Don't be surprised, it's basically the
same thing.
There Active Object implementations in
various languages and frameworks.
Here's a nice example, that.
Herb Sutter from Microsoft did, showing
how to
do, a simple Active Object implementation
in C++ 11.
I won't go through this, in the interest
of time, I
won't go this in full, full-blown detail,
but it's really cool.
It basically typed us a, a functor with
a, operator function call method defined
in it.
And you go down here and in the
constructor
of this active class it goes ahead and,
creates a
new thread with an anonymous Lambda,
expression that would
run a separate thread of control, calling
the run method
here's the run method, the run method
loops while
we're not done, and it pulls messages out
of this
message queue, and it goes ahead and it
executes
those messages because they have a falter
default on them.
And when the destructor runs it says shut
yourself down.
So, anyway I won't go through the whole,
the whole thing in here
but it's pretty cool, and it illustrates
how to implement the stuff in C++11.
ACE,
the framework that we've developed, for
many
years here at Vanderbilt and other places
also has Active Objects implementations so
you can, learn more about those as well.
so to summarize clients, may sometimes
need to be able to issue, service request
that need to run on other threads of
control in that case we may want to
schedule the activities to run or skip to
the operations request to run based on
varies criteria such as the time or the
priority or the deadlines and so on.
The active object kind of coordinates
these stuff and makes
it easier to program so it looks more like
a regular.
Programming an object it just happens to
run
concurrently and you can read more about
it
here, and as I mention before its
instructive
to compare to test Active Object with
another object.
The main difference is, Active Object is
more
powerful, it, it can run things, more
concurrently but.
It also, is more complicated, and there
could be
some additional overhead, for the reasons
we talked about before.
Okay.
Any questions about, any of the topics
that we just covered?
[SOUND].
[MUSIC]