[MUSIC]
Welcome to the next part of the module on
Android services and security which covers
the Android IntentService.
In this part, we'll explain how the
Android IntentService provides a framework
for programming
started services that can currently
process commands
expressed as Intents, as described in this
link.
We'll start by summarizing how the Android
IntentService
codifies a common idiom for concurrent
event processing.
Although we present this idiom in the
context of the download
service implementation discussed in the
previous
video, it's actually used throughout
Android.
This idiom involves two classes and
several methods.
The first step in the idiom involves
overriding the onCreate hook method
defined by a
service, which creates and starts a
Handler
Thread that processes Intent commands in
the background.
And then gives the handle threads looper
to an instance of
a service handler, so it will handle
messages in a background thread.
The second step in this idiom involves
overriding the onStart
Command method to create a message, that
encapsulates the Intent
parameter and the idea of the start
request and passes
it to the service handler by calling it
Send Message method.
The third step in the idiom involves
overwriting the handleMessage
hook method in the service handler
subclass to process the
message containing the Intent, which in
this case involves downloading
the image, storing it in a local file on
the device.
And returning the path name to the
activity
so it can be displayed to the user.
After the processing is finished the
service shuts
itself down via a call to stop self.
This idiom appears in a number of Android
packed applications, including
the calender and mms sms applications as
show in these path names.
[MUSIC]
Now that we've analyzed Android's idiom
for concurrent processing of Intents,
we'll show how this idiom is codified by
the Android IntentService.
Which is a subclass of service that
provides a started service
framework for concurrently processing
asynchronous commands
expressed as Intents as shown here.
The IntentService framework is easy to use
since subclasses simply override its
onHandleIntent hook
method and provide the logic for
processing
an Intent in a single background thread.
The typical use case for the IntentService
is also straightforward.
As we'll show using a variant of
the download service shown in the previous
video.
In the download application example, a
client sends
intent via calls to the start service
method.
Data, and even objects, can be passed
through the
IntentService, by putting extras into the
Intents, which is
used throughout Android to exchange
information between activities or
between an activity and a service as shown
here.
The IntentService is started on-demand via
the Activatior pattern,
which efficiently and transparently
launches services on-demand as shown here.
Subclasses of the IntentService implement
the onHandleIntent
hook method, to process the Intent sent
by the client concurrently in a background
threat by automatically performing the
steps outlined here.
For example, the onHandleIntent hook
method for the download service
simply calls downloadImageAndReply to
concurrently
retrieve the requested image, store
it in a file in the device, and pass the
path name back to the download activity
that originally called startService.
[MUSIC]
The IntentService implementation applies
the idiom described earlier in this
video, as shown by the code at this path
name.
In particular, its onCreate hook method
creates a
ServiceHandler which internally spawns a
single background Handler Thread.
Its onStart command hook method calls the
ServiceHandler's send message method to
enqueue each intent
received from clients into the message
queue managed
by the Handler Thread running in the
background.
The ServiceHandler's handle message hook
method then
receives the message containing the Intent
in
the Handler Thread and dispatches the
overwritten
onHandleIntent hook method, to process the
Intent.
Thereby ensuring, that long range
processing doesn't block the
user-interface thread.
The only and singleIntent is processed at
a
time by the one and only background
thread.
Finally the IntentService stops itself
automatically when
there are no more Intents to process.
In contrast a regular service must stop
itself
manually by calling the stopSelf method
and application code.
[MUSIC]
Now that we've summarized the structure
and the functionality of the IntentService
framework, we'll analyze its
implementation based
on the code at this path name.
The IntentService class extends the
service super class and overrides several
hook methods to process asynchronous
requests expressed as IntentCommands on
demand.
The IntentService class also defines
Looper
mServiceHandler objects as volatile data
members
to ensure that they are visible to the
background handler's thread, when a
client calls the start service method,
the android service framework launches the
IntentService
and evokes its onCreate Hook method, which
creates and then starts a thread.
To process the Intent concurrently in the
background using the handle thread class
covered here.
onCreate then passes the handle threads to
looper, to the constructor of service
handler.
So it's handle message hook method will be
dispatched in the context of that thread.
Each time an Intent is sent to the intent
service by the start service method.
The Android service framework invokes its
onStart command hook method, which
in turn invokes the OnStart Helper method
that forwards the intent
to the ServiceHandler by creating a
message containing the intent and
the start ID to guide subsequent
processing and shut down behavior.
Finally, onStart calls the
ServiceHandler's send
message method to pass the intent
and start ID to the background Handler
Thread using the hammer framework.
Since service handler extends handler,
it's
handle message hook method runs in the
context of the Handler Thread and receives
messages passed to it via sendMessage.
Handler message dispatches the
onHandleIntent
hook method which must be over
ridden by sub classes of IntentService, to
process the intent concurrently.
Only one intent is processed at a time,
but the processing happens
in the Handler Thread, that runs
concurrently with respect to other
application logic.
Therefore, if this hook method runs for a
long time, it will hold up
other requests with the same intent
service,
but will not hold up anything else.
When I handleIntent returns, the stopSelf
method is automatically called to
stop the IntentService, using the shutdown
idiom presented in the previous video.
After the IntentService stops itself,
Android service framework invokes it's on
destroy hook method which quits the looper
and then shuts down the handle thread.
[MUSIC]
In summary, the Android IntentService
provides the
framework to codifies a common Android
idiom.
It creates a Handler Thread that processes
Intent commands in the background.
Likewise, it uses the hammer framework to
dispatch calls to the onHandleIntent hook
method, which performs application defined
processing of
the intent parameter passed through this
method.
The IntentService is designed for started
services that only need to
process a singleIntent request at a time
and a background thread.
If additional concurrency is needed, then
other solutions are available.
As we'll discuss later.
The IntentService is a classic application
of the command processor pattern, which
packages a piece of application
functionality
as well as it's parameterization of
an object to execute it in another
context, which in this case
is a different process or a different
thread, as covered in upcoming videos.
If you compare the Android implementation
of the IntentService
with a download service implementation in
the previous videos
or with the open source Android calendar
and mms
sms applications, you'll get a sense of
deja vu.
Since they're very similar, which shows
how frameworks often evolve
organically by refactoring common idioms
and patterns into reusable software
components.
The IntentService itself is also used
heavily
in Android's packaged applications, as
shown here.
Additional information on the Android
IntentService appears at this link.