[MUSIC]
So let's take a look a this bit of code
that we've got here.
That's trying to make it so that we have
a flexible mechanism for storing data on a
device.
And so in this example, we have developer
who's gone through and built an ex,
an extraction called a storage handler,
that
can be plugged into this data storage
system.
And we can have different types of storage
handlers plugged in that are both public
and private.
So, for example, a public storage handler
can store data to the SD card.
Whereas a private storage handler can save
it to the app's private data storage
and encrypt it or do other things to it to
make it hard to access.
So, it has become a much more complicated
problem to look
at this code, and suddenly decide, is this
code secure or not?
Is it leaking data under the SD card?
One of the areas of, of difficulty in
understanding how this
code works, is we have a common interface
restoring all data.
That is, all data we're storing is going
through the same method.
In this case it's this stored data method.
That takes a key end value and stores it.
So, when you look at this, take a
second and say, can you immediately spot
the error?
And if you did see this code, would you
think that it was bad code?
Would you think that it was well
structured and modular code?
And probably, whoever built it knew what
they were doing?
Or would you be suspicious of it because
it's not
as simple and straightforward as the
examples that we've seen before.
Let's stop and take a second to look at
what this code is actually doing, and
it'll help us
to decide if we like this approach and the
series
of abstractions that this code is built on
top of.
The most basic, we have a set of key value
pairs that are being stored on the
underlying storage system.
And we take these key value pairs, and we
pass them to a method called store data.
And what store data does is then, based on
the key, it extracts a type from the data.
So we're going to read into the key, and
we're going to extract the type.
And then based on the type, it's going to
look up a handler that
can do the actual storage for that
particular type of data.
And then ask the handler to, and this our
storage
handler not an android handler, to store
the
data and then the handler itself may go
and store in
different locations either the SD card if
it's an
insecure one, or it may get stored down to
the private
data of that app.
And all of this is dependent upon the key
that is put into this store data method.
If that key has a type that says that it's
okay to be stored on the
SD card, then the app will store go ahead
and store it on the SD card.
If the key has an attribute that says it
should be private, then the
store data method is going to look up the
appropriate handler for private data.
And store it in the apps private data
maybe encrypt it, or applying other things
to it.
Now, if we look at this from a
software engineering or maybe a software
design perspective this
doesn't look all bad we've got an
abstraction that's
used to provide modularity inside the
store data method.
That is, these handlers allow us to plugin
new handler implementations.
We've got different handlers that are
dedicated to different functions.
So, it appears like we're building a nice
set of abstractions for storing data.
Now, let's take a look and dive a little
bit deeper into one
aspect of this application, and that's
this extraction of a type from the key.
We see that the first thing that we do in
order
to derive this type, is we're extracting a
suffix from the type.
So we're looking for the end dot something
on the keys that are provided.
And the idea behind this is that, any key,
that has
.puser on it, is going to be assumed to be
private data.
And any key that has .group on it, is
going to be assumed to be public data.
And then, based on these keys, these,
these
suffixes that are being attached to the
keys.
The actual code is going in looking up the
appropriate
handler, and delegating to it by calling
the store method.
So, it's looking up the handler in this
map, using that type.
Now, why is this a problem?
Well, let's look at this specific code
example.
If we look down in our Save Settings
method, one of the things that we
can see is that we're saving the private
groups, whatever that is, for this
particular app.
And we are creating a key, that's called a
private.groups.puser.
So this is clearly data that the developer
intended to be private.
Now, if we look a little farther up, what
we see is, suddenly we have a problem now.
Because this expression that's being used
to extract the type from the key,
in this case what we're doing a series of
substring operations on the string.
The developer didn't think through the
fact that
there might be keys that had dots within
them.
And we might end up in a situation where
we could extract the incorrect type from
the key.
So if we actually apply this function to
the private.groups.puser,
what we get is groups is what this thing
thinks is the suffix.
This expression thinks that groups is the
suffix,
when in reality .puser is supposed to be
the suffix, but because it thinks it's
groups,
it extracts groups and uses that as the
type.
Which then causes the public storage
handler to get
used, which stores this data onto the SD
card.
So in this case, it wasn't directly
obvious
that the developer was doing the wrong
thing.
But the fact that the user was, had to
write code that used this interface that
had a series of abstractions, that hid the
actual function of the code.
It made it difficult to see that private
data was actually being leaked onto the SD
card.
And, you know, certainly there are, there
are developers that
make mistakes and do the obvious things
that we've looked at.
But probably most of the mistakes that we
see out there from a security
perspective, or at least I hope they are,
are from this type of scenario.
Where we have a complex set of
abstractions that cause the developer
not to see a mistake in their code that
causes a security problem.