[MUSIC]
Welcome to the next part of the module
on services and local interprocess
communication mechanisms which
focuses on the mechanisms and frameworks
provided by
Android to enable communication between
activities and services.
In this part, we'll discuss how activities
can communicate to services as well
as how services can reply back
to activities that initiate communication
with them.
In addition to describing these
mechanisms, we'll also outline common
patterns
Android uses to implement frameworks
that support activity and service
communication.
Before covering these communication
mechanisms in
frameworks, we'll first delve deeper into
the
deployment model of started and bound
services, which can be configured to run
in the same process or in different
processes than their clients based on
the process element setting in an Android
manifest XML file, as shown here.
By default, services run in the same
process as other components in an
application.
To deploy a service in a separate process,
the
process element must be added to the
Android manifest file.
Although running activities and services
in the same
process is the most common deployment
model for
Android applications, there are several
reasons for running
a service in its own process, as discussed
here.
For example, a service must run in its
own process if it's shared by multiple
applications, which
is why the Android Bluetooth service runs
in
a separate process as shown at this path
name.
Likewise, if a service running in its
own process memory address space fails or
hangs,
the applications that use it may be
more robust, assuming they're programmed
defensively of course.
Moreover, if garbage collection occurs in
the virtual machine
of a service running in its own process,
that
won't affect other parts of the
application running in
other processes which may make the
application more responsive.
When a service runs in a different process
than the activity, then
they need some form of inner process
communication mechanism to exchange data.
Android implements these IPC mechanisms
using the binder framework covered
here which supports two-way or one-way
client service communication models that
could be programmed via interfaces,
generated from stubs by the Android
Interface Definition Language compiler, or
via messages passed using messenger
objects.
Depending on the type of communication
mechanism you
use by activities and services some
modifications to application
code may be needed to exchange objects and
data
correctly across processes as we'll show
throughout this module.
[MUSIC]
Android provides several mechanisms that
activities
can use to initiate communications with
services.
Selecting the right mechanism depends on
various factors, such as whether the
service
is started or bound, whether a
message-oriented
or method-oriented programming model is
desired, etc.
A simple way an activity can communicate
to a started service is by
passing an intent command to the start
service method, as shown in earlier
videos.
Parameters can be added as extras to the
intent and then
extracted by the started service and used
to guide its subsequent processing.
Two different mechanisms can be used to
communicate with
bound services, after first connecting to
them by calling
BindService and receiving a binder object
from the service's
on-bind hook methods, as shown in an
earlier video.
The first of these communication
mechanisms involves message passing by
calling
send on a reference to an Android
messenger that's covered here.
A messenger is a generalization of the
hammer framework, discussed here,
that encapsulates a reference to a handler
implemented within a service.
An activity uses this reference to pass
messages to the service's handler, even if
it's configured to run in a different
process, as shown in an upcoming video.
The other mechanism for communicating with
bound services involves invoking methods
on
stubs generated by the Android Interface
Definition Language Compiler that's shown
here.
These AIDL method calls can be programmed
to
implement various behaviors, such as
two-way synchronous request response
interactions, two-way asynchronous request
response interactions, or purely
one-way method calls, as shown in an
upcoming video.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC]
Android also provides several mechanisms
that services can use
to reply back to activities that initiate
communication with them.
The activity initiating the communication
typically dictates the reply
mechanism based on information it passes
to the service.
A simple way to communicate from a service
back to an activity involves the messenger
mechanism
covered here, and discussed earlier in
this video
in the context of activity to service
communication.
When used for service to activity
communication, the activity creates a
messenger that
encapsulates a reference to a handler
implemented
within the activity and then gives the
service a reference to the messenger via
the appropriate means, such as adding
it as an extra to the intent command,
passed to the start service method.
The service then extracts the reference to
this messenger, and
uses it to send a reply back to the
activity,
which is delivered to the activity's reply
handler, via its
handle message hook method, as shown in an
upcoming video.
Another common service to activity
communication mechanism involves the use
of callback objects based on the Android
Interface Definitional Language,
or AIDL, which can be passed from the
activity to
the service via a one-way AIDL method call
as covered here.
In this approach the service simply
invokes
the appropriate one-way AIDL method on the
callback
object to return its reply back to the
activity as shown in an upcoming video.
A variant to this approach uses a two-way
AIDL method
called from the activity on the service
which implicitly returns a
reply from the service back to the
activity when the up
call from the stub to the two-way method
implementation is done.
Although two-way method calls seem
convenient to
program, they're actually rather
problematic, since they
execute synchronously, which can block the
activity
and trigger the dreaded application not
responding exception.
[MUSIC]
Android's frameworks and applications of
these frameworks are designed,
implemented, and integrated in accordance
with many POSA and Gang of Four patterns.
We summarized key patterns using its
concurrency frameworks in an earlier
video.
We now summarize key patterns using
its communication and service frameworks,
focusing first
on a pattern Android uses to launch both
started or bound service on demand.
In particular the activator pattern
automates the
scalable, on-demand activation and
deactivation of service execution
context to run services accessed by
multiple
clients without consuming resources
unnecessarily as shown here.
Android's activity manager service applies
this
pattern to launch started and bound
services
in response to clients that invoke the
start service and bind service methods,
respectively.
In addition to launching services, the
activity manager service also applies the
activator pattern to launch other Android
components, such as activities and
broadcast receivers on demand as shown in
the code at this
path name.
Android applies a set of patterns that
guide the design
of its mechanisms for passing messages
between activities and started services.
In particular, the command processor
pattern packages a piece of application
functionality as well as its
parameterization in an object, to execute
it in another context, such as a later
point in time,
in a different process or in a different
thread, as covered here.
Android applies this pattern in its
intense service
framework which processes asynchronous
commands, expresses intents in
a background thread so they don't block
the
main thread as shown in this earlier
video.
The active object pattern defines the
units of
concurrency on a component to be requests
for service.
These service requests are processed in a
different thread then
the client threat that invoked the
request, as covered here.
Android applies this pattern via its
messenger mechanism which
it generalizes the hammer frameworks to
send message and
handle message methods to communicate
between activities and services
even across process boundaries, as shown
in this upcoming video.
When these message-passing mechanisms are
used to communicate between activities and
services, running and different processes,
they're
implemented internally using Android's
binder framework.
[MUSIC]
Android applies the command processor and
active
object patterns discussed in the previous
segment
to guide the design of its mechanisms
that pass messages between activities and
started services.
It applies a different set of mechanisms
and
patterns to enable communication between
activities and bound services.
In particular, the Broker pattern connects
clients with
objects in a separate process by mediating
invocations from
clients to these objects while
encapsulating the details
that the underlying interprocess
communication mechanisms, as covered here.
Android applies this pattern to support
method calls between activities and bound
services
running in the same or in different
processes, as shown in this upcoming
video.
Broker is actually a pattern language that
applies
many other Gang of Four and POSA patterns.
One pattern in the Broker pattern language
is the proxy pattern, which provides a
circuit or place holder for another object
to control access to it, as covered here.
Android's binder framework uses this
pattern to guide the implementation of
the stub code generated by the Android
Interface Definition Language compiler.
When parameters are passed from an
activity
to a service and back across process
boundaries, these stubs automate
martialing and demartialing,
which decomposes parameter objects passed
to the methods
into primitive data that the operating
system
can understand and then recomposes the
data into
objects on the receiver, as discussed at
this link and shown in an upcoming video.
We explore these patterns and their
application to Android
in more detail in a later section of this
MOOC.
[MUSIC]
In summary, Android provides a range of
mechanisms that enable activities
and services to communicate within the
same process or across different
processes.
This part of the module summarized
mechanism for passing
intent commands and messages between
activities and services, as
well as invoking method calls
synchronously or asynchronously between
activities and services using the Android
Interface Definition Language.
When activities and services reside in
different processes, these
mechanisms use the Android Binder
framework to communicate efficiently.
These communication mechanisms also apply
various Gang of Four and POSA patterns.
For example, programs based on the intent
service
apply the command processor pattern,
programs based on messengers
apply the active object pattern, and
programs based on
the Android Interface Definition Language
apply the Broker pattern.
Passing intent command via startService or
bindService is an
easy way to communicate from an activity
to a service,
though this approach is limited, since it
doesn't enable the
service to pass an intent reply back to
the activity.
When such two-way communication between
activities and services is
needed, Android Messengers are easy to use
for simple interactions,
since there's no need to define a separate
Android
Interface Definition Language interface,
extend stubs and override hook methods.
Messengers are often used to send replies
to a
started service back to an activity that
initiated it.
However, messengers are harder to use when
applications perform more sophisticated
communication interactions involving
complex data types,
especially when messages cross process
boundaries.
In these cases invoking methods via the
stubs generated by the
Android Interface Definition Language
compiler is
often more efficient and effective, since
these generated stubs automatically
perform marshaling,
and demarshaling, and shield application
programmers
from tedious and error prone details
of passing messages across process
boundaries.
However, the explicit use of the Android
Interface Definition Language cause
services to process method calls
concurrently in a pool of Threads.
So objects referenced by these Threads
must be
protected from raised conditions by the
appropriate synchronizers.
In contrast, messengers don't require any
particular concurrency model.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC]