[MUSIC]
Another mistake that developers make
sometimes, is that they will actually
go and store data to this private region,
on their device's data directory.
But, they'll go and store it in a way with
permissions that allow it to be accessed
by other applications.
So by default, when you store data to
an app's private data directory, it's
associated with the
user account of your app, and set to
a permission that prevents other apps from
accessing it.
But you as the developer have the ability
to override those permissions,
and make it so that even though you save
it to your private data directory.
You give permissions to that file that
allow other apps
to go and access it within your private
data directory.
So, in this code example here that we're
looking at, we're
actually opening a file and saving it to
our private data directory.
But we're saving it with mode world
readable.
And what this means is, is that any other
app on the device can
actually get access to that file, even
though it's stored in our data directory.
And you may think, well, this would never
happen, I would never do this.
Skype actually had a bug where incorrect
permissions were
being set on the SQLite database that they
were using.
And you can go and look at the details of
this bug.
But it exposed data and important settings
from that app to other apps on a device.
Now, here we see.
The actual, case where they're taking this
output stream, that's been created.
And it's been created world readable, and
then writing the secret,
to the output stream and saving this data,
to the disk, incorrectly.
So, if we look at the overall chain of,
of events that took place from the
developer's code.
That allowed this vulnerability to occur
is we start with a
secret setting, so some data that we don't
really want exposed.
We then unfortunately begin saving it by
opening it
in a output stream to a world readable
file.
And then we actually write that data to
that world readable file.
And so anytime like when we see
external storage directory, we see mode
world readable.
We need to really think about, do we plan
on
having this data accessed by any other app
on the device?
Do we really want that?
And if the answer is no, we don't want
that data
accessed by any other data or any other
app on the device.
That that data isn't always something that
should be public, then
we need to go and re-think how we're
saving that data.
The way that we really should have been
implementing this save settings
mechanism, if we wanted to keep those
settings private to that app.
We should have used mode private.
Which tells Android that that data is
private
to your application and should not be
shared.
So in this case, we actually are saving
settings to the
device in a way that other apps can't get
access to.
If we see mode private, we should assume
that that data that
we're storing to that location will not be
accessed by other apps.
But what we do need to remember, is
that just because data can't be accessed
by other
apps on the device, doesn't mean that it
can't be accessed by other users on the
device.
Just because we're saving data that is not
accessible to other apps on the device,
doesn't
mean that the owner or whoever has
physical
access to the device can't see that data.
And this unfortunately is a, a mistake
that developers commonly make as we've
discussed.
Is they assume that something that is
stored by their app that isn't
visible to other apps is also not visible
to whoever physically has the device.
And that's not actually the case.
If you are holding a device, there are
lots of attacks and ways
that you can, for example, route the
device and plug it into your computer.
And look at an app's private data.
So you shouldn't take anything that is
your private data and store it
in your app or on the devices of your
users.
If you give your app access to your own
private developer
data, you're then distributing that data
to all of your users.
And essentially saying, I want all of the
users of my
app that I wrote to have access to my
private developer data.
Anything that you put into your app or
give it at runtime, the
user of that app or the holder of that
device potentially has access to.
So in this case, for example, doing
something that's very commonly
done, and Amazon actually scans for now in
GitHub and other locations.
Like storing your Amazon web services
private key in your app or storing
it on the disk of a device that your app
is installed on.
Even if you go and download that key after
installation and store it, you're
still exposing that private developer data
to all of the users of your app.
So, you don't need to take data that
belongs to you
and is private to you and every give it to
your app.
Or store it on a device that your app
is installed on, even privately, and
assume that it's safe.