[MUSIC].
One of the important properties or design
principles
that we can use when we're trying to
build abstractions that help us improve
the security
of our applications and prevent us from
making mistakes.
Is to ensure that we don't tightly couple
our data to our security state.
Now what do I mean by data?
Well, I'm talking about the things that
our application
is doing as part of its normal function
that,
let's say that we remove security for the
moment
and we just needed to make decisions about
the data.
The things like the values that the user
is inputting into our user interface.
I'm talking about the temporary variables
that
we're creating that are based on that
data.
The data that we use to do calculations
and methods
or the key names that we decide to store
data with.
We want to separate those from the
variables and the flags and the other
things that we're using to indicate how to
securely process that data.
So if we take that, that principle and we
look at this code base that we've
just looked at, what we see is, there's
a problem here where we're violating this
principle.
And that is, we're coupling the security
state of
the application to the data state of the
application.
And that is this key that we're creating,
and passing
into the store data method is serving two
purposes simultaneously.
It's serving the purpose of deciding how
we
associate and store that data on disk, and
the
security decisions that are made with
respect to where
that data gets saved and how it gets
saved.
So we're simultaneously coupling this key
to both the security
state of the application and the data
state of the application.
So we have a simultaneous meaning for our
key that's causing problems.
If we go and we change our key, as
we just saw, it can unfortunately change
our security settings.
So, if we make a mistake in the key, we
will suddenly be making a mistake in our
security settings.
And what's also problematic is, we've got
a key
and a set of code that's being used to
decide
security settings from the key's value,
that's very hard
to test and prove from a security
standpoint, is correct.
So if we look at this code, it's not
immediately obvious if the code is always
going to work.
And if we hadn't happened to find the
right test case, to show that this
test, that this, this code doesn't always
work, we might assume that it was okay.
So by coupling our security and our data
state, we're not only having the ability
that our data can change our security in a
way that we don't want to happen.
But we're also making this much harder to
test and prove.
The other problem with coupling the data
and the security state is, if the key
was something, for example that was
provided or
potentially interacted with data from the
user interface.
Or from an intent or some other
application,
then we could pretend, end up in a
situation where an outside attacker can
inject or
easily manipulate the security state of
our application.
For example, by somehow manipulating the
keys so
that we save secure state in an insecure
way.
And these are the types of flaws that
attackers discover every day.
They discover things that the developer
didn't
think through that expose the application
to attack.
So how would we actually improve this
specific code example?
Well, the first thing we would want to do
is separate this data state and the
security state.
And we can do that fairly easily by
introducing a new method parameter that is
secure.
That is, we want to have the security
state in a separate variable that
is not tied to the data state, the key in
the value that we're saving.
So, by separating these out, we're helping
to prevent the ability for other
people to attack, and to have some of
these issues we just looked at.
And it's definitely an improvement, but if
we look
at this code, is this the best we can do?
And I think the answer is no, this is not
the best we can do.
We can still do better than this.
Yes, we can apply decoupling to improve
the application by separating the
security in the data state, but this alone
doesn't get us a more secure abstraction.
Its gets a, a possibly more secure
abstraction.
But we still have some other issues.