[MUSIC]
We've done a lot to improve the security
of this code, and to improve the
readability of our abstraction so that
developers
can use it in a way that's secure.
But there's still more that we could do
to make our abstraction a little better
designed.
And this is actually an important issue
that we want to address.
One of the problems that we have is that
our current state of our
code is set such that its behavior is
insecure by default.
Now what do I mean by that?
Well, this, Boolean that we are passing
in,
to determine if something is stored
securely or insecurely.
Well, by default, it's going to be
insecure.
Now the reason for this is, is let's say
that we have a class that defines our
security settings.
And we'll just call this settings.
And then, we create a Boolean variable
within this class.
It's a member variable and we call it,
secure.
The problem is, is that by default, if we
do nothing, and if we don't
initialize a value for secure when we
declare it, it's going to be false.
And, and this is not what we want in our
code.
We want the default state for our code to
be secure.
So, what we need to do when we design our
code
is try to ensure that if the developer or
the user or
caller or whoever it is of our code does
absolutely nothing to change
its behavior, then by default it will do
something securely.
If the person, or the caller or the
interface user uses our code and
wants to use it insecurely, they have to
go out of their way to do that.
We want to build abstractions and
interfaces that
are hard to do the wrong thing with.
And that's not what we have right now with
our current setup.
If somebody is using our code and they
call stored
data by default is secure is going to be
false.
Because Java Booleans, by default if
nothing else, is provided
when they are initialized, they're
going to be initialized to false.
So by default this code is going to
execute the ELSE branch.
Unless someone tells us that the code, the
data needs to be stored
securely, we're going to assume it
doesn't,
and we're not going to store it securely.
And this is not how we wannna build our
abstractions.
What we want to do is we want to build our
abstractions so that it's hard to use them
incorrectly.
That the low energy, low effort way of
using
our code, is to use it correctly and
securely.
The high effort, high energy way of using
our code, is to use it insecurely.
And what that does, is it makes it so
that,
we can rely on the fact that developers
are lazy.
That, code typically does not try to be
more complex than it needs to be.
Well, not necessarily, at least.
To ensure that our interface, normally,
when it's used, is going to be easier to
use in a secure way, and less likely
to have errors introduced from a security
perspective.
So how could we improve the security of
our code in this case?
Well, a better design for our abstraction
would be to change the Boolean variable
so that the Boolean variable indicates if
the user wants the data to be public.
So that by default, this conditional logic
is predicated
on whether or not the div, data should be
public.
And if the data is not explicitly flagged
to be
public, then it's stored privately, using
encryption or other means.
And if we take this approach suddenly our
conditional
logic is a lot more robust, and our
interface
is a lot more robust, it's going to be
hard
for developers to take this and mess it
up.
Or, at least, harder than it was before.
Because, now, the default state is to be
secure unless somebody tells us not to be.
But, although this code is good, is this
as good as we can get it?
Can we make it any better?
Hopefully you can see some ways that we
could possibly improve
on this code from the state that we've
already got in it.
What could we refactor to improve it even
more?
Well, one issue with this approach to
passing the Boolean value in,
is that it doesn't make it immediately
obvious to a reader of our code
whether or not a particular statement to
store data is secure or not.
If somebody looks at this code they have
to actually understand how that Boolean
value is used in order to determine if the
data is being stored securely or not.
And if that person that's looking at that
code has never encountered our interface
or our method calls before, the only way
that they're going to be able to know if
this is a secure way of using this data
storage system is by actually digging
into the data storage system's code and
looking
at how the different Boolean values are
used.
And you can imagine also sometimes in
compiled code, the actual
naming of the variables through
obfuscation
or other things, can be changed.
So we want to make it really obvious to
people reading the code.
Even if they don't have the code available
to them, on how the actual implementation
works, that
what they are seeing is a secure storage
of data, or secure use of that code base.
And right now we've simply got Boolean
values.
The other thing is, because there are
Boolean values and
the way they are being used, it could be
misinterpreted.
And you could look at this code and say,
you know what?
They're passing in false.
That means they are not storing the data
securely.
Because someone could assume that a true
value is
what you use to indicate something secure
versus insecure.
So our naming, here, of our interface
isn't very helpful to
users who are trying to audit this code or
understand its security.
So, how can we fix this?
Well, one simple approach to improving the
readability of our code and the clarity
of our interface is to incorporate a enum
to represent the security level.
Now you could do all kinds of things for
this enum.
We're going to come up with a very simple
example of
having two security levels, of either no
security or max security.
In reality you would probably maybe want
something
like encrypted and private, or
non-encrypted and private.
But, the key point here is is that
introducing
this enum allows us to have much more
readable code.
If we see down below, where we're
originally passing in a Boolean
that just said true or false, which didn't
really tell us much.
You know, is this code secure, is it not
secure?
I can't tell from true or false, or it's
not immediately apparent.
I have to dig down into the code.
If we look at this code, we see store
data.
We see some data in a key that's
being stored, and then we see security
level max.
It's much more apparent what the intent of
this code is.
It's much more apparent that the developer
is intending to store this data securely.
And for people who are reading our code,
other developers who are part of
our software engineering team, it makes it
more readily apparent what your code is
doing.
They don't have to worry as much about
digging deep into the details.
And also from the standpoint of code and
security auditing, we always want to put
less mental effort on our security
auditors
to make sure we're doing the right thing.
We want to make sure that our other
developers don't have
to think too hard about whether or not
something is secure.
They can look at it and tell immediately.
So if somebody's looking at this code,
they can very easily see,
I have some data and it's clearly being
intended to be stored securely.
And then they can make the decision on
whether or
not that data should or should not be
stored securely.
Similarly, the data that's being stored
publicly, they can look and that
data and they can see that the security
level is set to none.
And they can then say, am I okay that
there
is no security associated with this other
data that's being stored?
One other important property of this code,
is although we have switched to
this enum approach to representing the
security level, we still haven't
changed our code, so that it, it still
defaults to a secure behavior.
So no matter what, the default branch of
this conditional logic is to store things
securely.
Unless somebody explicitly tells us that
they want to store something
insecurely or publicly, we try to default
to storing things securely.
So we're maintaining that ability to have
a default of securing
our data, or a default of secure behavior
for our application.