[MUSIC]
Now some of you may think, why are we
going to all of this trouble to use an
enum?
Why don't we use something simpler like a
series of integer
flags to represent the security levels in
the application?
Well, is this really the right thing?
Can anybody see a potential issue if we
take this
approach to using simple integer flags to
representing our security levels?
What could be the problems with this
approach?
Well, one of the first things we realize
is that we are expanding the
bounds of the possible values that our
security level variable can take.
So suddenly, rather than having security
levels that are really
discrete and from a finite set of values
from an enum.
We have an unbounded, essentially, series
of values that are
only bounded by the minimum, maximum
integer values in Java.
And that's a huge number of different
values.
So, that immediately adds complexity to
our code.
Particularly from a testing standpoint.
If we want to know that this code does the
correct thing at all times,
we have to build code that suddenly tests
all of these different integer values.
Maybe not every single one of them, but
important boundary
conditions for sure, and ensure that our
code is operating properly.
Now, do we really need all of those
different integer values
to represent all of the different levels
of security in our application?
Probably not.
It's really unlikely that we actually need
the full range of integers, and that we
really have that fine of a grain, you
know, set of security levels in our
application.
So you can image this adds significant
testing complexity.
A simple code it doesn't really matter if
I use this integer value.
It's not really going to affect my testing
that much.
I can look at this code and I can
very easily decide which are the important
boundaries to test.
And therefore, it's not a big deal if
we used an integer to represent our
security level.
Now, in this specific case, if this code
never changed and if you
were the only developer working on it,
maybe that would be the case.
But the reality of the software
engineering world is, we work in teams.
We work with other developers, and it's
almost impossible to avoid the situation
that developers end up stepping on each
other's toes or using each other's code.
Are modifying each others code in ways
that the other developers didn't expect.
And so we have to be able to guard against
that by effective testing
and by effective testing so that we
can refactor our code and continually
improve it.
And, what would happen if a developer
comes along and decides that
they want to refactor our code and add a
new security level?
Or suddenly change the conditional logic
so that it checks if
the security level is high enough to add
encryption or not?
And suddenly we might introduce a subtle
bug
where we're incorrectly checking the
condition on that integer.
And suddenly our security level is not
causing the data
to be stored securely anymore, even though
it was before.
So without effective testing of a range of
values, and
continually updating our test cases to
account for all of these
different integer value ranges, and each
time we add some significant
value we have to test around the
boundaries of that integer.
So it, it, it adds significant complexity
to our code if we have
these unbounded integers that we are
trying to use for a security level.
So we want to try to have representations
of our
security state that are bounded and easier
to reason about.
Another issue that we have to think about
is what happens when
somebody misinterprets the usage of an
integer for a security level
and provides a value that we haven't
defined a security level for?
In this code, all we've got is a max
security level and then no security.
But, the actual security variable itself
could be any integer.
So what happens if somebody provides us a
random integer?
What if they provide us 43 or 17?
What does that mean?
Or in this particular case, what if the
person thinks
that, well, I'm going to write even more
secure code.
So, I'm going to take the most secure,
highest security
level that you've currently got, and I'm
going to increment it.
I'm going to make it one level greater of
security.
Well, what does that mean to us?
And we've, all of a sudden introduced,
complexity, the
potential for people to misunderstand how
our system works.
And the possibility of dealing with values
that we didn't
intend to be provided to us from a
security level perspective.
So we want to be careful that we bound our
security
level state and be able to reason about it
easily.
And also, by bounding it we make it easier
for other users to comprehend the
appropriate way to
use that state and how to express what
they
want done and how securely they want it
done.
The other issue with this integer approach
is it doesn't enforce any
type of type constraint, and that causes a
couple of problems for us.
One of them is.
Secondly, we would like to enforce some
level of
separation between the security state and
the data state.
We would like to make it hard to mix the
two together
and to set security state from some
computation on the data state.
But, with the current approach in this
code, I can do something odd like, I can
assign the security level to the number of
groups, or the size of the private groups.
So, maybe my thought process if I'm
another
developer is, well, the bigger the group
the more
I need to secure it because the more
damage could be done if those names got
out.
And if there's absolutely no one in the
group well, then that's fine.
That means that we have a security level
of zero because there's no point
in securing it because who cares if that
gets out, because there's no data there.
And the more people in the group, the more
data is been exposed to the higher the
security level.
So somebody could simply take what you're
doing and misinterpret it, and then
begin calculating some security level
based on their data state.
And that's not really what we want them to
do.
So, in this example down here, suddenly
they're setting the
security level equal to the size of the
private groups.
Which is clearly not something that you
intended for user of your interface to do.
So if we were smarter about how we
designed
our abstraction, we could add some typing
to our security
levels, to insure that we can enforce some
levels
of separation between the security state
and the data state.
Or at least make it harder to mix and
match the two directly.
So, if we go back and look at our enum
approach
again, we get a number of important
benefits from this approach.
The first benefit is that our, our
security state is clearly bounded.
We only have two specific values that we
have to worry about.
Security level max and none.
There is no in between and there's no
possibility to assign a value that's in
between.
And this is really important because it
helps us to prevent the
errors that we saw of people misusing our
interface to security.
And it also is very important from a
testability standpoint.
It's much easier with this enum approach
to figure
out what are all the important values to
test.
And then to go and build test cases
that ensure that those test cases
guarantee that
the security is upheld for each of the
values that we care about in that enum.
Another important aspect of this enum
approach is that it takes
many of these errors that we saw, that
resulted from misuse or
misinterpretation of our security level
and how we interpret
that, that, that type and push them into
compile time errors.
So if another developer is misusing our
interface, as many of the common ways
that it might be misused could be caught
at compile time as compile time errors.
So, for example, if we look at the
first line, they're trying to assign an
arbitrary
value, for which we don't have a
definition
of what that means in our security model.
Three.
What does three mean?
We haven't defined that value.
Well now, it's a compile error.
Because if they assign three, three is an
integer and our
security level is an enum, and you can't,
those things aren't compatible.
So that would be flagged at compile time
as a misuse of that particular interface.
So we've taken something that would have
been a
run time error and caused sort of
undefined behavior.
And we pushed it to the compile time error
to prevent a security problem.
If we look at the second line, there were
mixing our security state and our data
state together.
They were trying to assign a security
level
based on the size of the private groups.
So, suddenly, we can push this to a
compile time error as well.
Because directly assigning the security
level from
the groups and the size of the groups
is not possible because private groups
that
size does not give you a security level.
It gives you an integer.
Again a compile error because it can't be
assigned to the security level.
So we can help prevent people from mixing
security and data state.
Unless security state is somehow that
type,
security level is somehow represented in
the
data state, it's unlikely that they'll be
able to easily mix and match the two.
Of if the do, they'll be very aware of
what they're doing.
If we look at the third line, we
can deal with the misinterpretation of the
paranoid user
who tries to increment the security level
above our
maximum, because they're even more secure
than everybody else.
And again, this is being caught and
flagged and turned into a compile time
error.
So, by changing the design of our
interface and
using this enum, rather than an integer,
we're getting
a number of benefits from the ability to
catch
errors and how other developers are using
our code.
And also from a testability standpoint in
our ability
to maintain that code and ensure that it
stays secure.
Particularly in a group software
engineering environment where
other developers are modifying the code as
well.
So, is this as good as we can get this
interface?
Can we make these abstractions any better
than they already are?
Well, I think that we can.
There's still more that we can do to
improve
these abstractions that we've built to
store data securely.