[MUSIC]
Now a lot of you are probably saying to
yourselves,
I would never make such obvious mistakes
in my code.
I would never go and take a user's
password.
And store it to the external storage on an
Android device.
And probably most of you wouldn't if the
code was just that simple.
But in the real world, most of the code
bases that we work
with are a lot more sophisticated than the
ones that we've been looking at.
The examples that we've seen so far of
leaking private data are purposely
simplified code examples that help us to
illustrate the specific properties
that cause code to leak data on the
external storage, or by
having the wrong permissions, or by
inserting developer data inside of it.
But, in the real code basis that we work
with they're much more
sophisticated, and so it's not quite as
straightforward to see these types of
errors.
So what we're going to look at now is what
makes it hard to write
applications that don't necessarily adhere
to all
of the security practices we've just
talked about.
And the approaches that we can use to help
improve how we
write our code so that it's much more
obvious when we're making
mistakes, and much easier to ensure that
we don't make mistakes and
that other developers don't make mistakes
in how they use our code.
The key thing that we're going to see is
that when we
write apps, we typically don't write a
simple app, but we
write an app that's built on a series of
abstractions, that
get ever more, high level as we go up the
stack.
And our app is built on top of these
abstractions, and if we're not
careful about how we build these
abstractions and how we use them, we
will end up in situations where it's very
hard to see how an action appear
causes leakage of data out the bottom end
of the set of abstractions.
And so what the goal, of, these, tips that
we're going to talk about in a
minute, are, is to ensure that when we
build abstractions into our code, that we
don't
build abstractions that make it hard to do
the right thing, but instead we build
abstractions
and interfaces that make it easy for
developers
to do the right thing with our code.
And make it easy for developers to see
that code
written with our abstractions are doing
things properly and securely.