[BLANK_AUDIO]
Welcome to the next part of the
module on Android services and the local
inter-process
communication mechanisms, which focuses on
service to
activity communication via the Android
messenger communication mechanism.
In this part, we'll first explain
how the messenger generalizes the hamMeR
concurrency
framework's send message and handle
message mechanisms
to work across component and process
boundaries.
We'll also show how an Android messenger
object can
be used by the download service to
communicate the path
name to the retrieved image back to the
download
activity, so the image can be displayed to
the user.
We'll focus on using Messengers to send
reply messages from started services
to activities, though they can also be
used to communicate with bound services.
A Messenger is a proxy that encapsulates
access to a Handler
in a Component, such as an activity or
service shown here.
A reference to a Messenger can be passed
to one or more
components via some communication
mechanism, such as an extra to an intent.
The receiver generally does three things.
First, it obtains the Messenger.
For example, by extracting it as an extra
from the intent.
Second, it performs some processing, such
as retrieving an image from
a remote server and storing it in the file
on the device.
Third, it uses the reference to the
Messenger to send a reply back to the
handler in the activity, even if the
handler
resides in a different process than the
service.
For example, the download service sends
the path name
for the image file back to the download
activity.
The message sent by the receiver is
ultimately
dispatched to the handler's handle message
hook method.
For example, the download activity will
use the path name return
by the download service to display the
image to the user.
[SOUND] We'll now start delving deeper
into how a Messenger can be used
to complete the download application,
shown in earlier videos.
There are multiple classes, objects and
processes involved in this application.
So we'll analyze it from several
perspectives.
We'll begin by giving an overview and a
recap of the steps performed by the
download activity and download service,
focusing on the
implementation of the service handler and
download handler.
The service handler's download image and
reply method runs in a background thread
and sends the path name to the retrieved
image file back to the DownloadActivity.
The handler message hook method of the
DownloadHandler and DownloadActivity
uses this path name to display the image
to the user.
The DownloadActivity performs several
steps.
It first creates the DownloadHandler and
then creates
a Messenger that encapsulates a reference
to the handler.
DownloadActivity next creates an intent
sed to start the download service.
The Messenger is passed as an extra to the
intent, which
also stores the URL for the desired image
to download as data.
Finally, DownloadActivity calls start
service.
Passing the intent command as a parameter.
This configuration of the download
application runs
the download service in a separate
process.
So the Android activity manager service
launches the service, if it's
not already running, and sends the intent
across the process boundary.
At this point, control shifts to the
download service, which also performs
several steps.
It creates a handler thread and a service
handler
and queues the intent in the service
handler's message que.
The handler's thread then uses the
underlying
Android looper to deque the intent and
dispatch
the service handler's handle message hook
method, which
calls download image and reply to retrieve
the
image, store it in a local file on the
device and return the path name
of the file to the DownloadActivity by
sending
a message, via the Messenger past the
intent.
This message crosses the process boundary
back to the DownloadActivity,
where it's dispatched to the reply
handlers handle message hook method.
This method displays the image to the
user.
[MUSIC]
Now that we've given an overview of the
steps
performed by the DownloadActivity and
download service, we'll analyze
the source code, focusing on the methods
in download
handler and service handler that weren't
covered in earlier videos.
All this source code is available at this
URL, which I
encourage you to download and review as
you watch this video.
We'll start by recapping key portions of
the DownloadActivity, which creates
an instance of download handler that
processes replies from the download
service.
The download image method dispatch in
response to a button click from
the user, calls the make intent factory
method, defined in download service.
This method localizes the logic for making
the right intent.
In particular, it creates a new Messenger
that
encapsulates a reference to the download
handler and
adds a reference to the Messenger as an
extra to the intent under the name
Messenger.
The intent returned from make intent is
then
passed to the start service method, which
runs
the download service in a separate
process, which
is launched if it hasn't been started yet.
[MUSIC]
This analysis of download service focuses
on its download image and
reply method, which retrieves the
designated image, copies it into a local
file, extracts the Messenger stored as an
extra in the intent and
passes the Messenger and path name to the
send path helper method.
This method then calls the make reply
message factor method to create
a message that encapsulates the path name
for the downloaded image file.
In addition to storing whether the
download succeeded or failed into
the message, make reply message also
stores the path name in a
bundle, which is an object that map string
values to parsable types
and can be used to pass data across
processes as shown here.
The message returned for the make reply
message factory method is then passed back
to
the download activity as a parameter to
the send method provided by the
Messenger's reference.
The Android binder framework collaborates
with the hamMeR concurrency
framework to dispatch this reply message
as a parameter to
the download handlers handle message hook
method in the user
interface thread of the process where the
download activity resides.
This method extracts the bundle from the
message
and uses it to obtain the encapsulated
file name.
A check is then made to see if the
download succeeded.
If it did, the image file is decoded, and
the resulting
image is displayed in the context of the
user interface thread.
Note how the use of started services,
intents,
Messengers and handlers enables the
DownloadActivity to retrieve and
display an image without performing any
long duration
operations, that would block the user
interface threads synchronously.
[MUSIC]
In summary, Messengers provide a flexible
framework for itra-
and inter-process communication between
activities and services in Android.
We showed how to download application uses
a Messenger to communicate
a path name from the download service back
to the DownloadActivity.
This design is consistent with the common
idiom used throughout Android,
where an activity first creates a reply
handler, next creates a
Messenger that encapsulates a reference to
that handler and then passes
the Messenger to a started service as an
extra to an intent.
When the service receives the intent, it
extracts the
Messenger and uses it later to send a
reply
message back to the activity, where the
message is
delivered to the reply handler's handle
message hook method.
Although we focused on how a started
service can use
a Messenger to reply back to an activity,
it's also
possible for a bound service to create a
Messenger that
a client activity can use to pass messages
to it.
In this variant, the bound service creates
a Messenger that encapsulates a handler.
It then returns a reference to that
Messenger via
the services on bind factory method, which
is invoked automatically
by the Android service framework when an
activity calls bind
service with an intent that's associated
with that bound service.
Regardless of where the Messengers are
used
for activity to service communication,
service to
activity communication or communication
with bound or
started services, they implement a variant
of the
active object pattern, which defines the
units
of concurrency in a component to the
request
for service, which in this case are
the send methods calls on a Messenger
reference.
This pattern allows the service request to
be handled in a different thread or
process than the client thread that
invoked
the request, as discussed in upcoming
videos.
Messengers are best suited for relatively
simple interactions between
activities and services that pass
relatively simple data types.
When applications perform more
sophisticated interactions that involve
more
complex data types, it may be more
appropriate to
use the communication mechanisms based on
the Android Interface
Definition of Language, which we'll
discuss later in this module.
[BLANK_AUDIO]