[MUSIC]
So, how do we avoid situations like the
one we just saw where the complexity
of the code base made it difficult for us
to see that a mistake was being made.
Well there are a couple properties that we
want to make sure that when we write
abstractions that they, that our
abstractions possess
to ensure that we use those extractions
properly.
And we don't create security issues.
So if we think of our application as
relying on a layered set of abstractions.
There are a number of principles that we
want those abstractions to have.
One of them is, we want to have clarity
with respect to security.
We don't want to be able to look at our
abstractions and
not be able to obviously see how that
abstraction is impacting security.
We want to make security and our security
decisions as much as possible a compile
time decision, so if
somebody's making a mistake with their
security, we want to
be able to catch that as a compile error.
So we want to catch flaws.
As secure at compile time.
So if somebody makes a security flaw in
the
code, we would like that to show up at
compile
time, not when the app is deployed and
people
are using it and it's causing data to be
exposed.
We also want to make sure that when other
people use
our code, that it's obvious how to
properly use our code.
So we want the proper usage to be obvious.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then, finally, one other important
property that we
want is we want to be able to audit our
code, and ensure that we
don't mix our data and our security model
together, in a way
that exposes our security model to attacks
from outside.
So, we don't want to make sure, that we
don't build abstractions where it's
easy for people to go and inject data that
changes our security's decisions.
Or changes our security state so that they
can get us to do something insecure.
So we want to separate and protect, our
security state.
And what we'll see is that on Android,
there's a lot of things that we can
do that really make building abstractions
and interfaces
that have these properties, much easier to
do.