[MUSIC]
Welcome to the next part of the module on
Android Services &
Security, which continues our analysis of
how to program a started service.
Now that we have examined the design of
the download application, we'll delve
deeper into its implementation.
We'll start by analyzing the download
activity,
which contains an instance of a download
handler
that receives the path name of the
file containing the image retrieved by
download service.
The download activity extends activity and
displays a screen that prompts
the user for the URL of the desired image
to download.
After a user enters the URL into an edit
text window
and presses the download image button,
Android dispatches the download image
method.
Which gets the URL string entered by the
user and
calls the makeIntent factory method to
find the download service.
This factory method creates the
appropriate intent,
that contains the desired URL as intent
data.
Along with other information, used to
communicate from
the download service back to the download
activity.
The start service method is then called to
launch the download service, to handle
this intent.
After the service has successfully
downloaded the
image and stored it in a file on
the device, the path name is passed back
to the download activity via its download
handler.
Which is encapsulated by the Android
messenger inter-process
communication mechanism, which we'll
discuss in a later video.
[MUSIC]
We'll now analyze the download service
implementation, which contains an instance
of ServiceHandler
that runs in a background thread and
retrieves an image from a remote server.
Stores it in a file on the device and
returns
the path name of the file of the download
activity client.
DownloadService extends the Service
superclass and
overrides several of its hook methods.
It also defines a factory method called
makeIntent, that's called by the download
activity,
to make the right type of intent to pass
to the start service method.
This factory method creates an intent,
that's associated with the download
service class.
Adds the image URL as data for the intent,
and creates an instance of the messenger
inter-process communication mechanism.
Which encapsulates the download handler
and is added as an extra to the intent.
The download service later uses this
messenger to pass the path name back to
the download activity after it
successfully retrieves
the image, as discussed in an upcoming
video.
The download service class also defines
several data members.
The store looper and an instance of the
service handler.
These data members are defined as
volatile.
To ensure they're properly visible to the
background handler thread.
As discussed here.
The onCreate hook method is called when
the download
service is first launched by Android's
activity manager service.
It creates and then starts a handler
thread, which was covered in an earlier
video.
By default, a service runs in the user
interface thread,
which we don't want to block during the
image download process.
So the download service uses the handler
thread
to retrieve the image concurrently in the
background.
The onCreate hook method next gets the
HandlerThread's
looper and passes it to the constructor of
ServiceHandler.
So its handle message method will be
dispatched in the context of the handler
thread.
Which is a common idiom applied in various
Android
packaged applications as we'll show in an
upcoming video.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC]
The onStartCommand hook method is called
each time a started
service is sent an intent by the start
service method.
In the download service implementation,
onStartCommand invokes the
makeDownloadMessage factory method,
which creates a message that will be sent
to the service handler.
And used to retrieve an image based on
the contents of the intent encapsulated in
the message.
This factory method adds the intent to the
message to indicate which URL to retrieve.
It also adds the start ID to the message.
This parameter is passed by the Android
service framework to
onStartCommand and is used to indicate
which request is being stopped.
When the download completes, as discussed
shortly.
OnStartCommand then calls the service
handle'rs send message method.
Which uses the HaMeR framework to pass the
message to the service handler's handle
message hook method so it can be
processed concurrently in the background
handler thread.
The value return from onStartCommand
informs
the Android service framework not to
restart the download service
automatically, if
its process is killed while it's running.
The ServiceHandler class extends Handler,
and does the bulk of the work for
the download service, by concurrently
processing messages
passed to it, via the HaMeR framework.
The constructor of ServiceHandler gets the
handler thread's looper and assigns it to
be its looper, so it will
receive messages forwarded from
onStartCommand via sendMessage.
The handleMessage hook method runs in the
context of the handler thread.
It calls the downloadImageAndReply method
to retrieve an
image from a remove server, store it on a
file on the device, and send the path
name for the file back to the
DownloadActivity client.
Via the Android messenger inter-process
communication
mechanism as shown in an upcoming video.
[MUSIC]
Since the lifecycle of a service is
independent of
the component that launched it, the
Download Service must
be programmed to shut itself down or it
will
continue running the background
indefinitely and consuming system
resources.
After retrieving an image from a remote
server therefore.
The download service explicitly shuts
itself
down by calling the StopSelf method.
However, to ensure the download service
doesn't shut itself down until
all its current processing is complete, it
applies a common Android idiom.
For stopping service, that's covered here.
This idiom is used by services
that handle multiple start service
requests concurrently.
For example, in the download service, a
second
request may have arrived concurrently from
a client.
Via onStartCommand while the download
service was processing a first request
in the handle message method dispatched by
the service handler's thread.
The download service therefore can't shut
itself down when it's done
processing the first request since that
would terminate the second request
prematurely.
To avoid this problem, stopSelf has passed
the start id
of the request that was originally
delivered to the onStartCommand method.
And stored in the arg1 field of
the message created by the
makeDownloadMessage factor method.
In accordance with this idiom, if
DownloadService receives a new request via
onStartCommand before calling the stopSelf
method
and the ServiceHandler's handleMessage
hook method.
The startId will not match the last start
request and the
Android service framework will not stop
download service at that point.
Eventually the start ID will match the
last
start request and the download service
will be stopped.
At which point, the Android service
framework will invoke its onDestroy
hook method, which quits the looper and
shuts down the handler thread.
[MUSIC]
In summary.
This part of the module analyzed the
implementation of the download activity
and download service.
Which are used to retrieve images from
remote servers, store them
in files on the device, and display the
images to the user.
By default, a service uses the user
interface thread, and can
thus incur application not responding
errors if it blocks too long.
In particular, a service is not a thread,
and does not create a
run in a separate thread or process,
unless explicitly programmed to do so.
As discussed here.
Computer I/O intensive services therefore,
often
run in one or more background threads.
So, service implementations often focus on
defining classes
that leverage various Android service,
concurrency and communication mechanisms.
For example, the download service used
various classes from the android HaMeR
framework to process intents in a handler
thread and retrieve images concurrently.
Since writing these classes for each
service is tedious and error prone.
Android provides the intent service.
Which codifies concurrent internet
processing in a
reasonable framework that applies the
command processor pattern.
To handle asynchronous commands expressed
as intents in a
single background thread, as shown in the
next video.
[MUSIC]