[MUSIC]
Let's talk more in depth about this
analogy that apps
are people, and understand what that means
from a security perspective.
The first thing we can think about is,
what are the attacks?
If we assume that, that apps are people,
and
that's the analogy we're going to use for
security,
what are the attacks, or things that
people do
maliciously against each other, that we
want to protect against?
Well, the first thing that an app can do,
and maybe it's
common that people do unfortunately, is
they can lie to each other.
So, they can provide false information to
each other.
So, one app that's interacting with
another app or talking to it through
a IPC or intents, can lie and tell it
something that's not true.
So, as an app developer, we have to be
very concerned about checking
data or input validation of the things
that other apps are telling us.
Another thing that malware can do, since
it's a person
interacting with our app, is it can steal
from our app.
So, it can try to access information,
which is really the currency of apps.
It can try to access that information that
this app doesn't want exposed to the other
app.
And that information could help it to do
something malicious directly to this app.
Or it might be the information that that
app needs in order to attack somebody
else.
For example, to steal contacts from your
app so
that it can spam them and try to convince
them to install the app and also be
infected
so they can try to steal from each other.
Another thing that apps can do, which is
also sort of
a form of lying, but they can try to
manipulate each other.
By either lying, or more interestingly,
going and telling one of that app's
friends something that it would like that
app to know in order to manipulate it.
Because this app may trust another app,
more than it trusts the malware.
So, this malware doesn't necessarily have
to directly manipulate your app, it
may use another intermediary to manipulate
your app, another app that yours trusts.
So, you have to be concerned not only
about your own security,
but the security of the other apps that
you talk to and trust.
And, it can also go and manipulate the
user that's using
your app, by showing them a false GUI or
false information.
And trying to convince them to do
something to your app that, if
the user does it, you'll accept it but
another app couldn't necessarily do it.
So these are some interesting things, if
we use this
analogy of apps are people that we want to
protect against.
We don't want other apps to lie to us or
steal from us or manipulate from us.
Another thing we don't want to do, is we
don't want to have our app inadvertently
manipulated by another app into doing
something on
that other apps behalf that isn't a good
thing.
So, for example, if you told me to rob a
bank, hopefully I won't do it.
But if another app tells your app to go
and access the Internet, it's a similar
type of situation.
Maybe that original app doesn't have
access to the Internet.
It really wants access to the Internet and
it knows that your app does.
So maybe your app is the equivalent of the
bank manager that has access to the vault.
So if that malware, rather than directly
accessing the
vault, which it doesn't have access to,
can get
your app, which is the bank manager, to
access
that vault and give that information back
to the malware.
That's also just as good as getting access
to it itself.
So we have to protect our apps from being
manipulated by other apps through lying
or stealing or other means, in order to do
things bad on behalf of another app.
And we'll talk about specific types of
attacks that fall into this model of
lying and stealing and manipulation that
malware uses to attack good apps.