[MUSIC]
Now if all of our apps, were, wrapped up
and protected
by Android, to where they could never
interact and exchange data.
If they could never read each other's
saved state,
ever, we'd have much less interesting
applications on our devices.
Almost all of the really interesting
Android applications involve some type of
interaction between that app and another
app or set of services on the device.
Or with the data that they're storing
underneath their apps.
So for example, the Contacts app.
The Contacts app that's on Android by
default, stores its data and persists it.
And Android protects that save state of
your contacts.
But at the same time we want to be able to
get access to the contact list sometimes
from other apps.
So Android does provide mechanisms to
allow apps to share
data outside of the protected sandboxes
that Android provides for them.
So apps can both, share data outside of
the processes that they're running in, so
at
run time they can share data that they've
loaded and is running outside to other
apps.
And the Android apps can also, if they
want to, share
data that they persisted in the file
system to other apps.
Now, by default Android tries to protect
you.
It tries to keep your app within its own
little sandbox with its own
process, protecting the memory of that
app,
protecting the data its storing on the
disk.
But, it gives you the option to build
richer apps that do talk outside of their
sandbox.
But it's in these interactions where we
begin talking to
other apps and services on the device,
when we begin persisting
data in ways that other apps can read and
interact
with, that we run the danger of writing an
insecure app.
So, the two big areas that we have to be
careful of are, one,
that run time when we begin interacting
with and talking with other apps.
And typically the way that you do this on
Android is through, as you've seen,
inter-process communication, or IPC.
And IPC can take a number of forms, as
we've seen.
This can be the exchange of intents
between applications and services.
This can be binding, interacting with a
service, and
invoking a service that's running in
another app or process.
So, something like getting access to the
GPS.
That's not going to be running in your
apps process.
So all of these interactions through IPC,
whenever we decide to have those
interactions, we need to be cognizant that
we're exposing our app to another app.
We're opening up the sandbox that we live
in by default, and we're allowing our app
to interact with the memory of other apps,
and to interact with the memory of our
app.
So, whenever we begin doing interactions
through
intents, through services, or through
other mechanisms, we're
beginning to open up our app at run time
and open up those memory protections.
The other thing that we can do, is we can
save data to sort of communal areas on the
disc.
So we can do things like save data to the
SD card.
And in many cases, you want to save things
to the SD card.
So for example, if you have a custom
camera app
that you're writing, you probably want to
store those pictures on
the SD card so that the user can remove
the
SD card, put a new one in to store more
pictures.
And also so that other applications like
the Photo Gallery application can read
those photos.
So there are certain places, like the SD
card, when we store
data that we're opening our apps persisted
state up to other apps.
You can also store data with different
permissions.
So we can change the default permissions
when we store data.
Even they we're storing it in our apps'
own a little private data storage area on
the
device, we can still open up that data and
store it with things like, read from any
app.
And we can change those permissions.
So whenever we do those type of things, or
we store data in a
way that other apps can get access to it,
we have to be aware
of the possibility of another app coming
and either reading that information in
order to corrupt it, or to use that
information to attack our app in some way.
Or to trick it in some way.
The other area the Android can't protect
us
again, is if we have a graphical user
interface.
So we have a GUI that is a part of our
app.
Now, GUIs are great.
We can use a GUI to get information from
the user that we need, like their username
and password.
But GUIs are also areas where other apps
can try to attack our app.
Because a GUI is way of inputting data
into our app.
So although we have a process that's
protecting the memory around our app, any
type
of GUI is an area where we're allowing
data to be placed into our process.
Either through fields like username and
password that the user
is going to provide data, or by going in
adding buttons.
Which when they're clicked, they turn into
events that are injected into
the memory of our application and give
another app the chance to attack us.
Now, a GUI, another piece of
malware probably can't directly manipulate
your GUI.
But what it can do is, it can trick the
user into manipulating your GUI into a
state that it wants.
So it can trick the user and make it
think that it's doing something other than
it is.
So, it manipulates the user to convince
them that, it's logging into your
banking app when in reality it's providing
a fake GUI to do something else.
So the GUI is another area that we have to
protect.
We either have to protect it from taking
data that's
going into our memory and corrupting it in
some way.
Or getting knowledge of that data in some
way, such as user name and password.
Or, protect it from taking a GUI that's
supposed
to be putting data into our process and
our
memory space where it's protected, and
instead, extracting that
data and putting it into a piece of
malware.
So these are three really important areas
that we have to understand
what Android protects us against and what
it doesn't protect us against.
And what we as developers have to do to
make sure that we write more secure apps.
We want to make sure we protect our GUIs.
We want to make sure we protect the things
that
we store, in terms of state on the disk.
And we want to make sure that we protect
our
interactions with other apps through
inter-process communication or other
mechanisms.