[MUSIC]
Welcome to the next part of the module on
Android services and security.
Which begins our analysis of how to
program a started service.
In this part, we'll analyze key elements
of
the design of a Download Application and
show
by example how a Started Service can
concurrently
retrieve and display an image from a
remote server.
Before delving into the details of the
solution however.
We'll first outline the overall structure
and functionality of the download
application.
This application contains a download
activity.
When a user presses the Download Image
button, this activity launches a download
service
on demand by creating an intent command
and passing to the start service method.
After the download service is launched by
Android.
It uses a URL passed with the intent, to
concurrently retrieve
the image and store it in a file on the
device.
If all goes well, the download service
returns the path name of the file
containing
the image, back to the download activity,
which then displays the image to the user.
We'll just cover steps one and two in this
video.
Later videos, show how to return the path
name from the
service back to the activity,
using various Android interprocess
communication mechanisms.
The source code for the download
application is available at this link.
So download it, and watch this video and
the next
one carefully, perhaps multiple times, to
learn how it works.
This is the most complicated example
covered thus
far in this MOOC, since there are four
main components involved in the solution,
as well
as various Android service, concurrency,
and communication mechanisms.
So we'll progressively analyze the
design and implementation from various
perspectives.
To show how all the pieces fit together.
[MUSIC]
We'll now summarize the steps involved in
Programming Started Services.
Using our download application, as a
running example to re-efy each step.
In general, a client, typically an
activity launches a started
service by calling the start service
method as discussed here.
For example, the download activity uses a
factory method, to create an intent
command that identifies the service start,
which
in this case is the download service.
And supplies the URL parameter via intent
data, that tells
the service what image to retrieve from a
remote server.
The start service method, requests Android
activity manager service to start
the service asynchronously, so this call
doesn't block the clients service
synchronously.
While the DownloadService runs.
In response to the startService call,
Android's activity service will launch the
service if it's not already running, using
the activity pattern described here.
The activity manager service then invokes
a service's
onCreate and onStartCommand hook methods
to initialize the service.
In inherits these methods from the Service
superclass.
The DownloadServices onCreate hook method.
Starts a handler thread, which is used in
conjunction
with a service handler object to download
the requested
image in the background, store it in a
file,
and return the path name of the file to
the
client.
The onStartCommand hook method is called
each time a started service
is sent an intent, via a call to the
startService method.
The DownloadService implements
onStartCommand to send the intent
to the background handler thread for
concurrent processing.
OnStartCommand returns a value to the
android service framework.
But this value is not propagated back to
the client, that invoked the start service
method originally.
Instead, this return value tells Android
what it should do with
the service, if it's process is killed
while the service is running.
The valid return values are START_STICKY,
which
tells Android not to re-deliver the
intent.
To onStartCommand, when the service is
restarted.
Likewise, the Start_Not_Sticky return
value, tells android the service
should remain stopped, unless it's
explicitly started by some client code.
And finally, the start re-deliver intent
value tells Android to restart the service
via on start command supplying the same
intent as was delivered to it this time.
More information on these return values is
documented here.
A started service typically performs a
single operation, and doesn't
need to return or reply to the client that
started it.
And our download application example, the
download service defines a
download image reply method, that runs in
the background handler thread.
This method extracts the URL from the
intent.
Uses it to retrieve the image from a
remote
server, stores the image in a file on the
device,
and then returns the path name to the
image
to the download activity client, which
subsequently displays the image.
When a operation is done, the service can
be stopped.
For example, the download service called
Stop Self to shut
itself down when its done retrieving and
processing an image.
A service that stops itself, must be
careful that there aren't
current operations processing other
intents, as
we'll discuss later in this video.
A service can also be shut down by another
component.
For example, the Download Activity could
call the
stop service method, to unilaterally
terminate the Download Service.
[MUSIC]
Now that we've summarized the steps
involved in
programming started services in general,
and the Download
Service in particular, we'll examine the
design of
the Download Application, which contains a
Download Activity.
And the download service.
As outlined earlier, when the user presses
download image
button on the screen, the download
activity sends an Intent
to the URL to retrieve via call to
startService, which
launches the download service on demand
using the activator pattern.
The download service performs four main
actions.
First, it's on crate hook method.
Crate's the service handler, which extends
the android handler class.
The service handler is associated with a
single handler thread,
that runs in the background with it's own
threat specific looper.
And it can be used to send and handle
messages,
as discussed in the earlier video on the
hammer framework.
Second.
The download service itself, receives an
intent from the
download activity, via onStartCommand and
calls the service handler's
send it service message method, to insert
the intent
into the handler's thread message queue
for subsequent processing.
Third, the looper in the background
handler
thread dispatches the handler's handle
message hook method.
Which downloads the image designated by
the URL
in the intent and stores it in a file.
An upcoming video, will show how the
android messenger inner process
communication mechanism is used to pass
the path name of the file.
Back from the download service, to the
download activity.
Finally, the download service stops itself
when there are no more intents to handle.
This design is guided by the Command
Processor pattern,
which packages a piece of application
functionality and parameterises
it in an object so it could be executed
in a different thread or process as
described here.
The download service supplies this
pattern, to offload tasks
from applications main thread to a single
background thread.
Which works well if the service needn't
handle multiple requests concurrently.
[MUSIC]
In summary, this part of the module
progressively
analyzed the structure and functionality
of a download application.
To show by example, how to program a
started service.
It concurrently retrieves and displays an
image, from a remote server.
A started service is launched on demand by
another Android component, typically
an activity and it's lifecycle's
independent
of the component that launched it.
A start up service can therefore run in
the background indefinitely.
Even if the component that launched it, is
destroyed.
Started services are driven by a version
of control, from androids activity manager
service.
Which dispatches service like cycle hook
methods.
Such as uncreate, unstart command and
undestroy.
In response to various events, generated
by applications and the Android
infrastructure.
The next part of this video shows how
these
hook methods, can be implemented by
applying a common
Android idiom for concurrent service
processing, which is based
on the command processor pattern discussed
later in this MOOC.
[MUSIC]