[MUSIC]
So, one of the important things to
understand, when
building Android applications, is how to
write secure Android applications.
We've all seen stories in the news about
apps that didn't properly secure their
user's data, and allowed other apps to
read and write their private messages or
contacts.
And so what this series of lectures is
going to cover is, what are sort of the
basic things that you need to understand
about how Android security works?
And then based on your understanding of
what Android provides you from a
security perspective, how you can write
your app to improve its security.
So one of the first things to understand,
when
we're talking about Android security, is
how Android's version
of how applications, or apps operate, is
different than
from what we see on a traditional desktop
computing environment.
So in a traditional desktop and computing
environment, if
we launch an application, let's say it's a
photo editor.
And we'll say this is our first app that
we're launching, so this is app one.
And let's say that, that photo editor goes
and we open it and we decide that we
want to access the internet maybe to
download, send
images that we have stored, on Facebook or
Flickr.
And then after getting those images we go
and we edit
the images, and we save them to a storage
on the disk.
Now one of the important things about
the way that desktop environments work, is
that
they associate each app that you launch
with
a single person, that is your user
account.
If you launch an app, that app is
associated with your user account, and has
all of the permissions and capabilities
that
are part of whatever's in your user
account.
So, this app will be part of your user
And when you go and launch a second
application, this is where
this concept of each app running within
your user account becomes important.
So if we go and we launch a second
application, let's say that this is your
browser and you're going to view in a
web browser, exactly what that image looks
like.
So we'll launch our web browser.
This is our sec, second application.
One of the important things is, is that
this will also be running in our user
account.
And what that means is, is that this
application can go and directly
access those same areas of storage that
the first app can access.
And the reason is, that the privileges and
permissions
that are governing the web browser, which
is another app
that I, the user, have launched, are
exactly the
same as the privileges and permissions of
the first app.
And that's because I as the user launched
both of these
applications, and therefore both of them
are associated with my user account.