[MUSIC]
Welcome to the first part of the module
on Android Services and local interprocess
communication mechanisms.
Which provides an overview of Started and
Bound Services.
In this part, we discuss what a Service
is, summarize the two types of Services
supported
by Android, and outline steps for
implementing both
types of Services and configuring Services
into applications.
A Service is an Android component that can
perform long-duration operations in a
background thread or process.
Potentially communicating with other
components during
it's life cycle, as described here.
For example, a Service might perform
secure transactions with
an e-commerce website, playing music or
videos on a mobile
device, synchronize the contents of an
SQLite database with
the cloud, or download a file from a
remote server.
Which is an application use case we'll
explore further throughout this module.
Other android components can start a
Service automatically on demand.
Services are most commonly started by
activity components.
A Service can continue to run on behalf of
the activity
that started it even if the user switches
to another activity.
Since a Service runs in the background
it shouldn't direct the access the user
interface.
In particular, code running in a Service
should not make calls on
user interface toolkit components, such as
structured layered objects, controls,
dialogs and menus.
This restriction is similar to the
constraints on background
threads discussed in the module on Android
concurrency frameworks.
Although a Service may or may not actually
run in a background thread.
Android supports two different types of
Services.
A Started Service is launched when
a client calls startService, as discussed
here.
It usually performs a single operation on
behalf of the client that
started it, and often does not return a
result to the client.
A Started Service needs to shut itself
down explicitly
after completing the operation the client
directed it to perform.
Since it's life cycle is independent to
the client that started it.
So it can run in the background
indefinitely.
A Bound Service is launched when a client,
again,
typically an activity component calls
bindService, as discussed here.
A Bound Service offers a client-service
interface that allows extended
two-way conversations between one or more
clients and the Service.
A Bound Service runs only as long as at
least one client remains bound to it.
It's automatically destroyed when all
clients unbind.
Both Started and Bound Services can run in
the same or different
processes as their clients, based on
the configuration setting in the
AndroidManifest.xml file.
If they run in different processes, then
some former
inter process communication mechanism is
needed to exchange messages.
To implement Started and Bound Services
flexibly
and extensively, as well as to guide
their inter process communication
efficiently, Android applies
many POSA and Gang of Four patterns.
Including activator, command processor,
active
object, proxy, broker, and publisher
subscriber.
As we'll discuss later in this MOOC.
[MUSIC]
Now that we've presented an overview of
Started and Bound Services.
We'll summarize the steps needed to
implement them using Andriod's Services
framework.
Which is part of the Android's activity
manager service middleware, shown at this
path name.
The steps used to implement a Service are
similar
to the steps used to implement an
activity, as shown
in the week 2 lecture in professor
Porter's MOOC, since
both support canonical framework
techniques such as inversion of control.
The main specific structure and
functionality and some I
complete portions of applications, as
discussed in this video.
The first step in programming a Service
involves
extending the Android Service class, which
defines a number
of Service-specific lifecycle hook methods
that play the
role of primitive operations in the
template method pattern.
These hook methods are dispatched
automatically by
Android Service framework by inversion of
control,
in response to infrastructure and
application events
associated with changes to a services
lifecycle state.
Depending on whether the Service is
intended to be Started
or Bound, different subsets of these hook
methods must be overridden.
Which illustrates how Android's Service
framework defines reusable structure
and functionality that's specific to
different types of Services.
Certain hook methods are common to both
types of Services.
For example, the onCreate hook method is
dispatched by
Android Service framework when the Service
is first launched.
It's typically used to initialize the
Service.
Other hook methods are specific to one
type of Service or another.
For example, the onStartCommand hook
method is
dispatched by Android's Service framework
every time
the startService method is invoked to send
an intent command to a Started Service.
It receives the intent parameter past the
startService, which can be used
in conjunction with the concurrency model
the Service applies to perform its
processing.
The onBind and onUnbind hook methods are
caught automatically by the Android
Service framework, when
the client binds or unbinds to a
Bound Service by a bindService or
unBindService respectively.
OnBind receives the intent passed
bindService.
It's a factory method that returns the
interprocess communication
channel used by a client to communicate
with the service.
This IPC channel is typically an object
described using the Android interface
definition language.
OnUnbind is a disposal method called when
all clients
have disconnected from an interface
published by the service.
Finally, the Android Service framework
dispatches the onDestroy hook
method to notify a Service that it's being
removed.
And should therefore clean up any
resources it holds.
[MUSIC]
The Android Service framework provides a
semi-complete portion of an application.
So after the Service is extended, and its
hook method is implemented.
A description of it must be included in
the Android manifest file.
Together with other components to help
complete the application as discussed
here.
This XML file contains information that
Android needs to
plug-in various activity and Service
components, and execute the application.
Integrating a Service into an application
is straightforward.
And involves including the Service in the
AndroidManifest file and defining
various XML elements that control
properties
of the Service, that's covered here.
For example, a Service element is first
added as
a child of the application element in the
AndroidManifest file.
And a name is then provided to reference
the Service class.
Services don't automatically run in
separate processes or threads.
However, making the Service run in a
separate process, just involves
adding the process element to the
AndroidManifest file, as discussed here.
We'll show how to multithread a service
later in this module.
[MUSIC]
In summary, Android applications use
Services to
implement long duration operations in the
background.
This module focuses primarily on Services
written by application developers.
For example, we examine several variants
of Started and
Bound Services that can download images
from a remote server.
However, Android also provides many
predefined system services such as
the activity manager service, location
manager servic,e and telephony service.
Every Android application can use these
Services
as long as it has the proper permissions.
By default, a Service runs in the same
process as the application that it's a
part of.
Although it can easily be configured to
run in a
separate process by adding an element to
the AndroidManifest file.
Regardless of whether a Service is
configured to run in the same
process or in a different process however,
it continues to execute until
it stops itself, is stopped by a user or
is terminated by
the Android runtime system when it runs
low on memory, as discussed here.
Many properties of Services can be
configured
in an AndroidManifest.xml file, as shown
here.
Since Started and Bound Services are
implemented as part
of Android's Service framework, they
support inversion of control.
For example, Android's middleware
dispatches hook methods to manage
the service lifecycle in response to
infrastructure and application events.
The design of Android Service framework is
based on software product
line techniques guided by commonality and
variability analysis, as discussed here.
For example, Android's Service framework
enhances
commonality by defining a uniform
interface
for performing long-duration operations
that don't
interact directly with the user interface.
Likewise, this framework handles
variability by providing
a uniform means for subclasses to override
life cycle hook methods that perform the
desired initialization for Started and
Bound Services.
Android's packaged application contains
many Services, such as the
SMS, MMS service that manages messaging
operations, the Alert service
that handles calendar event reminders, the
Bluetooth Headset service
that provides Headset and Handsfree
capabilities for the phone application.
The Media Playback service that streams
audio files in the background.
And the Exchange service that sends email
messages to exchange servers.
Additional information on Android Services
appears at this link.
[MUSIC]