[MUSIC]
Let's contrast the way the Android works
from security perspective,
from the way that a traditional desktop
operating system works.
So what is fundamentally different?
Well, if you have to sum it up in
one phrase, it's that apps are people, on
Android.
And this is a really profound thing from a
security point of view that
makes Android behave from a security
perspective
very differently from a traditional
desktop environment.
So let's take a look at how this affects
things.
On Android, if I go and launch an app, and
let's
say it's, you know, it, we, we take a
photograph with
the camera, and we touch it up in a photo
editing
program, similar to what we were doing in
our desktop user example.
So, we launch our first app, which is a
photo editor, to touch up a photo.
And this is going to be our first app,
and it's going to access information on
the device.
Now, one of the immediate things that's
different is that this
app is going to be launched with its own
user account.
So the photo editor is going to have a
photo editor user.
It's a separate account that's associated
with it.
And what this means it that the photo
editor
has its own set of privileges and
permissions that
have been assigned to it, that aren't the
default
ones that are assigned to me as a user.
Because, even though I've launched that
app,
because I've launched it, under my user
account doesn't mean that, that photo
editor
automatically gets all of my permissions
and capabilities.
We want to restrict what that photo editor
is able to do, to
only things that I, as the user, want it
to be able to do.
So it has its own photo editor user
account that has been created when
I installed that app, and when I agreed to
let it have certain permissions.
So what this means is the photo editor can
access
parts of the storage that are associated
with the photo editor.
So that we can think of our storage as
being divided up.
And so there's a region of that storage
that's assigned to that photo editor.
And it can read and write files to that
region of the storage that's part of its
private data, or the area within the
storage that's been sliced off for it.
Similarly, if when I installed this photo
editor, I gave it permission to access
the internet, then its user account has a
special permission associated with it.
It allows it to go and access the internet
through the Wi-Fi or cellular network
connected to the device.
Where the model of security that has apps
as people
gets really interesting, is when we launch
a second application.
So, let's say on the Android we launch a
second application, which is a web browser
that we're going to view our edited image
in just like we did on the desktop.
Now, where there's an immediate difference
in how Android operates,
is what this web browser can access on the
storage system.
The web browser, if this was on the
desktop,
would be able to just directly go and read
this
file that I had saved in the photo editor,
because
both applications would have been
associated with my user account.
And thus they both have access to the same
areas in the storage system.
But, on Android, because this web browser
is going to run
underneath its own user account, its web
browser, user, it
can't directly access the files created by
the photo editor.
Because, the photo editor stuff is
private, so this is not allowed.
Because this is private access.
This is something that exists only for
this photo editor user account.
So one of the immediate differences is,
that each app that I launch as a user does
not automatically get the same permissions
and capabilities as other apps.
So I can't just launch a photo editor,
save some data to the
storage system of that, in the private
storage of that photo editor, and
then access it with the web browser,
because they have separate user accounts
and they have access to separate sets of
files on the file system.
Now there are ways to get around this that
we'll talk about.
And one of them for example, is saving
images to the SD card on your device.
But, when we begin doing things like
saving data
to the SD card, or to other places that
other
apps can access, we have to be conscious
from a
security point of view what the
ramifications are of that.
Now the important thing to remember is, by
default, Android wants each
app to be its own user and to save data in
its own private data store system.
By default, Android is segregating your
app from other apps on the system
to prevent them from stealing data from
your apps or doing other malicious things.