[MUSIC]
Welcome to the first module in the section
on Android Services and Security.
This module examines several types of
frameworks and mechanisms provided
by Android, that allow applications
to perform computations in service
components.
Which can execute long duration operations
in background threads or processes, and
potentially communicate with other
activity or
service components throughout their life
cycle.
It also examines several types of
inner process communication mechanisms
that Android provides,
to enable activity components and
background
service components, to interact
concurrently and securely.
We discussed started services, which
typically
perform a single operation before
terminating,
and bound services, which allow clients
to conduct longer conversations with
service implementations.
Activities and services interact via
several inter-process
communication mechanisms that are
optimized for passing
messages between processes on Android
mobile devices,
via the binder object-oriented remote
procedure call framework.
This module examines several Android
inter-process
communication mechanisms that use the
binder.
Including intents, which are commands
passed to
an activity or service when it's started,
and messengers which extend the intra
process
message passing mechanisms in the Android
hammer framework.
To enable interprocess message passing
communication.
We also cover the Android interface
definition language that's often used to
simply Java application access to the
powerful, but complex, binder
communication capabilities.
Naturally, the Android services and
interprocess communication mechanisms
apply many posa and gang of four patterns.
Which we also cover throughout the module.
[MUSIC]