[MUSIC]
So to help improve the security of how we
write apps, let's
talk a little bit about how Android
protects our apps from other apps.
And then once we understand how it
protects our
apps, we can also understand what it
doesn't do for
us, and what it expects us as developers
to
do to ensure that our apps stay safe and
secure.
So the first thing that Android does, is
whenever
you go and launch an app, as we've seen
before, that app has its own user account
associated
with it that determines what it can and
can't do.
But it also is launched in its own
process.
So, your app is launched in its own
process,
and what a process does is it's an
operating
system construct that protects the memory
of your app, while
it's running, from the memory of other
applications.
So your app will run in a process, and if
there's some malware that
might be trying to attack your app, it'll
be running in its own separate process.
So we'll have another process, and we'll
have your original process.
Now what this means is, if your app's
memory is protected,
let's say that this is the I Remember app,
and we
have a variable that, for example, maybe
it's the server that
we're going to save data to or try to
login to.
So maybe we have a server variable defined
in one of our Java classes.
Well, what the processed memory
protections means is that the
second process can't go and directly write
to this variable.
So this is not allowed.
That would be a violation of the security
that
processes provide to separate the memory
from each other.
Now, you can see why this is so important.
If this malware could go and directly
change
a variable in your code, for instance, if
it could go and change some variable
telling
where the I Remember app should log in.
And tell it to go and log in to another
server, for example, if you
go and capture your username and password,
and do all kinds of other malicious
things.
So, the memory protections that a process
provides are very important.
So, we get memory protection on our apps
from
other apps running on Android at the same
time.
Another very important thing that Android
provides
is it provides a guarantee on the storage
of the things that your app will decides
or persists to the storage on the device.
So, what do we care about in this case?
Well, we care about that we can save state
for
our app because our app may not always be
running and
that when we go and relaunch that
application, we know that
that state will still be intact and in its
original condition.
So you can think about, for example, if
you were storing important data about the
state
of your app to disk and another app
could come in, overwrite that state, and
change it.
Then you could do a lot of very malicious
things from another app.
So it's very important that Android
protects whatever state
or information we save to the underlying
storage system.
So, what types of state can we save that
are, get protected by Android?
Well the very first and important piece of
state that
we might save, for example, is the APK for
our app.
So, when we go and actually create an
app, we're creating a package that's going
to be
stored on the underlying file system on
the
device, that has all of our code in it.
So if another app could go and directly
manipulate our APK, it
could change the behavior of our app in
whatever way it wanted.
So it's very important that we protect
these APKs for our apps when they're
installed.
And Android does that for us.
It provides protections over the APKs of
each app.
So your app can't go and over write or
change another
app APK and those apps can't go and change
your app's APK.
What are other types of things that we
might want to store and protect?
Things like the database.
So if your app wants to store data in the
SQLite database on our device.
You can store that database, and Android,
depending on
how you store that data, and we'll talk
about
this, will protect that data so that only
your
app can read data in the database that
you're writing.
Other things that you might want to
persist are
settings for your app, and those can also
be persistent.
So how does Android go about actually
protecting these things under the hood?
Well the way that Android does it, as
we've seen
before is that each app has its own user
account.
And that essentially defines an area of
the
storage on the device that's assigned to
that app.
So if another app goes and tries to write
to this area of storage, it can't.
Because that's owned by that other app's
user account.
So by default, Android gives us two really
important things.
It gives us the ability to protect our
application's memory from other
apps running so they can't change our
variables or our run time state.
And then also it gives us the protect,
ability to protect the
data that we save to disc or to storage on
our device.
And that's protecting our state that's
persistent between launches.
So what Android's giving us is the ability
to protect our app, both when it's
running,
by protecting state that's in the process
of
that app, and then secondly, any state
that we
need to store, because it is a mobile
device, and apps get shut down from time
to
time, the, the battery on the phone dies,
and we need to be able to save state.
It protects all of that state that we
saved on the
underlying storage system in a special
area that's assigned to our app.