[MUSIC].
Welcome to the section on Android Services
and applications security.
Which explores the pattern oriented
frameworks and
mechanisms that Android provides, to
perform computations
in the background and communicate between
user
phasing components and background
components, concurrently, and securely.
Although the activity components, covered
in Professor Porter's Mooc,
provide a flexible visual interface for
interacting with the user.
Android also defines service components,
which run in the separate
background thread or process, and don't
interact with the user directly.
Instead, activities use services to
perform long duration
operations or access remote resources on
behalf of users.
Such as downloading files from a remote
server.
Or synchronizing data stored on a mobile
device, with a database in the cloud.
Activities and services can interact via
several interprocess
communication mechanisms, that we'll cover
in this section.
This section also focuses on Android
application security, which is an
important and
timely topic, due to the increasing
number of Android application
vulnerabilities being discovered.
We first describe Android security model
and
explain some of its risks and limitations.
We then discuss various techniques, tools
and
methods for building more secure Android
applications.
We explain the most common types of
security flaws in Android applications,
show how
to spot them in code, and describe methods
and means for fixing these flaws.
This section also explains how to design
and implement services, activities and
other Android components to protect your
applications against security flaws and
attacks.
[MUSIC]