[MUSIC]
When your app gets installed, that's when
the system creates the
identity of the account that's going to be
associated with your app.
So let's dive a little deeper into what
that actually
means an app for Android when you install
an app.
And what happens under the hood to create
that user account.
Well, when you create an Android app, one
of the things
you have to specify is an Android manifest
that XML file.
And this is a file, that all of you should
be very well familiar with if you've been
building Android apps.
And what this does is it tells Android
things that it needs to know about your
app
in order to install it on the system,
in order to understand what it's different
components are.
And very importantly from a security
perspective, it tells it
which capabilities of the hardware
platform on the Android device,
or the capabilities provided by other
apps, like the Contacts
app, that you want to have access to in
your app.
So you declare a series of uses
permissions.
And these are things that your app wants
to have access to on the underlying
platform.
And each of these user permissions
corresponds to
some type of underlying capability of the
device.
Something like access to the internet,
maybe.
Or, access to the camera.
And your app declares all of these things
up front, so that when the user
installs your app on their device, Android
can go and scan all of these
user permissions, figure out what they map
to in terms of capabilities on your
device, and then present a menu to the
user, saying do you want to allow?
[BLANK_AUDIO]
This app to have access to X, Y, and Z
things?
So the user gets to decide, is this okay?
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And if they say that it's okay, what
Android does, is it takes all of these
user permissions, and it goes and creates
an account on the underlying
Linux operation system, that's part of
Android, for your app.
So Android, is a modified version of Linux
that runs on mobile devices.
And when you create that install an app
and then create a user account for it,
what's actually happening is that the
underlying Linux
operating system is creating a user for
that app.
So this and this basically create
the Linux user, for your app.
This is what's define the capabilities of
this Linux user.
Is the things that you ask for in your
manifest file?
Underneath the hood, each of the things
you ask for like internet, or camera.
Each of those has a separate Linux group
that's associated with it.
For example, you may have the camera
group.
And this is a user group, that is set up
to
define the set of users that have access
to the camera.
And this is already on the device, when
you install the app.
And so what Android does is it creates
your Linux user.
And then based on each of the user permit,
user's permissions, it figures
out which of the different user groups
your accounts should be associated with.
So it associates, this, app, for a photo
editor, let's say, with it's own Linux
user, and then it associates that Linux
user with the underlying camera group.
And so now, when your app is running, if
your app goes and tries to
access the camera, Android and its
underlying Linux kernel can look
at the user account associated with your
app, and then can check if
it's part of this Linux user group that
should have access to the camera.
So underneath the hood, all of these
permissions
that we see in our apps, and that are
manifested as uses permissions in the
Android manifest XML
files, actually get mapped down to Linux
user groups.