[MUSIC]
One thing that we should try to avoid in
our
code, if possible, is to reduce the amount
of conditional logic.
We love to use if, else, switch statements
and all these other things in
our code to write methods and to write
logic, but all of this conditional
logic, even from a general software
engineering
sense, makes it harder to read our
code and harder to guarantee that a
particular state that we expect will be
reached.
It's also easier to go and introduce
errors when there's conditional logic.
Now, in a security point of view, suddenly
errors that we
introduced might not be our app crashing,
but they might be worse.
If we have conditional logic that's
incorrect, it might
be someone's very private data being
stolen by an attacker.
So, we really don't want to have
conditional logic that makes
it harder to secure applications and more
likely that we'll make mistakes.
The other thing is if other developers
come and read our
code, it's not as apparent which security
level should be chosen.
This example is pretty simple, so probably
Nobody is going to make a mistake.
But in many cases, there might be complex
conditional logic and the more complex
this conditional logic
gets, the more likely the users of this
interface are to make a mistake in its
usage.
So we'd like to simplify the conditional
logic to also avoid the chance that
somebody else will look at our code and
misinterpret how it's intended to operate.
It's also very important from a clarity
point
of view because when we audit our code, we
would really like to be able to prove or
know very certainly that our code is
actually secure.
If we have conditional logic, it makes it
hard to make
that argument that yes, this code is
always going to operate properly.
The final issue that we can see with this
security level approach is that
the semantics of what security level max
means versus security level none aren't
really clear.
It's not 100% obvious what it means to
have maximum security and whether
or not maximum security is good enough to
store a particular piece of data.
Or maybe it's not good enough, and maybe
you need to store that server side
somewhere else.
And so, because there's not a clear
meaning to
these security levels, somebody who is
using our interface may
not be able to make an appropriate and
reasoned decision
about how to securely code the storage of
their data.
So we would really like to have an
interface
that makes it clear what the semantics are
of the
calls that they're making, so there's no
way that
they could misinterpret what the security
is intended to do.
So how can we make this interface even
cleaner and more straightforward from a
security perspective?
Well, if we could remove the conditional
logic and refactor our code to look
more like this, where we actually have
two different methods that have very clear
intentions.
So by removing that conditional logic,
we're going to do two things here.
One, we're going to make our code a lot
easier to test.
It's pretty straightforward to test these
methods and to ensure
that we are exercising them in a way that
will check
the different conditions that those
methods can go through because
they're going to do the same thing
regardless of the input data.
So it's much easier to test these methods.
The second thing is we're going to make
the semantics and the intention of
these methods much more obvious because
store
data privately and encrypted is pretty
clear.
Store data with security level max is less
obvious as to what that means.
So we are making it harder for users of
our code to make mistakes
when they are building around our security
abstractions.
Another very important point is if we go
look at
places where our API, our abstractions are
being used, suddenly it
becomes very obvious what's going on, at
an even greater level
of clarity than we had before, with our
security level approach.
Suddenly we can look and we can see the
private groups
are being stored in way that is both
private and encrypted.
And that gives us more information for
reasoning about whether
or not that is an okay security decision
to make.
Similarly, we can go and look and see that
the profile photo
and the homepage URL are both being stored
publicly on the SD card.
And then we can reason about, is that okay
or not?
So, we have taken something that was
helping us
to name our security and we've increased
the semantics.
We've increased the richness of the
information that's being
expressed by the interface, so that when
somebody else
comes along and reads this code, they know
exactly
what's going on, or what should be going
on.
We've done a lot to improve the clarity of
our interfaces and abstractions that we're
providing in our application.
And we've also helped to eliminate some of
the testing complexity and some of
the conditional logic that was there that
opened us up to mistakes and security
vulnerabilities.
But there's still some more that we can do
to improve the security
of these abstractions and interfaces that
we're using in our implementation of them.