[MUSIC]
Let's look at another way that an open
service,
that can be invoked by an intent, might
accidentally
leak a capability that an, another app
does not
currently have permission to access,
through that intent-based service.
So let's assume that we have a service
that allows an app
to download an arbitrary file by simply
sending our app an intent.
And you tell our app what is the URL of
the file that you want to download.
Our app will automatically go and download
that file, store it to disk, and then
return via intent to whatever app called
us,
the location of the file that we
downloaded.
So we're creating a generic download
service that we want
to expose to other apps on the device via
an intent.
Well, let's say that you're malware and
you
want to download a malicious payload to
the device.
So, for example, you want to download some
extra
code that's going to be used to attack the
device.
Well, if you're malware and you have no
permissions, you
look a less, a lot less suspicious to the
user.
So you can have no permissions.
And essentially the user is going to
think, well it's unlikely this
app is going to do anything very
malicious, because it has no permissions.
But in reality, because you've created
this app that
allows another app to send an intent, to
download something.
So we're going to send an intent,
and we're going to say download, attack
payload.
So we'll go and tell it, this malicious
payload that we want
to get downloaded, it'll go off to the
internet, and,
get that payload for us, and return the
attack payload.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then it will return to this piece of
malware in its on, result.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The file where the attack payload is
stored.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So in this case, what we've got, is we've
got an app that's
creating a service that's intended to be
helpful to other apps in the device.
But, because it allows any app to send in
an intent saying,
go and download something for me and then
it blindly goes and accesses
the internet which is a capability that it
has, downloads the payload
for it and then returns the payload to
whoever sent it that intent.
Again, we're bypassing Android's built-in
permissions mechanism by having
a piece of malware that's essentially
manipulating another app into
getting access to a capability on the
device, in this
case, access to the Internet, that it
doesn't currently have.
So one of the things that you have to be
cognizant of, is that, although
you can create apps that can talk to other
apps, that when you talk to
those other apps that you talk to them in
a way and take commands or
other things from them in a way
that doesn't break the permission model on
Android.
That if you're going to use something like
internet an, or the camera, that you make
sure that the way that you're using and
accessing that thing and the data you're
returning to
the dev, to the application that's asking
for access to it, isn't done in such a way
that, you're breaking the permissions or
circumventing, what
the user intended that app to have access
to.
If the user didn't give a piece of malware
any permissions, your app shouldn't be
exposing additional capabilities
or permissions to that malware by not
checking the
capabilities that it has when it begins
interacting with it.