[MUSIC]
One of the challenges that we've
introduced is our current implementation
relies on secure pathways, such as the
store privately and encrypted pathway uuu.
If the developers call in that pathway,
they are assuming that it's intact
and that the data that they saved there
will be correctly stored and encrypted.
But the problem is that with our current
implementation, there's
no guarantee that the data will actually
be stored correctly.
And the reason is is that this secure
pathway relies on the underlying
handler mapping being correctly configured
in order to operate properly.
So, if unfortunately we set up these init
handler methods incorrectly, if we set up
these individual mappings inside the
handler mapping
and we map the wrong handler to the
wrong key, we're going to end up in
a situation where, for example, the stored
data
of privately and encrypted method ends up
using a handler that's actually a public
handler.
And this is a simple mistake that can be
made.
It's a configuration mistake, but it can
actually
break the underlying implementation of
that secure pathway.
Another challenge that we faced here is
that our handler mapping isn't immutable.
That is, it isn't actually a, a data
structure that can be changed at run time.
And whatever we have a secure pathway that
relies on some
data structure that can be changed at run
time, we open ourselves
up for the possibility of attack or the
possibility that due to some bug,
that secure pathway might be compromised
in certain execution scenarios.
So we, whenever possible, want to make our
secure pathways invariant and we want
them to be fixed at run time, so that
configuration errors, either on files that
we use to load our application and
bootstrap our state, or errors in the
actual configuration of the API and its
usage don't cause our secured pathways to
break.
This is particularly important because
we've take
so much effort to make our abstractions
obvious,
so we've made our abstractions and which
methods
should be called to be secure really
obvious.
But if suddenly the underlying
implementation is compromised
due to configuration errors, it can lead
to very
hard to detect bugs because on the
surface,
it looks like the API is being exercised
correctly.
But underneath the surface, the
configuration
of it is actually not enforcing
the rules correctly, and so, what looks
like correctly secured code is not.
So the way that we can improve this is by
trying
to make our secure pathways something that
is decided at compile time.
We don't want run time errors or
configuration
decisions that are made to affect that
secure pathway.
The simple way to do it in this case is to
change our get private encrypted storage
handler method to not use the handler
mapping at
all, but instead to directly instantiate
the appropriate handler.
In this case, the private storage adapter,
in
order to make sure that it's always
returned correctly.
We don't want to end up in a situation
where the handling
mapping either changes at run time due to
some circumstance that we
didn't anticipate, or where we have a
configuration file or some other
information that used to initialize this
handler mapping that is done incorrectly.
We want to have pathways that are secure
and they are secured
at compile time and that have unit tests
and other tests
supplied to them to make sure that they're
always exercised correctly
and that they always provide the security
guarantees that we want.
So, by using this implementation and this
design
change where we're going to directly
instantiate the appropriate
handler, it greatly improves our trust in
these
security pathways since they're not
exposed to configuration errors.
Now, some of you may say, but yes, aren't
we going back though?
Why aren't we tightly coupling our code
and removing some
of these wonderful patterns and
abstractions that we've learned to use?
Well, in this case I don't think that's
actually the case.
What we're doing is we're still using the
storage handler interface to decouple the
different parts
of our code, but we're being smart about
where we apply that decoupling, and
configurability, and modularity.
We don't want that decoupling and, and
configurability
to be present in our secure pathway in
a way that makes it possible that our
secure pathway could be compromised to an
error.
We want that decoupling to be present to
allow
us to plug in different implementations,
but we want to
be able to check those implementations and
test them, and
we don't want to expose that pathway to
configuration errors.
So, it's not that we are building
tightly-coupled code, it's that
we are building code that's modular, but
modular in the right places.
And we don't want modularity in a,
introduced
into those secure pathways in a way that
could compromise them at run time, or lead
to very subtle and difficult to detect
security problems.