[MUSIC]
Let's talk about some news stories that
have been out on the Internet about
different security issues that we've seen
with some production apps.
These are some pretty big name apps that
have had security
issues and we don't want to write apps
that have these same flaws.
Now the specific type of flaw that we're
going to
look at in this case is called a privilege
escalation.
Now you may say well, I would never
write an app that would accidentally have
this flaw.
But the reality is these are very subtle
mistakes that developers make.
Where they don't realize the ramifications
of
the decisions they're making, particularly
when they
let other apps talk to their app in order
to access services within their app.
It's very easy to make mistakes.
To accidentally break things like the
permissions model in Android.
Now you may say, I'll never do that.
Let's show you how you could accidentally
and
inadvertently do something like this with
the iRemember app.
Let's talk about two services that we
could extend the
iRemember app with, that might seem benign
and very helpful
to other apps on the device, but that we
can
actually show will create a security issue
on the device.
So let's talk about these two services
that we're going to extend
the iRemember app with and then use as an
example of poor security.
So the first one is we decide that we'd
like to be able to share stories via
an intent so that other apps that allow
you to compose a story and maybe
attach a photo to a story can simply send
an intent to this service.
So they'll send and intent and that intent
will have a story plus a photo.
And then the service will go off and share
that
story and that photo that the other app
sent to us.
Now, let's further assume that, you know,
to
be really flexible, we decide that we
want to create
a version of the iRemember app that can
share
stories and photos to different servers on
the Internet.
So we don't want to control all of the
iRemember servers.
We want to have, maybe, iRemember servers
that are for Vanderbilt
University or a set of iRemember servers
that are for the
University of Maryland, because we want to
be able to
have different sets of stories and
photographs, depending on the location.
And we decide we don't want to centrally
manage all of that information.
So one of the things that we could do on
this intent is we could allow it to
also include the URL of the server that we
want to share that story and that photo
with.
And then what we would do is actually when
this intent gets sent to the
service to share the story and photo, it
would go off and would access the
Internet.
And do the actual share force by sending
it to that server.
Now this seems like a very benign thing,
but as we'll show in
a second here, this actually opens up
a security hole in Android's permissions
model.
Now, let's look at our second service that
we're going to add.
So, let's say, for example, that we decide
that we want to be able to attach
photos to these stories in iRemember, but
attach
photos that aren't necessarily locally
stored in the device.
So, we want the user to be able to type in
a URL of a photo to share, maybe it's a
photo that's stored on Facebook's servers
or Google Plus' servers or somewhere else.
So we want to give the ability for a user
to specify an arbitrary URL and then we
want to create
a service that will automatically go and
fetch that photo
from the Internet and download it to the
local desk.
And then return a file descriptor or
URI specifying where that photo was
downloaded to.
But since we're already going in and
creating a capability
to allow other apps to share stories and
photos, why don't
we go ahead and just expose the service to
download
arbitrary photos from the Internet as an
intent service as well.
So similarly, we'll allow apps to send to
this service an intent, and in that intent
we will have the URL of the photo that we
want to go and collect from the Internet.
And so the service will go and access the
Internet, it'll download that file.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And then it will return to this original
service the file that was
downloaded, or the location of that file
that was downloaded.
Again, this seems like a, a helpful
service to, we can have
our app, the iRemeber app exposed to other
apps on the device.
So that it makes it easier for them to
share photos and stories.
But, in both cases, we'll actually see,
that
we're doing something inadvertently,
that's breaking Android's permissions
model.
One of the things to remember is that, for
both of these to
work, we're going to have to add the uses
permission to iRemember for Internet.
Now we've already probably got it there
for
the capabilities that we're exposing in
iRemember, but
we have to remember that we have Internet
permissions in order for all of this to
work.