[MUSIC]
As we saw, the problem that we ran into
was
that our app was acting like a naive bank
manager.
It was giving out access to anybody that
asked for it.
Without actually vetting that they should
have access.
So we were going and getting from the
Internet
any resource that we asked to go and
retrieve.
Without really thinking about does the app
that's
calling us have permission to access that
resource.
We were blindly taking it, information out
of the intent that was a set to us.
And assuming that it was okay to go
and get whatever information that caller
was asking for.
Without vetting that information or the
intent, or the sender of that intel.
But, in the Android, there's a way we
can avoid these issues, these privilege
escalation problems.
And that's by insuring that whoever calls
our code has a specific permission.
So for example, if your app is using the
internet or
if a particular activity like our download
activity, is using the internet.
We can also require that anybody that
launches, the download activity also have
that permission.
So let's take a look at how we do that.
So here's the manifest file for the
download activity that we just looked at.
And it's a standard Android manifest.
We've got an application and then we've
got our download activity here.
Now, ordinarily, if you just add an
activity and that
activity is exported and visible to other
activities on the device.
Then anybody can send an intent, and
launch it.
And since we're not betting the data in
anyway in our download
activity, we're assuming that the caller
was a, allowed to launch us.
We're just going to go and blindly, use
whatever permissions or
capabilities have been given, to complete
the actions that we need.
But in this case we're doing something
special,
to protect that activity, and prevent a
privilege escalation.
What you'll see is with interactivity we
have this line requiring
that whoever calls this particular
activity have the Internet permission.
And what this means is, is that at
runtime, if another activity or some
other app sends us an intent and it is
sent to this particular activity.
If the caller does not have the internet
permission, it will cause an exception to
be thrown.
So this is a really important way that you
can protect activities
that are accessing resources that they've
gained access to through a permission.
So, in this case, we're accessing the
internet, which is a
resource that we got access to by using
the internet permission.
But we want to make sure that callers of
us also have
that internet permission, since we're
going to use it on their behalf.
So this is a way of making the download
activity safe.
Now in some cases you may have a situation
where your activity
relies on multiple permissions or relies
on some new type of permission.
And in those cases you can declare
somewhere up in your
manifest file a new particular permission
that you want callers to have.
So, for example, let's say that you have a
custom
service that allows people to buy things
on the internet.
And you want to be able to accept intents
that
allow callers to add things to your buyer
shopping cart.
Well in that case, you're about to do
something, you're going to expose a
service that could potentially cause the
owner of the device to be charged money.
So you'd want to create a new permission
for that.
And then in the activity, where you
actually added things to
the cart, or the service where you added
things to the cart.
You'd want to add that permission in to
make sure that anyone
that called you and asked you to add
something to the cart.
They had told that user that they were
going to do that
and they had gotten sig off, and approval
to have those permissions.
So it's really, really important that
whenever you build, activities, services,
broadcast receivers, content providers,
that you safeguard the resources.
The permissions that you've been given and
don't leak them to other applications.
And there's all kinds of different ways
you can do it.
But the way that you can protect yourself
is
by ensuring anyone that calls you has the
appropriate permission.
And that they have at least as many
permissions
as your activity requires to perform that
particular service.
Any of our application components.
Ranging from activities to services to
broadcast receivers to content
providers could potentially be the source
of a privilege escalation.
So although we've looked at protecting
activities.
You should also be cognizant that all of
the same
techniques apply to you, the other
component in your application.
The broadcast receivers, the services,
whether they
are unbound or bound, the content
providers.
And just like we did with the activities,
we can
still protect each of these individual
components of our application.
We simply need to go and look at each
individual component.
See what the permissions are that is needs
to carry out the services
that it's performing or see the
sensitivity of the services.
And the information that that application
component is working with.
And then make a decision about what
permission should be used to protect that
service.
And then, whatever permission we decide
on, we
can, just as we did with the activity.
Add that permission to that particular
component
or application in order to protect it.
So, just because we create a component in
our
application doesn't mean that we have to
leave it unprotected.
Anything we can create can then later be
protected with a permission in the
manifest file.
Similarly, if, for example, you
programmatically create a broadcast
receiver.
There is code that can be used to actually
add that permission to the broadcast
receiver when it's registered.
To ensure that that broadcast receiver
only gets
invoked if the caller has the appropriate
permission.
So whenever you're building your different
application components.
Particularly application components that
are designed
to interact with other apps and services.
It's very important that we protect them
with the appropriate permissions.
So that our app doesn't become the
equivalent of that
naive bank manager who starts handing out
access to the vault.
And all of the money and other secrets
stored
inside that that bank manager has been
giving access to.
We want to protect and ensure that whoever
gets access to that vault.
Whoever gets access to the information or
services that we've gained access to
through permissions.
Also has the appropriate permissions to
operate on that data or
to take the actions that are being exposed
by those services.