[MUSIC]
One of the things we have to be careful of
when we're
building activities and services and
broadcast
receivers, is that we don't accidentally
take the permissions and the capabilities
and the resources that we've been
given access to and expose those
permissions or capabilities to other apps.
So how might we go about accidentally
exposing, let's for example say a resource
that we were given access to, in this case
the Internet, to another application?
Well, intents give other applications the
ability to communicate with us.
Interprocess communication gives other
applications
the ability to communicate with us.
So whenever we build services or
capabilities that allow other activities
or
other applications to communicate with our
activities, we have to be very careful
that the way that those activities behave
doesn't violate the trust that's
been placed in those activities in terms
of the permissions they've been given.
So, for example, let's take a look at this
code base here.
We see that we've got a simple download
activity which seems like
a good idea to help other people be able
to download files.
So, we have this download activity that
we're going to expose to
other activities to allow them to send us
an intent, that specifies
an address of some resource on the
internet that they would like
to download, and then a file where they'd
like that resource saved.
And then that other activity can go and
get access to it.
So, we'll see that in our onCreate method,
we do the normal things where
we set up the content view for
this activity, and then we do something
interesting.
We do this performDownload.
So, immediately upon starting up, our
activity is going
to try to download some file from the
internet.
Now clearly, in order for this code to
work, our activity had to be given
internet permission.
Otherwise any, you know, attempt to access
the internet is simply not going to work.
So let's take a look at what we do with
that permission, that capability,
and how we then leak that, or
cause a privilege escalation potentially
from another application.
So in our performDownload method, the very
first thing that we do, is
we go and get the intent out, that's
actually been sent to us.
And one of the things that we see in that
intent
is an address of the file that the caller
would like downloaded.
We then take that intent, and we also
abstract, extract
the actual location where the caller would
like that file saved.
And then finally we simply go and download
that file and save it to disk.
Now, can you see the problem with this
code that we've got here?
Do you see the issue that we're creating?
In order for us to be able to go and
download this file, and
save it to disk, that requires that our
app have a series of permissions.
In particular, the internet permission.
But, other people, other apps can simply
send us an
intent, and we will go and download a file
for them.
And we're placing no restrictions of what
files or, we'll go an get.
So, we'll take anything in the address.
We don't care what's in that address.
And we'll save it to any old place on
disk.
So any place that we can access, and that
another app tells us to save
it, we will go and save that resource that
we downloaded from the internet there.
So, another app doesn't actually have to
get the internet permission.
All another app needs to do, is send us an
intent
and we'll go and do the work on that other
app's behalf.
Now if you remember early on in the series
of lectures we talked about
this model of apps are people and how apps
can try to manipulate each other.
And we gave it an analogy of convincing
the bank
manager to go and rob the bank vault for
you.
And that's essentially what this code is
doing.
Another app is convincing our code,
because we're naive in the way that
we've built this, to go and download some
arbitrary resource from the Internet.
There are no checks that being placed on
what's being downloaded, or what's being
done with it.
So we are essentially, through all of this
code
that we've got here, we are causing a
privilege escalation.
Or a potential privilege escalation.
And that's because anybody can call this
activity and tell it to go get something
off the internet, which is something that
should require internet permissions.
But, in this case, we already have the
permission, so the caller doesn't need it.
And that's a problem.
Because that's allowing us to leak access
to a critical
resource that we've been given access to,
to another app.
And so now all that some malware needs to
do is simply,
go and fire off an intent to our
application, we'll
go off and actually access the internet
for it.
And then, send it back, and say we're done
downloading it,
and then the malware can go and access the
downloaded file.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And get it, and do whatever it needs to do
with it.
So suddenly, the malware doesn't need the
internet permission anymore, because we're
creating a privilege
escalation situation were it can simply
get access
to the resource that it wants through us.