[MUSIC]
Now, as we've talked about, malware is
trying to manipulate the state of your
application in order to cause it to do
something that it wouldn't ordinarily do.
So, malware has the problem though, that
the process
boundaries are, preventing, the alware
from directly going and modifying
your stated memory, or the filesystem
permissions are, preventing the
malware from directly accessing state that
you've stored on disk.
So, one of the things that malware does
often to
try to manipulate the state of your
application, and get
access to it, is it relies on an entity
that
always has access to your application, and
most of its state.
And that's the user.
And so, what a common attack that malware
will use is to try to trick the
user into doing something that will
manipulate the state of your app.
And this can take a variety of different
forms, but the most common way that
malware will try to trick the user is by
displaying some type of fake message.
Or fake user interface, to the user that
is provided by
the malware, so that the user doesn't know
what they're looking at.
They think that they're interacting with
something legitimate, but
in reality it's a user interface or a
message
that the malware has created to try to
manipulate
the user into changing the state of your
application.
Or into taking some state from that
application and giving it to the malware.
And so we're going to talk in detail,
about what are the
different types of manipulations that
malware can use to try to gain
access to the state of your application,
and manipulate it in some
way, or read from it, in order to gain
access to it.
One of the other attacks that malware can
employ against your app or another
app on Android, and it's related to the
user interface constraints on
a mobile device, is to try to trick the
user into completing some
action because they can't tell what the
real state of your app is.
So, very commonly we rely on different
indicators of the state of
an app to know whether or not it's safe to
perform an action.
So, for example, when you're using a web
browser and you're going to log
in, often people will look for the little
lock icon which indicates that the,
the connection and communication with the
server are protected by TLS or https and
so it's an encrypted connection and we
feel safe sending our data across the
network.
So our ability to see that little lock
icon is very important for knowing whether
or not we should use the web browser to
enter our username and password.
So, the ability for the user to assess the
state of your app, and the security of
that state is a very important aspect of
developing good apps that are secure.
So, one of the types of attacks that
malware will employ is to rely on the
fact that, on a mobile device, you have
very little space available for the user
interface.
So it's very easy for the user to not see
important indicators of state
that they need to make a decision about
the security of the state of an app.
So, for example, let's say that we have an
app,
and it's going to display the login screen
for Coursera.
And in order to display that login screen,
it's going to use a
web view to directly display the web page
that's normally the Coursera login screen.
Well, if you have a web view, typically
you'll have an address bar here, that
displays the full address of the website
that's currently loaded into the web view.
Now, because there's a limited amount of
space here to
display the URL the true URL is going to
be something much longer,
but what we see in here, may be a
truncated version of that.
So, in this case we only get up to
Coursera, so if I'm the
user I may go and look at this and say oh,
okay, this is secure.
I should go and log into it because it's
the Coursera website.
I see Coursera there.
Now the attack that malware can play is if
there's a way to
trick your app into loading another
website into its web
view, it could, for example, redirect you
to, a slightly
different version of that website that
would display
exactly the same URL bar, so in this case,
rather than taking
it to coursera.com, it takes you to
corseratac.com.
And because the URL is truncated right
here, both of these two URLs
display exactly the same way in your
address bar of your web view.
And unless the user takes the time to
actually click on
that address bar and try to scroll through
and look at every
character of that URL, they may
accidentally feed their username and
password into Courseratac.com, which may
be a website owned by the attacker.
So in this case, the fact that our user
interface is limited and we can't see
the full domain name allows the malware to
go and manipulate the user with this
particular app.
Often because there's not a lot of screen
real estate
for our apps to use on a mobile device we
try to help the user out by hiding
different parts
of the user interface that we consider to
be superfluous.
Things that we think aren't immediately
relevant to what the user's trying to do.
So unfortunately, a common way that we
might try to add screen real estate
with a web view is to just remove
completely the address bar.
So that the user just gets a full screen
experience
with that one web page that we're
expecting to be displayed.
Now the problem with this is, if malware
is able to go and change or inject a URL
into our web view, for example, let's say
our
app accepts intents that can cause it to
perform different
actions, and one of those happens to be
loading
something into a web view, it's possible
that the
malware can manipulate the URL that we go
to
and because we go to a different URL and
we've
hidden the address bar, there's no way for
our app to realize that the user is going
to be fooled because the user is going to
go and look at this and they're going to
say, hey, I'm at the user name and
password login page that I'm normally see
for
Coursera because they can fake the look
and
feel of the website that they redirect you
to.
But because they can't see this address
bar up
here, they don't know that they've
actually gone somewhere else.
So it's really important when we're
designing user
interfaces to realize that although we
have constraints, on
the screen real estate that's available to
us
in a mobile device and other aspects of
our
interface with the user, it's really
important that
we think through our decisions about what
state we
show the user, so we don't hide state that
they need in order to make relevant
security decisions.
So, for example, if we're hiding the
address of a webview that we're
displaying, and there is the potential
that the URL being fed into that webview
could be changed, it's really important
that we have some other way of indicating
the user, if they are at the webpage that
they think they are at.
Either we have to show them the URL or we
have to display
an error of some type if that web view
goes to another page.
It's very important to display state
relevant
to security decisions that the user might
make.
And even though we have a limited real
estate, not to hide things that
are important for the user to make those
security decisions that they need to make.