[MUSIC]
Welcome
to the next part of the module, which
presents
an overview of key Java synchronization
and scheduling classes.
The concurrent Java program examples
presented in the previous part
produced incorrect results, since they
lacked proper synchronization and
scheduling.
Therefore, this part summarizes the key
Java classes provided by Android to
synchronize access to critical sections
and
schedule interactions among threads and
concurrent programs.
We don't show any Java code in this part.
We just outlined it's key synchronization
and scheduling classes,
and compare and contrast them at a
conceptual level.
Subsequent parts of the module will show
how to program these mechanisms in Java.
Java defines many synchronization and
scheduling
classes, in its Java util concurrent
and Java util concurrent locks packages,
which are described at this link.
We'll cover a subset of these classes,
including a reentrant lock, which
is a mutual exclusion mechanism, that
extend Java's built in monitor lock
capabilities.
Reentrant read write lock, which improves
performance when resources
are read much more often than they're
written to.
Semaphore, which is conceptually a non
negative integer used to control
the access of multiple threads to a
limited number of shared resources.
ConditionObject, which allows threads to
block themselves until some
conditions involving shared state become
true and count down latches,
which allow one or more threads to wait
until
a set of operations being performed in
other threads complete.
Although these 5 classes allow Java
threads
to serialize and coordinate their inner
actions.
They are distinct from the synchronized
keyword and
the wait, notify, and notify all methods
provided
by the built-in monitor object mechanisms
available to
all Java objects, which are described at
this link.
These 5 classes are more fundamental and
flexible, than the
monitor lock and monitor condition
provided by built-in monitor objects.
So we present them first, which has the
added benefit of making it
easier to understand Java's built in
monitor objects, when we cover them later.
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The performance in behavior of the Java
synchronization and scheduling classes
we'll cover in the remainder of this
module, depend on a number of factors.
Such as the implementation of the Java
virtual machine, operating
system, hardware, and the use cases in
which they're applied.
There are various ways of implementing
these classes.
One alternative involves so-called spin
locks, described at this link.
That busy wait, without sleeping, until
the lock is acquired.
Spin locks often use low level hardware
test and set operations to implement
mutual exclusion.
These hardware operations are fast, but
can incur
the overhead of busy waiting, described at
this link.
An alternative is sleep locks, where the
system
puts a thread to sleep, until it may be
able to make progress again, which is
often used
for semaphores and ConditionObjects as
described at this link.
Although this approach doesn't incur busy
waiting overhead, it incurs contact
switching
overhead to put a thread to sleep and wake
it up later on.
Some implementations provide adaptive
locks that spin for a short time, and
then put the thread to sleep, if they
can't acquire the resource quickly.
An excellent presentation on the design
and implementation of
the Java Util concurrent package appears
at this link.
There are other issues to consider when
choosing between
the Java synchronization and scheduling
classes provided by Android.
ReentrantLocks have lower overhead than
ReentrantReadWrite locks.
Since the latter has more complicated
semantics and implementation complexity.
On the other hand, reentrant read-write
locks can
able more parallelism on multicore, or
multiprocessor hardware.
Especially if an object's data is read
much more often than it's written to.
ConditionalObjects and semaphores
generally have more
overhead than reentrant locks and
reentrant read-write
locks because the former [UNKNOWN] sleep
locks
whereas the latter can do spin locks.
On the other hand, ConditionObjects in
semaphores are
much more expressive, since they provide
greater capability.
For example, ReentrantLocks and Reentrant
ReadWriteLocks must
be used in a fully bracketed manner,
where the thread that acquires a lock must
be the one to release it.
In contrast, ConditionObjects and
semaphores allow threads to
coordinate their processing via more
flexible interaction patterns.
For example, threads can use a semaphore
to take turns communicating via a shared
object.
Moreover, ConditionObjects allow threads
to coordinate their interactions via
arbitrarily complex conditions involving
state that's shared by multiple threads.
ConditionObjects have a fundamentally
different
purpose, than ReentrantLocks and
ReentrantReadWriteLocks.
A thread can use these latter two locks to
keep
other threads out of a critical section,
while performing its computations.
Conversely, a thread uses a
ConditionObject
to keep itself out of the critical
section, until it can make forward
progress, when changes to shared state
occur.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC].
In summary, all the Java synchronization
and scheduling classes outlined in
this video appear throughout the
Android infrastructure, framework and
application software.
Including many examples we cover in this
MOOC.
So it helps to know something about them
when you examine
the Android open source code base, which
is available at this link.
There's several reasons why concurrent
programs use these classes.
One reason is to protect the objects and
resources shared by multiple threads from
race conditions that would otherwise
corrupt them,
if they were accessed and updated
simultaneously.
Another reason is to schedule and control
the order in which threads execute.
[BLANK_AUDIO].
The importance of these mechanisms is
reflected in the
amount of time we devote to them in this
module.
Which is roughly an order of magnitude
longer
than we devoted to Java threading
mechanisms themselves.
The reason for this additional focus, is
that complexity
in concurrent programs, as in life, often
stems from
trying to coordinate multiple
interdependent entities working together,
rather
than the behavior of individual entities
working in isolation.
For each class covering the next 5 videos,
we'll first summarize
the general concept, outline an analogous
humanoid use of the concept
to make it easier to remember what it
does, and then
share how the class is implemented and
applied in the Android.
Therefore, even if you're already familiar
with
the Java synchronization and scheduling
classes, you
may learn something new about how they're
implemented and used in the Android
environment.
[MUSIC]