[MUSIC].
Welcome to the next part of the module,
which
covers the Java CountDownLatch class that
implements barrier synchronization.
This part provides a conceptual overview
of barrier synchronization, explains how
the Java CountDownLatch class implements
these concepts to enable one or
more threads to wait until a set of
operations being performed
in other threads completes, and shows how
CountDownLatches are applied in Android.
A barrier is a synchronization technique
that halts the
progress of one or more threads at a
particular point.
No thread can proceed until all other
threads
reach this barrier, as described at this
link.
Barriers are commonly used in several
ways.
One way is to defer the start of
current computations until after an object
has been initialized.
For example, the main thread of an
application
that coverts a video from ABC HD format
into
MP4 format might spawn four threads to run
different parts of the conversion
computations on different cores.
An initialization done barrier, created
with a count of one, can be used to defer
the start of these threads until the main
thread has finished initializing its
internal data structures.
When initialization is finished, the main
thread decrements the count
to zero and all the threads can begin
their conversions concurrently.
Another common use is to allow one thread
to wait until a group
of other concurrent threads are done with
their processing before it can continue.
For example, the main thread in our video
format
conversion application can use a
conversion done barrier, created with
a count of four, to wait until all the
threads finish their conversions before
continuing with its other work.
As each thread finishes, the barrier count
is decremented by one.
When the count reaches zero, the main
thread can continue.
A human known use of barrier
synchronization is the protocol used by
a tour guide, described at this link, who
waits until all the
tourists have arrived before starting
their tour, and who also waits until
all the tourists have finished the tour
before continuing with their other work.
[MUSIC].
Java provides barrier synchronization via
its CountDownLatch class,
which allows one or more threads to wait
until a set of operations being performed
in
other threads have completed, as described
at this link.
Most of its implementation is written in
Java, as shown at this pathname.
CountDownLatch uses the gang of four
bridge pattern, described at this
link, to inherit the bulk of
it's functionality from the
AbstractQueuedSynchronizer class.
Which provides a framework for
implementing
blocking locks and synchronizers that rely
on
first in, first out, or FIFO wait queues,
as described at this link.
The constructor initializes CountDownLatch
with a given count.
Once this count is set, it can't
be reset without creating a new
CountDownLatch instance.
An alternative is to use a Java
CyclicBarrier, which is cyclic because
it can be reused by resetting the count
after waiting threads are released.
CyclicBarrier is useful for programs with
a fixed size number
of threads that wait for each other, as
described this link.
The key methods in CountDownLatch are
await and countdown.
Await causes the calling thread to wait
until the latch's count reaches zero.
CountDown decrements the count of the
latch, releasing
all the waiting threads if the count
reaches zero.
A CountDownLatch doesn't require that
threads calling countDown
wait for the count to reach zero before
proceeding, it simply prevents any thread
from proceeding
past an await call until all threads can
pass.
[MUSIC].
To show how Java CountDownLatches are used
in Android, we'll analyze its Contacts
Provider,
which is a source of data for a device's
contacts application, shown at this link.
The Contacts Provider is implemented by
the ContactsProvider2 class, which extends
AbstractContactsProvider that, in turn,
extends Content
Provider, as shown at this pathname.
We don't analyze every detail of this
code, just
the parts we need to explain how the
CountDownLatches work.
A Content Provider is a core Android
component that manages access
to a central repository of structured
data, as described at this link.
The Contacts Provider presents its data to
applications by a standard Content
Provider methods,
such as insert, query, update, and delete,
which internally accesses multiple SQLite
database tables.
A pair of CountDownLatches are used to
defer read
and write operations until the Contacts
Provider is properly initialized.
The Contacts Provider onCreate entry point
method calls its internal initialize
method.
Initialize starts a background thread.
It initializes the SQLite database by
importing the legacy
contacts, updating accounts, locale, and
search information, et cetera.
These time consuming tasks continue to run
concurrently, even after initialize and
onCreate have returned.
So, Contacts Provider methods, such as
query and
insert, must not be allowed to read from
or write to the database, since it's state
will be inconsistent until the background
initialization tasks finish.
To ensure consistency and optimize
performance, two CountDownLatches, each
initialized
with a count of one, prevent database
access during initialization.
Splitting the CountDownLatches into read
and write
access optimizes performance, since
read-only methods on the
Contacts Provider can be processed as soon
as that portion of the database is
initialized.
For example, any calls to query, block
until the Read Access Latch count equals
zero.
Likewise, any calls to insert, block until
the Write Access Latch count equals zero.
All these Contacts Provider methods call
the
private waitForAccess method, which calls
a wait
on its CountDownLatch parameter to block
the
caller until the designated initialization
is complete.
As initialization tasks running
concurrently
in the background thread complete, the
performBackgroundTask method calls
countDown on the
appropriate Read and Write Access Latches.
Which unblock any methods that read from
or write to the Contacts
Provider, so they can proceed and compete
for the database transaction monitor.
[MUSIC].
In summary, a Java CountDownLatch provides
a versatile barrier
synchronization tool that can be used for
several purposes.
If it's initialized with a count of one,
it serves as a simple on-off latch.
For example, in our earlier video
conversion example, all four threads that
evoke
await, block on the initialization done
latch until the main thread invokes
countDown.
If it's initialized to N, it can make one
thread wait until N
threads have completed some action or some
action has been completed N times.
For example, the main thread in the video
conversion
example waits until all the worker threads
are finished.
At which point, it returns to it's caller.
ACountDownLatch supports several types of
await operations,
including an await that causes the current
thread
to wait until the latch is counted is down
to zero, unless the thread is interrupted.
Or, a time to wait that blocks until the
specified waiting time elapses.
CountDownLatch is used throughout Android,
both in its
frameworks and in its common applications
and providers.
[MUSIC]