[MUSIC].
Welcome to the next
part of the module, which covers the Java
ConditionObject class.
This part provides a conceptual overview
of condition variables.
Explains how the Java conditionobject
class implements
these concept, to enable user-defined Java
objects
to have multiple weight sets per object,
and shows how conditionobjects are applied
in Android.
A condition variable is a synchronization
and scheduling mechanism,
that's commonly used to implement the
guarded suspension pattern.
Which requires both the acquisition of a
lock and the satisfaction of
a condition before an operation can be
executed, as described at this link.
A thread can suspend itself on a condition
variable until another thread notifies it,
that a
condition involving shared state it's
waiting on, may
now be true, as described at this link.
This condition can be arbitrarily complex.
So a lock must therefore be associated
with a condition variable to protect
the shared state and the condition from
being corrupted by other concurrently
running threads.
When a thread waits on a condition
variable,
the lock associated with it is released,
and
the thread is suspended atomically until
the condition
is satisfied, in accordance with a guarded
suspension pattern.
When another thread signals the condition
variable, and the thread
scheduler wakes up the waiting thread, the
lock is reacquired
implicitly, and the code running in the
reawakened thread checks
to see if the shared state has satisfied
its designated condition.
If the condition is satisfied, it's
processing can continue.
If not, it suspends itself by waiting on
the condition variable again and releases
the lock atomically.
Conditions variables form the basis
scheduling
synchronization methods in Java and
Android.
For example, classes in the
Java.util.concurrent
package use Java's implementation of
condition
variables called conditionobjects, to
allow multiple
threads to put and take messages from
synchronized queues and deques correctly
and
efficiently, as shown in this diagram of
the ArrayBlockingQueue class, described at
this
link and analyzed later in this video.
Condition variables are also instrumental
in Java built-in monitor
objects, described in an upcoming video in
this module.
And the monitor object pattern, which is
described in a pair of upcoming videos.
Condition variables are a powerful
synchronization and scheduling mechanism.
But they have a lot of moving parts, which
can make them hard to understand and apply
properly.
So you may want to watch this video
multiple times and read the
links shown at the bottom of the
slides carefully to fully understand these
concepts.
[MUSIC]
A human known use of condition variables
is shown in the pictures on this slide.
Imagine that you and several of your
friends take a second
or third job to make some extra money by
delivering pizzas, which
is a growth industry, since in many places
people eat pizza
when times are good, and they eat pizzas
when times are bad.
So you and your friends deliver pizzas
using a protocol that synchronizes and
schedules the accessed, the limited number
of
pizza delivery vehicles and pizzas to
deliver.
To make a delivery, you need two
resources, the
pizza and the keys to a pizza delivery
vehicle.
However, if you only get the pizza or you
only get the keys, you
can't make your deliveries, so you and
your friends wait in the kitchen sleeping,
since
this is your second or third job, until
both conditions become true; The cooks
are done with the pizza and the keys to a
pizza delivery vehicle are available.
When cooks finish a pizza, they ring a
bell.
Likewise, when someone returns from
delivering a pizza, they
put the keys on a hook and ring a bell.
These bells notify all sleepers that
conditions have changed.
They then wake up and try to get both the
pizza and
the keys, which must be acquired in the
same order, to avoid deadlock.
If someone only gets one resource, just
the pizza, or just the keys, they must
release it and go back to sleep until
they're reawakening, the next time a bell
rings.
This whimsical example shows how condition
variables can be used to wait for
various conditions to become true and
coordinate the activities of multiple
interdependent entities
[MUSIC].
Java provides condition variables by
its conditionobject class, which
implements the
conditional phase within the abstract
queued
synchronized class, described at this
link.
Android also provides a non-standard
condition
variable class, described at this link,
which implements the condition variable
concept,
though the semantics are somewhat
different.
So we'll focus on conditionobjects in this
video.
Conditionobject is mostly implemented in
Java, as shown at this path name.
The key methods in a conditionobject are a
wait, signal, and signal all, which are
named
to align with the wait, notify, and notify
all methods provided by Java's built-in
monitor objects.
Through they're implementations differ, as
we'll cover later on in the module.
Internally, a conditionobject uses various
cues that
enable threads to coordinate their
interacts by
waiting and signaling each other when
changes
occur to states shared by the threads.
To ensure that this shared state is
protected from race conditions, a
conditionobject is
always used with a lock, such as
the Java reentrantrock discussed in an
earlier video.
In fact, reentrantlocks have a new
condition method.
That returns a conditionobject instance
that can be
used with a reentrantlock as shown at this
link.
User-defined Java objects can have
multiple conditionobjects per object.
In contrast, Java's built-in monitor
objects
only allow a single monitor condition
per object, which is more restrictive and
can lead to problems like
nested monitor lockout, as described in
this link and covered in this
video on Java built-in monitor objects, in
a later part of this module.
[MUSIC].
To show how conditionobjects are used in
Android, we'll
analyze an implementation of array
breaking blocking queue.
Which is a block bandit cue that stores
its elements in
first in, first out or FIFO order, as
described at this link.
Arrayblockingqueue extend abstract queue
and implements blocking
queue; as shown at this path name.
We don't analyze every detail of this
code, just
the parts we need to explain how
conditionobjects work.
This discussion extends our earlier video,
showing how arrayblockingqueue applies to
reentrantlocks.
Arrayblockingqueue is implemented as a
dynamically sized array.
Some relevant data members include the
array
of queued items and the indinsies used to
keep track of the were the next put or
take item occurs in the items array.
Just as Java's reentrantlock class can
replace the
use of Java's built-in synchronized
methods and blocks.
A conditionobject can replace the use of
built-in Java
monitor object methods, such as wait and
notify all.
For example, arrayblockingqueue's
implementation has
a reentrant lock to serialize
access to its state, as well as two
conditionobjects, not
empty and not full, that allow its take
and put
methods to block when the queue is empty
and full, respectively.
The arrayblockingqueue constructor
initializes these data
members using the reentrantlocks new
condition
method to associate the not empty and not
full conditionobjects with the lock.
[MUSIC].
Arrayblockingqueue uses reentrantlocks and
conditionobjects to implement the
monitor object pattern, described at this
link and discussed later in this module.
This diagram shows the structure of the
arrayblockingqueue monitor object,
which we'll use to visualize the analysis
of its code.
This implementation of monitor object
differs from Java's built-in monitor
objects.
Because it creates an explicit
reentrantlock
and multiple conditionobjects, rather than
using
the implicit monitor lock and single
monitor condition provided by built-in
monitor objects.
Although we focus on the
arrayblockingqueue here, these steps are
applicable to the monitor object pattern
and conditionobjects in general.
Assume thread T1 calls take to remove the
first element in a
new instance of arrayblockingqueue, which
will block, since the queue is empty.
When take is called, it acquires the
reentrantlock, if no other thread
owns it, and starts to run in the monitor
objects critical section.
Where it will determine that the count is
zero and so must wait on the not
empty conditionobject, which atomically
releases a lock and
puts thread T1 to sleep on the
conditionobject.
Assume now that the second thread, T2
creates
a new string and calls put on the
arrayblockingqueue.
Since T1 released a lock when it went to
sleep on the not empty conditionobject,
when thread T2 calls put, it acquires a
lock and runs in the monitor object.
Where it determines the queue isn't full,
and this
we'll call insert, which adds the new
element to the
tail of the items array and signals the
not empty
conditionobject to indicate that the queue
is no longer empty.
When insert returns, the put method
releases
a lock and leaves the monitors critical
section.
At this point, thread T1 is reawakened
from its wait on the not empty
conditionobject in take method, acquires a
lock
and continues running in the take method.
Where it determines that the queue is no
longer empty and calls the extract method.
Extract removes the head element, in the
items
array, signals any threads waiting on the
not full
conditionobject to indicate the queue is
no longer full,
and returns the element back to the take
method.
Which then releases a lock and leaves the
monitor object.
[MUSIC].
In summary, a Java conditionobject
provides a flexible synchronization
and scheduling mechanism that allows a
thread to suspend
its execution until it's notified by
another thread that
some shared state it's waiting on may now
be true.
Unlike built-in Java monitor objects,
which can only have one
wait queue, a user-defined Java object can
create multiple conditionobjects.
A conditionobject is always used in
conjunction with a lock, such as a
reentrantlock, to ensure state share by
multiple threads is protected from race
conditions.
A conditionobject supports several type of
wait
operations, including interruptible,
non-interruptible, and timed waits.
A call to wait should almost always be
invoked inside of a
loop that tests for the condition being
waited on, for several reasons.
First, a loop is needed since a waiting
thread can't assume that
a notification it received was for the
particular state condition it's waiting
on, or that the condition is still true,
due to the non-deterministic
operations of other threads accessing a
conditionobject concurrently, as describe
at this link.
Second, it needs to guard against spurious
wake ups, that occur due
to quirks of multi-processor or multi-core
systems, as described at this link.
Although conditionobjects aren't used much
in Android application software, they are
used in the underlying
Java.util.concurrent
package, shown at this path name,
unless they're used by extension
in Android's concurrency frameworks, which
use
Java.util.concurrent heavily, as we'll
cover in the next module in this section.
[MUSIC]