[MUSIC]
Welcome to the next part of the
module, which covers the Java
ReentrantReadWriteLock class.
This part provides a conceptual overview
of readers-writer
locks, explains how the Reentrant
read-write class implements these
concepts to provide readers-writer lock
semantics to concurrent Java
programs, and shows how
ReentrantReadWriteLocks are applied in
Android.
A readers-writer lock is a synchronization
mechanism often used in situations
where many threads concurrently access the
same shared resource at one time.
Some reading, and some writing, with a
constraint that no thread may access the
resource
for reading or writing while another
thread is in the act of writing to it.
As described at this link.
It allows access to a shared resource
either by multiple threads
that have read only access or one thread
that has write access.
Readers-writer locks may help improve
performance when resources
are read much more often than written,
especially
on multi-core and multiprocessor platforms
that can perform
many computations in parallel, as
described at this link.
A loosely analogous human known use of
readers-writer locking is the protocol
followed in
formal political debates, such as the
United
States presidential debates described at
this link.
Where only one person, the writer, is
allowed
to speak at a time, at least in theory.
However, everyone in the audience, the
readers,
can listen to what the speaker is saying.
Likewise, audience members can ask
questions, thus
becoming writers for the duration of their
questions.
[MUSIC].
Java provides readers-writer locks, via
it's ReentrantReadWriteLock class.
Which implements the ReadWriteLock
interface, as described at this link.
Most of it's implementation is written in
Java.
As shown at this path name, reentrant
reader writeer lock,
contains two instances of inner classes,
reader lock, and writer lock.
That implement the read and write lock
behaviors respectively.
This diagram shows how multiple reader
threads
can acquire the reader lock and execute
concurrently.
Where as this diagram, shows how just one
writer
can acquire the WriteLock and one at a
time.
ReentrantReadWriteLock uses the
Gang-of-Four Bridge
pattern, described at this link.
For several purposes.
First, inherits the bulk of its
functionality
from the AbstractQueuedSynchronizer class
described at this link.
Which provides a framework for
implementing, blocking locks and
synchronizers that rely on first-in,
first-out, or FIFO wait queues.
Second, it implements a fair or non-fair
lock acquisition order model via a common
interface.
Its constructor selects the designated
model based on the fair
parameter, similar to the ReentrantLock
presented earlier in this video.
Its constructor also initializes the
readerLock and
writerLock data members that implement the
lock
interface, and thus support the standard
and unlock methods covered in the
ReentrantLock video.
The key methods in reentrant reader writer
lock or the readLock and writeLock
accessor methods that return the
underlined readerLock
and writerLock objects initialized in its
constructor.
Which are used to acquire the lock for
reading and writing respectively.
[MUSIC].
To show how a Java ReentrantReadWriteLock
is
used in Android, we'll analyze an example
from
the BluetoothSocket class, which manages a
connection to
a Bluetooth device, as described at this
link.
BluetoothSocket implements the closable
interface, as shown at this path name.
We don't analyze every detail of this
code, just
the parts we need to explain how
ReentrantReadWriteLock's work.
BluetoothSockets constructor creates a
ReentrantReadWriteLock and
stores it in the nLock data member.
The BluetoothSocket close method releases
any system resources it holds.
Although only the first call to close has
any effect, it's
safe to call close multiple times
concurrently on the same object.
When close runs, it first acquires a
readLock on nLock,.
Execute some operations that examine the
state of
the socket and returns if it's already
closed.
Unlocking the readLock as it returns.
If the sockets not already closed,
close acquires a writeLock, sets the
BluetoothSocket
state to closed, releases the resources,
and unlocks the writeLock as it returns.
Multiple threads can acquire mLock for
reading at the same time.
But only one thread at a time can acquire
mLock for writing, thereby ensuring
readers writers lock semantics.
[MUSIC].
In summary, a Java ReentrantReadWriteLock
allows greater concurrency
when accessing shared data than a
ReentrantLock, as discussed at this link.
ReentrantReadWriteLock exploits the fact
that while only a single
writer thread can modify the shared data
at a time.
Often any number of reader threads can
concurrently examine the data.
However, speedups from
ReentrantReadWriteLock will only be
fully realized on a multi-core or
multi-processor system.
And then only if the access patterns for
shared data are suitable.
Profiling and measurement can be used to
determine if
a ReentrantReadWriteLock is suitable for a
particular use case.
This link presents a pattern language for
selecting among various locking primitives
for concurrent programs.
In addition to the acquisition order
fairness
policy, discussed earlier in this video,
Java
ReentrantReadWriteLock's also support
recursive lock semantics, lock
downgrading from a writeLock to a
readLock.
An interruption of lock acquisition.
Finding a compelling use case for
ReentrantReadWriteLock
is hard in Android, where they're used
sparingly.
Clearly, optimizing the performance of the
BluetoothSocket
closed method doesn't do justice to a
ReentrandReadWriteLock.
And it's power as a
scalable synchronization mechanism for
parallel processing.
Further discussion of
ReentrantReadWriteLock's and their
broader applicability appears at this
link.
[MUSIC]