[MUSIC].
Welcome
to the next part of the module, which
covers Java built-in monitor objects.
These mechanisms can be used to
synchronize and schedule
the interaction of multiple threads, in a
concurrent program.
This part motivates the need for built-in
monitor objects, by fixing the
simple, but Buggy concurrent program,
shown in the earlier part of the module.
This program contained two threads.
A producer and a consumer, that incurred
race conditions,
when calling the put and take methods of
Buggy Queue.
To fix the problems with the Buggy Queue.
We use a Java built-in monitor object,
that enables the threads
to communicate, by passing messages,
via a properly synchronized SimpleBlocking
Queue.
A monitor is a classic concurrency control
mechanism,
that can be used to coordinate
synchronization scheduling.
Of multiple threads, that access and
interact in
a critical section, as described at this
link.
In particular, a monitor allows threads to
have both mutual exclusion, and,
the ability to block, while waiting for
certain conditions to become true.
Monitors also have a mechanism for
notifying other threads, the conditions
they're
waiting on have been met, so the other
threads can continue their processing
accordingly.
[MUSIC].
Before we show the complete Java built-in
monitor object solution, we outline
a partial solution to the race condition
problems with the original Buggy Queue.
This solution, called Buggy Synchronized
Queue,
uses Java synchronized methods, to specify
sections
of the code in an object, that can't be
accessed concurrently by multiple threads.
In particular, allow the Java synchronized
keyword,
to the Buggy Queue's put and take methods.
Which has two effects.
First, it's not possible for two
indications of
put and take on the same object to
interleave.
When one thread is executing a
synchronized put method on an
object, all other threads that invoke
synchronized methods for the same object.
Will block, until the first thread is done
with the object.
Second, when a synchronized method exits,
it automatically establishes a
happens-before relationship,
with any subsequent invocation, of a
synchronized method for the same object.
Which insures that changes to the state of
the object, are visible to all threats.
This link provides more information on the
syntax and semantics of Java synchronized
methods.
Although using synchronized insures that
put and take
critical sections can't be access
concurrently by multiple threads.
There are still some problems with this
solution.
For example, the take method will waste
CPU
cycles by spinning in a busy way, throwing
the index out of bounds exception,
whenever the
remove method is called in an empty array
list.
Likewise, the put method, could continue
adding new messages
to the array list, until heat memory is
exhausted.
This link provides more information on
busy
waiting, and outlines some solutions to
the problem.
One of which is addressed by Java built-in
monitor objects, which we'll cover next.
[MUSIC]
All objects in Java can be used as
built-in monitor
objects, which support two types of thread
synchronization and scheduling.
Mutual exclusion, and cooperation, as
described at this link.
Mutual exclusion enables multiple threads
to access
and update shared data without race
conditions.
It's supported in the Java Virtual
Machine,
by an object's entrance cue and
synchronized methods.
Cooperation enables threads to coordinate
and schedule interactions.
It's supported in the Java Virtual
Machine,
via an object's wait queue, and
notification mechanisms.
These mechanisms implement a variant of
the monitor object
pattern, described at this link, and
covered in upcoming videos.
This pattern ensures that only one method
runs within an object,
and allows an objects methods
to cooperatively schedule their execution
sequences.
Well applied Java's built-in monitor
objects to implement a
better solution, to the Buggy synchronized
queue shown earlier.
In particular, this solution, which is
called
Simple Blocking Queue, improves upon buggy
queue.
By preventing erase conditions from
occurring, when put
and take methods are called concurrently
by multiple threads.
It also improves upon Buggy synchronized
queue,
by preventing busy waiting from wasting
CPU cycles.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC].
To make simple blocking queue a monitor
object, we'll first add the synchronized
keyword to its put and take methods,
following the approach described in this
link.
Although this is not the complete
solution, it's the starting point
to ensure access to the queue's put and
take methods is serialized.
Similar to the axis protocol, for an
airplane restroom, discussed in an earlier
video.
Java also supports synchronized
statements,
often called synchronized blocks, which
acquire and release a lock, within the
scope of a statement.
In the synchronized statement example on
this slide, the
lock is a simple block and queue object
itself.
Which is the intrinsic lock, that's
associated with every Java object.
Although programming synchronized blocks
requires more effort
than programming synchronized methods,
they can enhance
concurrency by enabling fine grain
serialization, that
minimizes the scope over which locks are
held.
For example, in this implementation of
put, the entire synchronized method is
serialized.
Whereas in this implementation, only the
synchronized
statement is serialized using the
intrinsic lock.
Likewise, it's possible for a synchronized
statement to use an explicit lock object.
That's different from an object's
intrinsic lock.
Which provides further opportunities for
fine grain serialization.
This link has more information on
intrinsic locks,
explicit locks, synchronized methods, and
synchronized statements in Java.
[MUSIC]
As discussed earlier, synchronized methods
and
statements are only a partial solution.
Therefore, Java's built-in monitor
objects, also provide waiting and
notification mechanisms, that help threads
cooperatively schedule their interactions.
Each built-in monitor object inherits the
weight, notify and
notify all methods from the Java Object
Class, which are
similar to the weight, signal and signal
all methods,
defined by Java Condition Objects,
described in this earlier video.
Each Java monitor object has one wait
queue and one entrance queue.
All calls to wait are done in a wait
queue, and
all notify and notify all calls, also
apply to this queue.
Having only one wait queue in a built-in
monitor object, is more restrictive than
programming the Java
condition objects, which allow an object
to have
multiple wait queues, as shown in this
earlier video.
Some consequences of this restriction,
will be discussed in this video's summary.
Android's Java virtual machine implements
built-in
monitor object synchronizers, via POSIX
mechanisms.
For example, an entrance queue is
implemented as
a POSIX mutual exclusion, or mutex lock,
augmented
to support recursive locking semantics,
which protect shared
data from race conditions, as described at
this link.
A wait queue is implemented as a POSIX
condition variable.
Which allows one or more threads, to block
on the wait queue of
an monitor object, until some conditions
become true, as described at this link.
POSIX condition variables are conceptually
similar
to Java condition objects, discussed in
our
earlier video, though their
implementations differ,
since they're written in different
programming languages.
For example, condition objects are written
largely in Java, and POXIS
condition variables are written in C, as
shown in these path
notes.
[MUSIC].
Now that we've provided an overview of
Java built-in monitor objects.
We've visually analyzed their behavior, in
the
context of our simple block and queue
example.
As shown in this diagram, each Java
monitor object
has one entrance queue, associated with
its monitor lock.
And one wait queue, associated with its
implicit monitor condition, as described
at this link.
When thread T1 calls take on an empty
simple blocking queue, it enters the
monitor object.
Assuming though the thread is active
inside the monitor object.
Key one acquires a monitor lock.
And starts to run the code in Buggy
synchronized queues critical section.
Where it will determined that the
underline array list mQ is empty.
As long the mQ list is empty, key one will
wait, on the monitor condition.
Calling wait on the monitor condition
atomicaly releases the monitor lock.
And blocks the current thread, until a
call to
notify or notify all is made on the same
object.
In the context of our concurrent
producer-consumer example,
assume that thread T2 calls put on simple
blocking
queue, while thread T1 is blocked on its
monitor
condition, causing T2 to end with the
monitor object.
Acquire the monitor lock, add the message
to the
mQ list [INAUDIBLE] notify all to wake up
any
null threads waiting on the monitor
condition, and then
release the monitor lock, and exit the
monitor object.
At this point, thread T1 will be unblocked
from the monitor condition.
We acquire the monitor lock, and remove
and return the first item in the mQ
array list, which will cause T1 to release
the monitor lock, and leave the monitor
object.
[MUSIC]
Now that we've examined the behavior of a
monitor object
visually, we'll show some simple blocking
Q Java code.
And discuss several implementation
considerations.
Within a synchronized method, a thread can
wait for a
condition to become true, using the
guarded suspension pattern, described at
this link, which requires both a lock to
be acquired, and
a condition to be satisfied before an
operation can be executed.
For example, the synchronized take method
implicitly acquires the monitor lock.
Checks the array list mQ size, and blocks
if it's empty.
A call to wait should almost always be
invoked inside
of a loop, that tests for the condition
being waited on.
A loop is needed since a waiting
thread can't assume that a notification it
received.
Was for the particular condition it's
waiting on.
It also can't assume the condition is even
still true, due to the non-deterministic
operations of other threads, accessing the
monitor
object concurrently, as described at this
link.
A thread blocking on wait, won't continue,
until another
thread notifies it, that the condition may
be true.
For example, I take call block because the
array list mQ is empty.
Won't wake up, until put notifies it that
there's a message to process.
When a thread blocked on wait is notified,
it wakes up, obtains
the monitor lock, and checks to see if the
condition has been satisfied.
If so, it exits the loop, and continues
processing the code and the method.
When it's done, it releases the monitor
lock.
And leaves the monitored object, for
example, when a
block take call is awaken after put calls
notify all.
It checkes to make sure that mQ array list
is no longer empty, and then
removes and returns the first item in the
list; as it leaves the monitor's critical
section.
[MUSIC].
In summary, any Java object may be used as
a built-in monitor object, by marking its
methods with
the synchronized key word, or marking
portions of its
code as synchronized statements as
described at this link.
Although these synchronized methods can
help, they're only a partial solution.
Since they don't address problems with
busy waiting.
Therefore, Java built-in monitor objects
also provide waiting and notification
mechanisms.
Although Java built-in monitor objects are
relatively simple, they have some
subtleties and limitations, such as nested
monitor lockout, which occurs when
a first thread, acquires a nested object's
monitor lock, without relinquishing
the monitor lock, already held by the
object containing the nested object.
Thereby preventing a second thread, from
acquiring the containing object's monitor
lock.
This link describes the nested monitor
lockout problem, and
outlines problems, that can be applied to
remedy it.
There are also some subtleties, related to
the
wait queue, associated with the Java
built-in monitor object.
Which supports both notify, and notify all
methods.
Notify wakes up a single thread waiting on
the monitor condition.
Whereas notify all, wakes up all threads
waiting on the condition.
This link describes how to choose which
method to use.
There are situations where a program, may
need to tightly control
the order in which threads are unblocked,
when a condition changes.
Rather than relying on the arbitrary
built-in
semantics, of Java's built-in monitor
notification mechanism.
This link describes a pattern for
explicitly designating which thread should
proceed.
Yet another limitation with Java built-in
monitor objects, is
that they lack certain useful features,
provided by reentrant locks.
For example, there's no equivalent to
tryLock.
Or lock interuptedly on a built-in monitor
object.
Which is one reason why Android and the
java.util.concurrent package, often use
reentrant locks, instead of built-in Java
monitor objects, for their synchronization
needs.
Although Java monitor objects are
relatively
easy to use for simple concurrent
programs.
It's often the case that production
software
may need more than Java's built-in monitor
objects.
This link provides more information on the
broader range of
synchronization and scheduling mechanisms,
in
the java.util.concurrent and
java.util.concurrent.locks package.
It's also common for Android applications
to use its
concurrency frameworks, than to use Java
built-in monitors objects directly.
These frameworks implement a broader range
of concurrency, patterns and
mechanisms, as summarized at this link,
and described later in this section.
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]