[MUSIC].
Welcome to the next part of the module,
which presents an example that shows how
the Java
concurrency mechanisms covered earlier,
can be used to
synchronize and schedule the behavior, of
a multithreaded program.
Although previous part of this module,
have shown how Java
synchronization and scheduling classes are
used in production Android software.
These examples have just shown, snippets
of code.
Therefore, this part analyses the design
of,a pattern oriented framework.
That's then customized and implemented in
the next part, to create two
Java threads that alternate between
printing
Ping, and Pong on the computer Console.
[BLANK_AUDIO].
The Ping-Pong program presented earlier,
lacked proper concurrency control, so
it's [UNKNOWN] was incorrect, in contrast,
the example we analysed
now works correctly, since it coordinates
thread interactions by a
Java synchronise, such as Semaphores,
condition objects and countdown latches.
In addition to outlining the
object-oriented
design of this synchronized Ping-Pong
program,
this part shows how the application of
Gang of Four patterns, such
as template method strategy, and factor
method provide several benefits, in
particular,
these patterns make the framework and
the resulting Ping-Pong program, more
reusable.
Flexible and portable.
Although we focus on a Java Console
application again, this
framework makes it easy to port our
solution in Android.
After we discuss the User Interface
Threading model, later in this
section.
[MUSIC].
The Ping-Pong Program, is structured using
an object-oriented design.
Consisting of a number of classes
associated with each other, by
inheritance and containment relationships,
as shown in this UML class diagram.
This UML sequence diagram, depicts the
flow of
control between the key classes in the
program.
The main entry point method, creates and
starts
a thread, that's passed an instance of the
Ping-Pong
run and play implementation, the run hook
method of
play Ping-Pong, creates and starts two
Ping-Pong thread objects.
The run hook methods in these objects are
template methods,
that implement the Ping-Pong algorithm
concurrently, using a pair of
synchronizer.
Which can either be Java semaphore or
condition objects.
This synchronizer control the order which
the threads alternate
printing Ping and Pong, via the configured
platform strategy.
Which factors out all of the platform
dependent output.
And synchronization operations, so that
the Play Ping-Pong
code will execute without change, in
multiple runtime environments.
It also contains a CountDownLatch, that's
used to
wait for the two Ping-Pong threads to
exit.
Extending this program is relatively
straight
forward, since it's based on a framework,
who's design is guided by several Gang of
Four patterns, as discussed next.
[MUSIC].
Before analyzing the implementation of the
object-oriented framework and
application code, for the concurrent
Ping-Pong program in detail.
We'll outline it's pattern oriented
software architecture.
Which applies three Gang of Four patterns
to guide the design of it's classes.
And enhance certain software quality
attributes.
For example, we want our solution to
maximize systematic software reuse, which
involves intentionally creating or
requiring reusable
assets, and then consistently using and
evolving
them, to obtain a high degree of reuse,
thereby optimizing the ability to
produce quality software products, rapidly
and
effectively, as discussed in an earlier
video.
To achieve this attribute, we used the
Template Method pattern.
Which provides a skeleton of an algorithm
in a method,
deferring some steps to sub classes, as
described in this link.
The Ping-Pong program applies this
pattern, to implement
the Ping-Pong algorithm once in the run
template method.
Defining the Ping-Pong thread base class,
shown on this slide.
Sub classes that acquire the over lease
and hook methods, which
play the role of primitive operations in
the Template Method pattern.
These methods alternate the printing of,
Ping and Pong.
Via different synchronization and
scheduling mechanisms.
Such as the Ping-Pong thread sema sub
class, that
uses Java Semaphores as discussed in the
next video.
This pattern maximizes algorithm reuse, in
the Ping-Pong threads run method.
While making it easy to change policies
and mechanisms.
Such as replacing the use of semaphores
with condition objects, and
supporting more sophisticated alternation
behavior, without
changing the underlying, Ping-Pong
algorithm itself.
Also shown in the next video.
[MUSIC].
Another
software quality attribute, we want to
maximize
in our object-oriented Ping-Pong Program
design, is portability.
Which enables the same implementation to
be applied, in different operating
environments.
Thereby increasing the potential userbase,
and
market size, as described at this link.
To achieve this attribute, we use the
strategy pattern, which defines a family
of
algorithms, encapsulates each one, and
makes them
interchangeable, to let clients and
algorithms vary independently.
As described at this link.
The Ping-Pong Program applies this
pattern, to define a platform strategy
class hierarchy, that factors out
different ways of printing Ping and Pong.
And coordinating the completion of
printing operations, on different runtime
platforms.
Such as a Java Console application.
Versus an Android application, for
example, the platform
strategy begin method initializes the
count down latch
to account for two threats, this method
work
the same on both Console, and Android
applications.
Conversely, the console platform strategy
print() method calls the Java system
println() method, which writes the output
string to the Console window.
In contrast, the Android platform strategy
print
method, creates a runable, who's run hook
method.
Write the string, to a text view, and then
cues
this run able, on the User Interface
Threads looper cue.
Since Android, only allows the User
Interface Thread, to write to the display.
Likewise, the platform strategy done
method, is implemented
differently in an Android application
versus a Console application.
Though the count down latch, count down
method is used on both platforms.
The await done method implementation is
the
same on both platforms, simply forwarding
to
the countdown latch wait method, to
perform
barrier synchronization as described in
this earlier video.
[MUSIC].
Yet another software quality attribute, we
want to maximize, is flexibility.
Which enables designs, to adapt more
readily in response to internal
or external changes in requirements or
environments, as described at this link.
To achieve this quality attribute, we
apply the factory
method pattern, which provides an
interface, for creating an object.
But leaves the choice of the objects
concrete type
to a sub class, as described in this link.
The Ping-Pong program applies this pattern
in several ways.
For example, a variant to this pattern is
used in the make
Ping-Pong threads factory method, that
creates
the appropriate sub class, of Ping-Pong
Thread.
Depending on a runtime option, that can be
configured
by the user, a simifour based Ping-Pong
Thread object.
Or, a condition object based Ping-Pong
thread
object is created, without affecting the
implementation, of
the play Ping-Pong algorithm, that uses
the object
return, by the make Ping-Pong Threads
factory method.
The Ping-Pong program also applies this
pattern.
To the platform strategy factory, that
creates the
appropriate instance, of the platform
strategy sub class.
In particular, depending on the settings,
of the Java specification
vendor system property, the make platform
strategy factory method, in Console
platform strategy, in Android platform
strategy, either create an instance
of the Android platform strategy, or the
Console platform strategy, respectively.
In addition to enhancing flexibility, the
Factory
Method Pattern enhances systematic reuse,
and portability.
By enabling the family of Ping-Pong
programs, to vary
transparently, and run on different
platforms, without requiring any changes.
To the rest of the framework, or
application code.
[MUSIC].
In summary, this video analysed the design
of a pattern oriented framework,
that can support a family, of related
concurrent Ping-Pong programs.
In the next video, we'll customize this
framework,
with several different Java synchronizers,
and use it
to implement two Java threads, that
correctly alternate
printing Ping and Pong to the computer
Console.
In addition to fixing the concurrency
control problems, with the
buggy solution we examined earlier,
our framework-based solution, is more
portable.
Reusable, and extensible.
Since it applies the Gang of Four template
method, strategy, and factory method
patterns, to factor out various platform,
and
concurrency control mechanisms, into
several inheritance hierarchies.
Which can then be customized by
applications,
to support different requirements, and
different environments.
Although we present these patterns in the
context of the Ping-Pong program,
they're actually broadly applicable to
many
types of software, both concurrent, and
non-concurrent.
As shown in an upcoming module, on Android
concurrency frameworks.
We'll also reuse this pattern erected
framework,
to port the Ping-Pong program to Android.
Without changing the core Ping-Pong
algorithm, or the framework software
itself.
Which your program is part of an
assignment, later in this MOOC.
[BLANK_AUDIO]