[MUSIC]
Welcome to the next part of the module,
which covers the Java ReentrantLock class.
This part provides a conceptual overview
of mutual
exclusion, explains how the ReentrantLock
class implements these
concepts to provide mutual exclusion to
concurrent Java
programs, and shows how ReentrantLocks are
applied in Android.
Mutual exclusion is one of the most
fundamental synchronization concepts,
which defines a critical
section where only one thread at a time
can execute, as described at this link.
A human known use of mutual exclusion is
the protocol used in an airplane
restroom, which is a critical section
where only one person at a time should be.
If the sign says vacant, one person can
enter.
When they lock the door, the sign then
says occupied.
As long as the restroom is occupied, other
people must
queue up outside and wait for their turn
to enter.
When the person in the restroom exits,
they set the
lock back to vacant allowing a waiting
person to enter.
Note how this protocol is fully bracketed.
In other words, the person who enters the
restroom and locks the door must
be the same person who unlocks the door
and exits the restroom when they're
done.
[MUSIC].
Java provides mutual exclusion via its
ReentrantLock class, which
implements the lock interface, as
described at this link.
Most of its implementation is written in
Java, as shown at this path name.
ReentrantLock uses the Ganga four bridge
pattern
described at this link for several
purposes.
First, it inherits the bulk of its
functionality from
the abstract queued synchronizer class
described at this link; which
provides a framework for implementing
blocking locks and synchronizers that
rely on First In, First Out or F.I.F.O.
wait queues.
Second, it implements several lock
acquisition models via its common
interface,
if the fair parameter pass, so the
ReentrantLock instructor is true.
Then access is always granted to the
longest waiting thread.
However, if it's false or if the default
constructor is
used, a lock does not guarantee any
particular access order.
The key methods in ReentrantLock are lock,
lock interruptibly, and unlock.
Lock acquires a lock if it's available.
Otherwise, it spins or blocks until the
lock become available.
Lock interuptibly acquire a lock unless
the thread is
interrupted, in which case it throws an
interrupted exception.
Unlock attempts to release the lock if
it's the holder.
These methods simply forward to the fair
or non-fair implementations selected in
the ReentrantLock instructors.
The non-fair implementations of these
methods are
optimized to use faster mutual exclusion
mechanisms.
Such as spin locks as describe in this
link.
[MUSIC].
To show how a Java ReentrantLock is used
in Android, we'll analysis
a portion of the take method from the
array blocking queue class.
Which is a bounded blocking queue that
stores its elements in
First In, First Out or FIFA order, as
described at this link.
Array Blocking Queue extends Abstract
Queue and implements
Blocking Queue as shown at this path name.
We don't analyze every detail of this
code, just
the parts we need to explain how
ReentrantLocks work.
Array blocking queue uses a ReentrantLock
to protect against
race conditions when threads concurrently
access its internal data members.
Such as the array of queued items, indices
for the next
take or put calls, and the number of
elements in the queue.
These data members need not be defined as
volatile.
Since a ReentrantLock implementation
enforces the same memory
synchronization semantics, provided by
built in Java monitor locks.
Which ensure that reads and writes the
data members
by different threads are properly
propagated through memory caches.
As described at this link.
Assume thread T1 calls take to remove the
first element in a new
instance of an array blocking queue, which
will block since the queue is empty.
If another thread doesn't already hold the
array blocking queue ReentrantLock,
thread T1 will acquire it, sending the
lock's hold count to one.
The ReentrantLock's data member is copied
into a final local variable.
Which is an optimization idiom that
produces the
smallest byte codes, as described at this
link.
If thread T2 tries to acquire the lock
held by T1, T2 becomes dormant until T1
calls unlock, which will decrement the
hold count
and release the lock when the count
reaches zero.
Unlock is typically called [INAUDIBLE]
block to ensure the lock is
released no matter how the method exits as
described at this link.
After T1 releases a lock, T2 can acquire
it and enter the critical section.
We'll examine the broader aspects of
synchronizing and scheduling array
blocking queue methods in our upcoming
video on Java condition objects.
Where we use both a ReentrantLock and a
pair of condition objects to
implement the monitor object pattern,
described at
this link and covered in upcoming videos.
[MUSIC].
In summary, a Java ReentrantLock provides
a lightweight mutual exclusion mechanism
that
defines a critical section where only one
thread at a time can execute.
It provides the same basic behavior and
semantics as the implicit monitor
lock accessed using Java's built-in
synchronized
methods and statements, but with extended
capabilities.
Such as methods that perform non-blocking,
interruptible, and time lock acquisition
operations.
A ReentrantLock must be used by a fully
bracketed protocol, since a
thread that acquires a lock, must be the
one to release it.
Another example of a fully bracketed
protocol, is documented
by the scoped locking pattern described at
this link.
Likewise the C++ resource acquisition is
initialization idiom, uses its
protocol to ensure exception safety, as
described at this link.
A thread owning a ReentrantLock can
reacquire
it without deadlocking, since the
underlying ReentrantLock implementation
simply increments its hold count in
accordance with
the recursive lock semantics described at
this link.
Although ReentrantLocks are a fundamental
mutual exclusion mechanism.
They can be tedious and error-prone to
program, due to the following common
mistakes.
Acquiring a lock and forgetting to release
it, releasing a
lock that was never acquired, holding a
lock for a
long time without needing it, and
accessing a shared resource
without acquiring a lock for it first or
after releasing it.
Java built-in monitor objects address some
of these limitations.
As we'll discuss later in this module.
ReentrantLock is used throughout Android,
particularly
in its Java token current package
implementation,
as shown by the source code at this path
name.