[MUSIC].
Welcome to the next part of the module
which
continues the analysis of an example that
shows how
Java concurrency mechanisms can be used to
synchronize and
schedule the behavior of threads in a
concurrent program.
This part focuses on the ping pong program
implementation,
building upon the design of review in the
previous part.
In particular, we conduct a detailed
walk-through of the
pattern oriented framework source code,
and show how it's customized
to create and start 2 Java threads whose
run hook
methods alternate printing ping and pong
on the computer console.
In addition to showing how to program with
Java
semaphores, condition objects and
countdown latches, we demonstrate by
example how the application of gangoffour
patterns, such as
template method, strategy, and [INAUDIBLE]
method provide several benefits.
For example, we show how this pattern
related framework makes
it easy to replace the use of Java
semaphores with
Java condition objects to support more
sophisticated behavior without changing
the core ping pong algorithm, or the
framework software itself.
We examine a lot of design and programming
concepts and source code in this video.
And even though it's clean and concise,
it's also heavily refactored, and pattern
oriented.
So it's important to read and run the
code, available at this link.
Carefully watch this video and the
previous one,
perhaps multiple times and learn how the
various
patterns described at the provided links
work to
fully understand how all the pieces fit
together.
[MUSIC]
Now that we've covered the design of the
pattern
oriented Ping-Pong program, we'll analyze
its implementation in detail.
The bulk of the Ping-Pong program code is
defined
in the play Ping Pong class which
implements the runnable
interface and provides a pattern oriented
framework for varying
certain aspects of the Ping-Pong
algorithm, and its concurrent behavior.
The play ping pong class contains several
static
data members shared by the threads it
creates internally.
These data members keep track of the
number of iterations to play ping
pong, the number of times to print either
ping or pong during each turn.
A strategy object used to portably to
print the ping and pong output and
synchronize completion of the internal
threads and
the type of synchronization mechanism to
use.
For example, Java semaphores are condition
objects.
The play ping pong constructor initializes
these
data members using the parameters passed
to it.
A static method ping pong thread class
extends thread and plays
the role of abstract class in the temporal
method pattern described earlier.
The acquire and release abstract methods
are
over written by sub classes to schedule
the
order of printing the ping or pong string
set by the ping pong thread constructor.
The ping pong thread run hook method
executes in a separate thread
and plays the role of the template method
in the template method pattern.
It loops with a designated number of
iterations, and performs the protocol that
uses the
acquire and release hook methods to
alternate printing
the ping and pong strings to the output.
Several pattern oriented aspects are shown
in this run template method.
First, the platform strategy print method
uses the strategy pattern discussed
earlier
to provide a platform independent means
for writing text to the output display.
Second, the acquire and release hook
methods play
the role of primitive operations in the
template
method pattern but aferring the specifics
of synchronization
and scheduling to the ping pong thread
subclasses.
When the loop exits, the platform strategy
done method is called to indicate
the thread has finished its processing
which decrements the countdown watch by
one.
When all running ping pong threads have
returned, the countdown latch drops to 0,
which
informs the play ping pong objects thread
to
shut down, as shown later in this video.
[MUSIC].
The pattern oriented ping pong framework
can be transparently
configured to support different
synchronisers either semaphore based or
condition object based using the make ping
pong threads
factory method covered both earlier and
later in this video.
We first analyzed the semaphore based
synchroniser configuration which enables
the ping and
pong threads to alternate printing the
ping and pong strings to the console.
In this implementation, the pingpong
threadsema class extends pingpongthread
and plays
the role of the concrete class in a
template method pattern.
It defines a [INAUDIBLE] array of Java
semaphores
that schedule the order in which its
acquire
and release hook methods alternate the
printing of
ping and pong in its superclasses run
template method.
The pingpong thread sema constructor
initializes this
array with the semaphore parameters it
receives.
The PingPong ThreadSema acquire and
release hook
methods simply forward to the acquire and
release methods of the first or second
semaphore stored in the semaphore array
data member.
[SOUND] These 2 members play the role
of primitive operations in the template
method pattern.
They're used to decouple the core
Ping-Pong algorithm in the Ping-Pong
thread run hook method from the
actual mechanisms that perform the
synchronization.
[MUSIC].
The ConditionObject base configuration of
the ping pong program
supports more flexible behavior than the
semaphore based configuration.
In particular, it uses condition objects
to enable each thread
to print multiple ping or pong strings
consecutively during it's term.
The PingPongThreadCond class extends
PingPongThread, and
also plays the role of the
concrete class in the template method
pattern just like the PingPongThreadSema
class.
However, it defines more data members
since
its synchronization mechanism and behavior
are different.
These data members include a 2 element
array of Java conditions
that are used together with a re-entrant
lock, to schedule the order
in which its acquire, and release hook
methods consecutively print ping
or pong in the super classes run template
method during a turn.
2 other data members keep track of the
threat identifiers, that
coordinate the passing of control between
the ping and pong threads.
The constructor of PingPongThreadCond
initializes all these
data members with the parameters passed to
it.
The acquire hook method of ping pong
thread
cond is more complex than ping pong thread
sema.
In particular, it first acquires the
ReentrantLock to enter the critical
section
and then check to see if it's the owner of
the turn.
Since the thread can only print ping or
pong when it's the turn owner.
If it's not the turn owner, it waits
on the condition object which atomically
releases a
lock and goes to sleep until the other
threads signals it after making it the
turn owner.
The release method works collaboratively
with acquire.
When it's called by a thread, it acquires
the
reentrantLock to enter the critical
section and then decrements
the turn countdown data member by 1 which
keeps
track of the number of consecutive
iterations per turn.
This threads turn is over when the value
of
turn count down drops to 0 in which case,
it makes the other thread, the turn owner
and
it resets the iterations per turn to max
turns.
Finally, this thread signals the other
thread that its turn can begin and then
releases the ReentrantLock before
returning from the critical section.
[MUSIC].
Now that we've examined the pieces of the
ping
pong program, we'll show how they all fit
together.
The run hook method of the play ping pong
class is the entry point into the ping
pong algorithm.
It executes into a separate thread and
informs
the platform strategy that a new game is
beginning.
It then creates an array of ping pong
thread objects that
are initialized by the make ping pong
threads which uses the
factory method pattern described earlier
to configure either Java semaphores or
Java condition objects, control how the
threads alternate between Ping and Pong.
After this factory method returns, the
Ping and Pong threads are started
which causes the Java virtual machine to
execute their run template methods.
Play Ping-Pong run uses a countdown latch
defined by the platform strategy await
done method,
to block until both of these threads
finish their processing and exit, before
it returns.
The make Ping-Pong threads factory method
isolates the creation of the requested
synchronization and scheduling mechanisms
which in
this case, are implemented using
semaphores.
In particular, we create a pair of binary
semaphores, one for the ping thread, and
the other for the pong thread and
initialize the ping semaphore to start out
unlocked.
We next create 2 ping pong thread Sema
objects, passing in the parameters.
These semaphores are passed to these
object constructors in opposite
order to ensure the threads correctly
alternate printing ping and pong.
For example, the ping thread is passed the
ping semaphore, followed by the pong
semaphore whereas the pong thread is
passed
the pong semaphore, followed by the ping
semaphore.
The main entry point method in the main
class sets all the pieces in motion.
It uses the factory method pattern to
initialize the platform strategy object
which in this case is the console platform
strategy, which then initializes the
command line options, which can be used to
control the number of
ping pong iterations and finally,
initializes
the PlayPingPong object, with the
requested parameters.
When all this initialization completes, an
anonymous
thread is created and started to run
the PlayPingPong object, which triggers
all the
concurrent ping pong algorithm processing,
discussed earlier.
[MUSIC].
In summary, this video analyzed the
implementation of a pattern
oriented framework, that supports a family
of related concurrent ping pong programs.
Unlike the buggy implementation we
examined in an earlier
video, this framework was customized and
configured with Java's
semaphores, condition objects, and count
down latches to correct
the alternate printing ping and pong on
the computer console.
The use of the gangoffour template method,
and factor
method patterns, enhance systematic reuse
and flexibility by making
it easy to switch between Java semaphores
and condition
object synchronization mechanisms, without
changing
the framework or application software.
These patterns also extended the program
to
transparently support more sophisticated
ping-pong behavior such
as allowing each thread to print multiple
ping or pong strings consecutively, during
its turn.
The use of the gangoffour strategy
pattern, enhanced portability, by defining
a
platform strategy class hierarchy, that
factors at different ways of printing ping
and pong and coordinating the completion
of printing operations on different run
time platforms, such as a Java console
application versus an Android application.
Although there are many classes in this
framework based solution,
knowledge of the patterns that motivate
and guide its design
and implementation greatly simplify both
understanding how it works, and how to
extend it, to support new requirements and
environments.
[BLANK_AUDIO]