[MUSIC].
Welcome
to the next part of the module, which
covers the Java Semaphore class.
This part provides a conceptual overview
of semaphores, explains
how the Java Semaphore implements these
concepts, to enable multiple
threads to control access to a limited
number of
shared resources and shows how semaphores
are applied in Android.
A semaphore is conceptually a non-negative
integer that can be
incremented and decremented atomically to
control access to a shared resource.
An early use of semaphores was to provide
train operators with simple stop and
proceed indications
to ensure they shared a single train track
safely and efficiently, as described at
this link.
In concurrent programs, they're used to
synchronize schedule, the
interaction between multiple concurrent
threads as described in this link.
For example, to ensure overall system
responsiveness, it may be necessary
to eliminate the number of resources
devoted to a particular task.
Consider a pool of threads performing
image
rendering, which is computationally
intensive that use
a semaphore to restrict access to a fixed
number of cores on a multi-core processor.
Such as two out of four cores on a quad
core system.
Before threading the pool can render an
image,
it must first acquire a permit from the
semaphore.
Decrementic by one, thereby ensuring that
a core is available for use.
If two threads each acquire a permit from
the semaphore, it's permit count drops to
zero.
At this point, only these two threads can
perform
rendering, the others must wait, blocking
for an available permit.
When a thread is done rendering the image,
it's placed back in the pool, and a
permit is returned to the semaphore,
allowing another
thread to access the core and process
another image.
The acquisition and release protocol in
this example is fully bracketed.
Similar to a reentrant lock or a reentrant
read write lock, since the
thread that acquires a permit is the same
thread that releases the permit.
But that's just one of several use cases
for semaphores that we'll examine in this
video.
There are two general types of semaphores.
Counting semaphores allow an arbitrary
resource count.
For example, our image rendering example
used a
counting semaphore with an initial count
of two.
Conversely, binary semaphores restrict the
count to either zero or one,
which corresponds to locked or unlocked,
available or unavailable, et cetera.
Later in this module, we'll show how a
pair of binary semaphores can
be apply to fix the buggy ping-pong
program covered earlier in this module.
[MUSIC].
We'll
now examine a human known use of
semaphores that I learned
when I was a graduate student at the
University of California Irvine.
Irvine is located close to the beach.
So we played lots of beach volleyball on
the weekends.
For example, the Corona del Mar Beach
described at
this link had a half dozen or so
volleyball courts.
On a nice day, however, there were always
more teams
that wanted to play volleyball than there
were courts available.
So courts were a limited resource.
To schedule access to the courts, a
counting semaphore protocol was used
that involved placing a bag full of beach
volley balls in the sand.
One ball for every available court.
Each pair of teams that wanted to play
volleyball would send a representative
over to the bag.
If there was a ball in the bag, that
representative
could take the ball, and the teams could
play volleyball.
As long as the bag was empty, however,
teams that
wanted to play volleyball would have to
wait for other
teams to finish their games and return a
ball to
the bag, so they can claim it and start
their game.
Semaphore protocol used in this example is
fully bracketed.
Similar to the image rendering example we
discussed earlier that granted
the pull of threads access to a limited
number of processor cores.
[MUSIC].
Java provides semaphores by its semaphore
class, which
implements counting semaphores as
described through this link.
Implementing a binary semaphore is easy.
Simply create a Java semaphore with a
count of one.
Most of its implementation is written in
JAVA, as shown in this path name.
Semaphore using the gang of four bridge
pattern, described in this link, for
several purposes.
First, it inherits the bulk of its
functionality from
the abstract cube synchronizer class,
described at this link, which
provides a framework for implementing
building blocks and synchronizers that
rely on first in, first out or FIFO weight
cues.
Second, it implements several lock
acquisition model via a common interface.
If the fair parameter to the sum of our
constructor is
true, then access is always granted to the
longest waiting thread.
However, if it's false, or if the default
constructor is
used, a lock does not guarantee any
particular access order.
Both constructors create a semaphore with
a designated number of permits, which set
the number of resources that can be
acquired before threads block on the
semaphore.
The key methods in semaphore are acquire,
try acquire and release, which
forward to the fair or not
fair implementations, selected in the
constructors.
Acquire obtains permit from the semaphore,
blocking til
one is available or the thread is
interrupted.
If a permit is available, acquire returns
immediately,
reducing the number of available permits
by one.
Try acquire obtains a permit from the
semaphore
if one becomes available within the given
waiting time.
And the current thread has not been
interrupted.
Release returns a permit to the semaphore,
increasing the number of available permits
by one.
If any threads are trying to acquire a
permit, then
one is selected and given the permit that
was just released.
Unlike reentrant locks and reentrant read
write locks,
there's no requirement that semaphores
must be fully bracketed.
For example, a thread that releases a
permit need
not have acquired that permit in the first
place.
[MUSIC].
To show how a Java semaphore is used in
Android,
we'll analyze an example that implements
the VideoEditor interface, which
provides editing and preview functionality
for audio and video media
items in a project timeline, as shown at
this link.
VideoEditor is part of an internal package
used by the Android VideoEditor
application, found in the packages apps
folder, shown at this path name.
VideoEditorImpl implements the VideoEditor
interface shown at this path name.
We don't analyze every detail of this
code, just
the parts we need to explain how
semaphores work.
VideoEditorImpl creates a binary semaphore
that uses the fair acquisition model to
insure FIFO ordering of videos previews
run in a background worker thread.
It also defines lock and unlock wrapper
methods.
They call tryAcquire and release on the
semaphore to
the control the order in which videos are
previewed.
If the start preview method acquires a
semaphore within a designated time
out ,it previews all the audio and video
items in a timeline.
Conversely, stop preview stops the preview
and releases the semaphore.
The VideoEditorActivity is the main
activity of the VideoEditor.
It handles user requests on a project
timeline, as shown at this path name.
It contains a private class called Preview
Thread, that
extends thread and starts preview
playbacks in the background.
When a preview playback runs, it
calls the VideoEditorImpl start preview
method, which
acquires a semaphore lock to ensure only
one preview runs at a time.
If the user wants to stop watching the
current preview, the
preview stop method is called from the
user interface thread, which
in turn, calls the VideoEditorImpl stop
preview method that releases a
semaphore, so the next video can run in
the background thread.
Unlike our previous example that used a
semaphore to schedule access of image
rendering threads to processor cores, the
VideoEditorActivity
does not use a fully bracketed model.
Since the background thread that acquires
a semaphore is not
the same as a user interface thread, it
releases it.
[MUSIC].
In
summary, a Java semaphore provides a
flexible synchronization and scheduling
mechanism that
enables multiple threads to control access
to a limited number of shared resources.
A key part of its flexibility stems from
the fact that its acquire and release
methods need not be full bracketed unlike
Java reentrant blocks and reentrant read
write blocks.
In particular, there's no requirement that
a thread
that releases semaphore must have acquired
it earlier.
A semaphore supports several types of
acquire and release operations,
including blocking, non-blocking, timed,
and
multi-permit acquire and release
operations.
The blocking operations of a semaphore are
implemented
by asleep blocks, which trigger a context
switch.
So the overhead of waiting to acquire an
unavailable semaphore may be
higher than mechanisms that use spin locks
as discussed at this link.
When used to coordinate access to a pool
of resources, a semaphore
tracks how many resources are free, but
not which particular resources are free.
Therefore, some other mechanisms, possibly
involving conditional objects or more
semiphores, may be required to select a
particular free resource.
Semaphores can be tedious and error-prone
to
program, due to the following common
mistakes.
Requesting a permit and forgetting to
release it.
Releasing a permit that was never
requested.
Holding permit for a long time without
needing it.
And accessing a shared resource without
requesting
a permit for it or after releasing it.
For these reasons, Java semaphores are
rarely seen
in Android, being limited primarily to
unit tests.
[MUSIC]