[MUSIC].
Welcome to the next part of the module on
Android Concurrency frameworks.
Which covers the looper class.
This part explains how the looper class
provides a thread-specific event loop.
That waits for and dispatches messages to
handlers, and shows
how loopers, are applied in Android
applications and concurrency frameworks.
A looper contains the synchronized message
queue that's used to process messages
placed
on the queue by one or more threads, as
described at this link.
This queue can be used to implement a
thread, specific of
that loop, which is a key portion of an
event-driven programming model.
Where the control flow of the thread
is determined by messages to corresponding
user actions.
Such as touch screen presses, sensor
outputs, or messages from other threads.
As described at these links.
Only one looper is allowed per thread.
This constraint is enforced by the
thread-specific
storage pattern as described in an
upcoming video.
Multiple loopers can run concurrently in
multiple threads, and communicate by
passing messages.
The key method is defined by the looper
class are
prepare, loop and quit as shown at this
path name.
Prepare is a static method that uses the
Java thread local class described at this
link.
To initialize the current thread as a
looper.
In accordance with a thread specific
storage pattern described at this link.
Prepare must be called explicitly before
running the event loop.
Followed by creating handlers that then
reference this looper.
The loop static method, runs a threads
event loop which waits
for messages to arrive on the looper's
thread specific message queue.
The call to next on the message queue.
Can block waiting for messages to arrive.
Using the Linux e pole scalable I/O event
notification mechanism, as shown at this
path net.
Once the next message is received, the
loop
method dispatches the message to its
target handler.
Note the inversion of control here.
The looper runs the threads event loop,
and messages are
processed via call backs to handlers
provided by application developers.
Quit initiates the shutdown of a loopers
event loop.
Quit doesn't immediately terminate the
loop but instead it queues a special empty
message that informs the looper to shut
down, when it processes this message.
The actual task of managing the queue is
done by
a handler which is responsible for adding,
removing and dispatching
messages in the message queue to their
intended targets as
described in this link and covered in the
upcoming video.
[MUSIC].
We will now examine one way in which
Android software uses loopers.
By default a Java thread, and thus and
Android thread described in this
link, which is a Java thread does not have
a looper associated with it.
Therefore if a thread needs looper
behavior, one
approach is to program it directly into
the thread.
Following the steps shown at this link.
For example, a canonical looper use case
appears in the
video editor activity, covered earlier in
the Java Semaphore video.
This activity contains a private class
called
preview thread shown at this path name.
The first step in making preview thread a
looper, is to extend the Java thread
class.
The constructor of preview thread then
starts
itself to preview videos in the
background.
When preview thread is started, its run
hook method performs the next step
by calling loop or dot prepare, which
initializes the current thread as the
looper.
The step after that involves creating one
or more handlers to process incoming
messages.
The final step involves calling
looper.loop to
run the event loop, process messages and
dispatch
call backs to handlers, until the loopers
explicitly
told to stop by calling its quit method.
Although, we show these steps in the
context of the video editor activity.
This approach is applied to add loopers
to threads throughout Android middleware
and applications.
[MUSIC].
Now that we've shown the key methods in
the looper
class, and outlined a canonical
application of this class in Android,
we'll show several examples of how
Android's concurrency frameworks use
loopers for both the user interface
thread, and background handler threads.
The user interface thread has a looper
that it uses to receive
messages from itself, and other background
threats as described at this link.
The message que in the user interface
thread's looper help
serialize access to the user interface
components such as views,
and menus and insures the only objects
running on the
user interface thread have access to other
objects in that thread.
As described at this link.
The User Interface thread's looper is
implemented in
the ActivityThread class, as shown at this
path name.
ActivityThread's main entry point method
calls PrepareMainLoop, which
initializes the current thread as the
application's main looper.
The Android runtime environment creates
the main looper for an
application automatically, so there's no
need to call this method directly.
Loopers can also be defined, and used in
non user interface threads.
As found throughout Android's frameworks,
applications and providers.
Their methods are typically called from
within a run hook
method that performs some kind of service
in a background thread.
This use case is such a common idiom, that
Android defines a helper class.
Called handler thread, which starts a new
thread
containing a looper as described at this
link.
The handler thread class uses a template
method pattern, described at this link, to
perform the fixed, prepare and loop steps
in the handler threads run template method
algorithm.
Sub classes of handler thread can create
their desired handlers.
By over riding the on looper prepared hook
method, which plays
the role of the primitive operation in the
template method pattern.
The handler thread start method must still
be called explicitly to spawn the thread
which
invokes its run hook method, as shown
in this example from the Android intent
service.
Which handles asynchronous requests,
expresses
and tents on demand, as described
at this link, and covered in the next
section of this MOOC.
Handler threads are used extensively
throughout Android's frameworks,
applications and providers.
[MUSIC].
In summary, a thread can be programmed to
contain a looper.
Which in turn, contains a message to you.
These objects collaborate to provide
applications with
a thread specific event loop that waits
for and dispatches messages to handlers,
in
the user interface thread or in background
threads.
A loop is often invisible to application
software components.
Which typically acts the user interface
threads implicit looper
by handlers, as described next two videos
in this module.
Explicitly program loopers are typically
used in background
threads but applications that needed more
sophisticated concurrency model.
Then the default single threaded model
described at this link.
As shown at these path names, loopers are
used throughout
Android's open source applications,
application
frameworks and core concurrency
frameworks.
In particular, loopers playing a central
role in providing
inversion of control to Android's hammer
and async task frameworks.
[MUSIC]