Welcome to part two of the module on
framework examples.
In the previous part in this
module, we presented scope commonality and
variability
analysis as a method for developing
and applying software product lines and
frameworks.
And we also presented a couple of examples
of
applying scope commonality and variability
analysis to Android and ACE.
We're now going to dig a little bit
deeper and discuss some examples of
Android framework components.
And naturally, we'll be emphasizing the
commonality and variability of these
components and frameworks as we go through
this part of the module.
The two framework components we're
going to focus on here are activities,
which provide a visual interface for user
interaction in Android, and services,
which are classes and objects and
components that run in the
background and perform long running
operations
or allow access to remote resources.
So here's a quick recap of the Android
activity.
We've talked about this before, but here's
a little summary.
As we mentioned, an activity provides a
visual interface to user interaction.
An activity typically supports one thing a
user can do.
So it might allow you to view an email
message or send an email message.
It might show a login screen.
It might allow you to download files from
some remote server.
Applications can include one or more
activities and there
are various ways to figure out what
activities are
available by looking at various tools you
have in
the, the Android development environment
for Eclipse, for example.
If you take a look at this URL, you
can find out lots more information about,
about activities.
Implementing an activity is fairly
straightforward.
You inherit from the Activity class and
you
override a number of so-called lifecycle
hook methods.
And then we are going to include that
Activity with the appropriate metadata
in something called the Android
manifest.xml file,
which is basically a file that describes
properties and metadata, inner information
resources about
how your activity and other activities and
other parts of Android like services and
so on get packaged together and
downloaded.
Android communicates the changes that are
taking place to the Activity via
its hook methods and its lifecycle hook
methods as, as the states change.
We'll take a lot about this in a second
and I'll
walk you through the various states, but
before we do that, just
a quick note as we go through this
discussion to keep in
the mind the commonality and variability
of what we are talking about.
The activity class provides a common
interface for interacting with users,
including operations that are performed as
you move between lifecycle states.
And of course the variabilities are
provided by enabling
sub classes to override various methods,
especially the lifecycle
methods to do the necessary things to
remedy and
address what happens as the states change
in the system.
Let's first talk a little bit about the
Activity lifestyle states.
This discussion isn't really specific to
concurrent
and network software, but it's very
relevant to
frameworks cause it gives an illustration
of things
like inversion of control and commonality
and variability.
When Activity starts up, when it's
initially
launched, there's a set of initialization
steps that
take place as call backs to these hook
methods, onCreate, onStart, onResume,
which we'll talk about.
Once the activity is initialized and up
and running, then various things can
happen.
It can be visible and have the focus, so
the user
can interact with it, touch buttons, enter
in information into text fields.
You can also do various things that will
cause the activity to be paused or
stopped.
Things could be paused when the activity
doesn't have focus but still visible.
For example, if a dialog or a toast pops
up.
And when an activity is replaced by
another activity, it becomes stopped.
And at some point along the way, an
activity will either
decide to terminate itself voluntarily or
the Android runtime system they shut
it down involuntarily because it's perhaps
running low on memory or it's
decided the activity hasn't responded in a
while or may be hung.
So in that case there's some other things
that take place.
Take a look at this URL for more
information
about how these different lifecycle states
occur in Android.
So getting back to the concept of
frameworks, Android defines a whole set
of lifecycle hook methods that you can
fill in in your activity subclasses.
And we're just going to talk about them
very briefly here.
The onCreate method is called to
initialize an activity when it's first
created.
The onStart method is called when an
activity is becoming visible to a user.
The onResume method is called back when
the user returns to an
activity from another activity that was
blocking it on the task stack.
OnPause is called when a user leaves
an activity that's still visible in the
background.
OnStop is called when a user leaves an
activity for another, such
as launching a picker to choose a
particular contact from your address book.
And onDestroy is finally called when
things
are going away and, and the system has
decided to shut you down or the, the
activity has decided to shut itself down.
There's more discussion about these
various callback hooks here.
Here's a very simple, quick example to
illustrate a useful helper class to keep
track
of when and how these various callback
hook
methods are invoked by the Android runtime
environment.
What you do here is you define a
class called LifecycleLoggingActivity,
that inherits from the Activity class.
And then you can override the various
lifecycle hook methods to print out
to the logger that they are being called
at different points in time.
And if you built an Android application
using this by
inheriting from LifecycleLoggingActivity
instead of
the normal Activity, you can see
very easily by looking in your developed
environments log capability
when the different transitions are
occurring between the different lifecycle
states.
Note also the use of inversion of control
in the Activity framework.
You're not calling these methods directly.
They're being dispatched on your behalf by
the android run sys, runtime system.
In particular, this is using something
called the Activity
Manager Service behind the scenes to do
this work.
Let's now talk a bit about the, the
Android Service.
This is a bit more relevant to the context
of network and concurrent apps.
A Service is an app component that runs in
the background and it
performs long-running operations, and it
does not
provide direct access to the user
interface.
So you would typically use a Service for
certain long-running things.
You might handle network transactions in a
Service.
You might play music.
You might interact with a content provider
that
stores data persistently in a SQL Lite
database.
You might run various periodic tasks and
so on in a Service.
As you've seen there's a running example
we've used throughout the class
of an application I've developed for some
of my courses where we, we
download application, we download images
and use a service to help to
decouple that downloading from that
activity
where the user interface interactions take
place.
An application component can start a
service.
For example, an activity can start a
service, and that service will continue
to run even if the user switches to
another application or another activity.
Components can also bind to services and
interact with them
to perform various kinds of local or
remote interprocess communications.
And you can see this URL for lots more
information about services.
So how do you implement a Service?
Well, implementing a Service in Android is
very similar to implementing an Activity.
You inherit from Service and you override
a number of hook methods.
Depending on the kind of service
that you're defining, you'll override
different methods.
And then you would go ahead and add this
Service implementation to your
Android manifest file so it's known to the
system and to Package Manager.
Android communicates state changes to a
Service by invoking the lifecycle hook
methods as call back, so we'll talk more
about that in a second.
Before we do that, a quick recap of
commonality and variability.
The Service class component provides a
common interface for performing these
long-running operations that don't need to
directly interact with the user.
Subclasses can then inherit from the
Service
class and fill in what needs to happen
for different kinds of services to
initialize different
services, started services, bound
services, and so on.
And we'll take a quick look at that on the
next couple slides.
Here's a quick overview of the Service
lifecycle hook methods.
There's a method called onCreate, much
like there is with an activity, which
is called when a Service process is
created by whatever means it's created.
There's a couple of different ways you can
create a service.
One is using the command processor pattern
by invoking the startService method
which calls, causes the onStart hook
method to get called back in the service.
This is typically used when you launch
services and want to be able to have them
do something on your behalf, but not keep
them around for a long period of time.
There's also another approach for
so-called bound Services, and this
implements more of the broker-like pattern
that we've talked about before.
In this particular way of doing things,
you call bindService, which starts
the service up, and then you can go ahead
and interact with it.
When you do this, the onBind call is
automatically invoked, which can
be used to pass back a binder object, back
to the client.
And when things get shut down at some
point unbound will be automatically by the
Android runtime.
And then as with Activity there's
onDestroy hook method that's also called
back when a Service is going to away
either voluntarily or involuntarily.
Note that services don't automatically run
in separate processes or threads.
If you want it to run in a separate
process, you can do some steps in the
manifest
file that we'll look at in a second to
designate that a Service runs in a
separate process.
If you want it to run in a separate
thread, then
you'll have to use some of the concurrency
mechanisms available in Android
or use something called the intense
service, which uses a command
processor-like model to run the requests
that come in in separate threads.
Here's a very quick example illustrating a
ThreadedDownloadService example.
We could have a situation where we
inherit from Service and create a
ThreadedDownloadService.
And then its onStart command method could
take a look at
the parameters that are passed along with
the intent as extras,
and then use them to download the
designated content from a
remote server, using whatever is the
indicated or desired concurrency model.
This illustration here at the very bottom
of the slide shows how you can make
a service run in its own process by
changing the declaration in the Android
manifest file.
Note again, the inversion of control
that's taking place here.
You don't call onStartCommand.
You don't call onBind or onUnbind and so
on.
Those calls are made on your behalf by the
Android runtime.
So to wrap up this part of the
module, the Android framework components
like activities and
services, supporting version of controls,
that's one of
the key characteristics, key defining
characteristics of a framework.
And they also embodied many commonalities
and variabilities of mobile application
development, which is one of the things
that makes them so powerful.
There are many, many patterns used in
Android.
In earlier parts of this section we've
discussed a
number of patterns that occur in the
Android infrastructure.
Things like the broker pattern, or the
proxy pattern, or
the command processor pattern, or the
observer pattern, and so on.
There are lots of other patterns that are
being used there as well.
It's also interesting to note that there
are many
patterns for interacting with users at the
application level.
There's a book on android design patterns
for user interfaces, there's websites, and
so on.
So if you're interested in patterns for
Android, there are many different places
you
can go to learn more about how
to apply these techniques to your systems
effectively.