[MUSIC].
Welcome to the next part of the module on
Android concurrency frameworks,
which continues our discussion of the
Android Handler class.
This part explains how the handler class
enables the posting and processing
of runnable objects via the Message Queue
associated with the thread's looper.
It also shows how Handlers and runnables
are
applied in Android applications and its
hammer concurrency framework.
The Handler class defines methods that
enable
programs to post a runnable to, or remove
a posted runnable from the message queue
associated
with a handler as shown at this link.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The Handler and its thread specific looper
collaborate to
dequeue each posted runnable and dispatch
its run hook method.
In accordance with the command processor
pattern, which packages a piece of
application
functionality, as well as its
parameterization and
object to execute it in another context.
For example, at a later point in time, in
a different
process, in a different thread, et cetera,
as described at this link.
There's several variance of post, some of
which are highlighted on this slide.
A runnable can be posted to a Handler in
several ways.
For example, it can be added to the front
or rear of the
message queue and processed as soon as the
queue is ready to do so.
Alternatively, a delay can be specified
using relative time, which indicates
how much time must elapse before the
runnable can be processed.
Or finally, a delay can be specified using
absolute
time, which indicates when the runnable
should be processed.
The latter two methods allow programs to
implement
time outs, ticks, and other timing related
behavior.
There're also several variances of the
handler's remove method that delete any
pending
posts of the designated runnables that
still reside on the underlying message
queue.
[MUSIC].
Now that we've shown the key post related
methods in the Android handler class,
we'll analyze an
example of how to post a runnable command
to
an activity, via it's run on UI thread
method.
Which uses an internal handler object to
ensure this runnable
is executed in the context of the user
interface thread.
Since this example examines a lot of code,
you may want to
download the Android open source release
available at this link and follow along.
This example is based on the Android
activity class.
Which provides a single focused thing that
a user can do, as described at this link.
The activity class defines dozens of call
back hook methods
and life cycle methods, as shown at this
path name.
These methods perform their computation in
the user interface thread.
To allow background threads to execute
actions in the user interface
thread, the activity class defines a run
on UI thread method.
An action passed to this method must be
implemented as a Runnable
command, as depicted in this code snippet
from an earlier video that
showed how the Strategy pattern can be
applied in the Ping Pong
application to print ping and pong strings
to the user interface thread.
Internally, the run on UI thread method
uses
an instance of a Handler that's associated
with the
user interface threads looper to execute
the specified
action in the context of the user
interface thread.
If the thread calling run-on UI thread is
the
user interface thread itself, the action
is run immediately.
If it's not the user interface thread
itself however, the action is
posted to the message queue of the user
interface thread via the handler.
Naturally, this use of the Handler's post
method is not limited to the activity
class.
It's a common Android idiom that will
apply throughout this module.
[MUSIC].
Now that we've analyzed the activities run
on UI thread
method, we'll examine the implementation
of the handlers post method.
We also show how the Android handler,
looper, and message queue classes,
collaborate to
use and implement a portion of the hammer
frame work outlined in an earlier video.
Although you needn't understand all these
steps to
use the HaMeR framework effectively, it's
useful to
know how it works, since common and
generalizable
concurrency patterns and framework
techniques appear throughout its
implementation.
When an action is posted to the activity
from a background thread,
the handler's post method adds the
runnable action to the looper's message
queue.
This method performs several steps.
Many of which are shared with the send
message methods as shown at this path
name.
First, post calls the get post message
method, which obtains a message from
a factory and then capsulates the runnable
as a callback field in the message.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Post then inserts this encapsulated
runnable into
the message queue, via a call to send
message delayed, with a delay of 0, which
ultimately calls the send message at time
method.
This method first stores the thread
specific loopers message queue in a local
variable, and then sets the target of the
encapsulated runnable to be this handler.
Which the looper uses later, to dispatch
the Runnable's Run Hook Method.
Finally, the encapsulated runnable is then
queued on the looper's message queue.
At this point, we switch our focus from
the background
thread to the user interface thread,
starting with its looper.
The looper's loop method collaborates with
the message queue
and handler classes as described in a
previous video.
In particular, loop calls dispatch message
to process
an encapsulated Runnable, via the
handler's handle callback method.
This method then invokes the encapsulated
Runnables
run hook method to execute the command.
Run executes in the thread associated with
the handler
instance, which in this case, is the user
interface thread.
Note the inversion of control in the path
through this code.
The looper runs the user interface
thread's event loop and encapsulated
runnables are executed by the run
hook methods provided by application
developers.
We'll explore the entire code path used by
the hammer framework to post, schedule,
and dispatch runnables later in this
module,
when we present the command processor
pattern.
[MUSIC].
In summary, the post methods in the
handler class
form a key portion of the Android hammer
framework.
In particular, they provide the means to
end queue and later process runnables
posted
from within a single thread to itself or
posted from one thread to another.
They're often used to send runnable
commands from one
or more background threads to the user
interface thread.
In fact, the collaboration between
handler's
post methods and the message queue,
and looper classes implement the command
processor pattern as described in upcoming
videos.
In practice, the post methods of handler
often leverage Java's local class feature,
which allows
runnable commands to reference variables
in lexically enclosing
classes, or variables in a lexically
enclosing method.
As shown by the highlighted variables in
this code snippet
from the ping pong application, shown in
the earlier video.
[BLANK_AUDIO].
In this example, the M text view data
member in the Android
platform strategy class is accessed within
the runhook method of the runnable
command.
These job on Android capabilities provide
a variant of closures, which allow a
method to access non local variables, even
when invoked outside its immediate lexical
scope.
As described, this link.
[BLANK_AUDIO].
Java support for closures is also covered
at this link.
The handler's use of runnable commands
centralizes the processing
logic at the point where the post method
is invoked.
So there's no need to write separate
receiver logic to handle the post.
In contrast, the handler's send message
methods require developers to explicitly
extend the handle message hook method as
shown in the next video.
[BLANK_AUDIO].
To showcase the command processing
features of handler, we analyzed an
example of the Android activity class run
on UI thread method.
Which uses an internal handler object, to
ensure runnable actions passed to it from
background threads, are executed in the
context of the user interface thread.
[MUSIC]