[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO].
Welcome to the next part of the module on
Android
concurrency frameworks, which provides an
overview of the Handler class.
This part explains how the handler class
enables the sending and processing of
message and runnable objects in the
message cue associated with a threads
looper.
It also shows how handlers are
applied in Android applications and
concurrency frameworks.
Each thread-specific looper contains a
synchronized MessageQueue
that's used to process messages and
runnables
placed on the queue by one or
more threads, as described in the previous
video.
However, the actual management of the
MessageQueue is
done by instances of the Android handler
class.
Each of which is associated with a single
thread, and is responsible for adding and
removing messages in the thread-specific
Looper's MessageQueue, as
well as dispatching messages to their
intended targets.
As described at this link.
A Handler is associated with a particular
Looper, which defaults to
the Looper for the current thread in which
the Handler was created.
Though a different Looper can be passed as
a parameter
to the Handler constructor, which stores
it in a data member,.
And uses it to control which thread
manages operations on the Handler.
A Handler provides several capabilities to
applications.
For example, it can be used to send
Message objects, and or post
Runnable objects to a Looper in the
Handler's thread, or in a different
thread.
In either case, the Looper's MessageQueue
enqueues, schedules, and
dequeues these objects, and collaborates
with a Handler to
execute them at some point in the future
in
the context of the thread associated with
a Handler.
A Handler and Looper also collaborate to
serialize
the processing of messages within the
thread they're
associated with, which can be used to
simplify
concurrency control by eliminating the
need for synchronization mechanisms.
As long as the appropriate patterns and
framework
design rules are followed, as described at
this link.
Objects running in different threads can
interact via their Handlers.
For example, they can exchange messages
via Handler
and message cues associated with each
other's Loopers.
Android concurrency frame works use the
Handler, MessageQueue
and Looper classes to implement key
concurrency patterns such
as active object, command processor, and
the half sink
how they sink, as discussed later, in this
module.
The Handler class has a large number of
methods.
Over two dozen, as shown at this link.
These methods can be grouped into four
main categories,
which correspond to various POSA and Gang
of Four patterns.
We briefly outline each category here.
The first category of Handler methods
enable
programs to post or remove a runnable.
By inserting it into or deleting it
from the MessageQueue associated with the
Handler.
When a runnable is posted, the Handler and
its thread specific Looper
then collaborate to dequeue each runnable
and dispatch its run hook method.
In accordance with the command processor
pattern, described in these upcoming
videos.
The second category of Handler methods,
allows
programs to send or remove a message.
Again, by inserting it into, or deleting
it from the MessageQueue associated with
the Handler.
When a message is sent, it contains a
bundle of
data that will subsequently be processed
by the Handler's handleMessage
hook method, in accordance with a message
passing variant of
the active object pattern, as described in
these upcoming videos.
The third category of Handler methods are
factories that create the messages passed
to sendMessage.
In accordance with creational patterns,
described at this link.
The fourth and final category of Handler
methods is used
to dispatch and handle messages by the
handleMessage hook method.
This method must be overridden.
To receive and process messages enqueued
via send message.
The handleMessage hook method runs in the
context of
the thread specific Looper, associated
with the Handler instance.
Again, in accordance with the message
passing variant of the active object
pattern.
This overview just scratches the surface
of
the many methods associated with each
category.
Which we elaborate upon.
In the next two parts of the module.
[MUSIC]
In summary, background threads and the
user interface thread in
Android, often need to communicate to
perform their operations concurrently.
And or coordinate their behavior.
The HaMeR framework uses the Handler class
to support these interactions.
The Handler allows one or more background
threads to send
messages or post runnables to the user
interface threads MessageQueue.
As well as allow a thread to send messages
or post runnables to itself.
Moreover, background threads can also
interact via Handlers.
The post methods are generally used when
the sender knows
what operations to perform, as shown in
this upcoming video.
The sendMethods methods are generally used
when the receiver knows
what operations to perform, as shown in
this upcoming video.
Handlers are widely applied in Android
applications.
Application frameworks and concurrency
frameworks.
In the HaMeR framework, Handlers
collaborate
with Loopers and MessageQueues to
implement key
framework characteristics, such as their
support for
inversion of control, concurrency to main
specific
structure, and functionality like
synchronized MessageQueues
and thread tools, and semi-completed
portions of
concurrent applications whose run and
handle hook
messages can be overridden by application
developers.
As described in the next two videos.
The AsyncTask framework also uses Handlers
for
similar purposes, as shown in these
upcoming videos.
Other sources explain how to use Handlers
in Android concurrency frameworks and
concurrent applications.
As described at this link.
[MUSIC]