[BLANK_AUDIO].
Hello, and welcome to part one of the
Frameworks Examples module.
In this module, we're going to present
an overview of scope, commonality, and
variability
analysis, as a method for developing and
applying software product lines, and most
importantly, frameworks.
We'll then going to give a quick overview
of scope
commonality and variability analysis
applied to Android and ACE,
which are open source platforms we'll be
using throughout
the course to demonstrate the concepts of
patterns and frameworks.
Before we talk about scope commonality and
variability analysis, however.
Let's first give a quick summary of what a
software product line is.
A software product line is a form of
systematic software reuse.
It's basically a set of software intensive
systems that share common managed sets of
features, that satisfies specific needs of
a
particular market segment, or mission, or
domain.
Software product-lines are developed from
a common
set of core assets, in a prescribed way.
As we'll see throughout this entire
module,
but especially this first part, frameworks
and patterns,.
Can help to develop and define and
improve software product-lines by
factoring out many
reusable general purpose and domain
specific services
from the responsibility of the application
developers.
If you take a look at this URL,
you'll see a lot more information about
software product-lines.
By some of the groups at the software
engineering institute who
have pioneered and propagated this
prospective for a number of years.
So let's talk now about scope commonality
and variability analysis.
Key software product line and framework
structures and behaviors
can be captured using scope commonality
and variability analysis.
It's basically a way to look for things
that are going to be common and therefore
fixed and stable and worthwhile to build
your
overall solution around because they don't
change a lot.
As well as identifying things that can
change, that can vary, the so called
variabilities.
One of the key themes we'll see here is to
find ways to take
the variabilities, and provide a common
interface
to them so that when they change,
it doesn't break other parts of the
product line, or the applications, or the
frameworks that are using, that are using
these techniques in order to achieve
systematic reuse.
We're going to be applying scope,
commonalty, and variability analysis to
guide the development and application of
software product lines and frameworks.
If you take a look at the URL at the
bottom of
this slide, you'll see a paper written a
couple of years ago
that goes into more detail about the
method of scope, commonality, and
variability analysis, and I highly
encourage you to take a look at this.
It provides a good grounding for what
we're about to talk about.
So lets talk about how we might apply
scope commonality and variability analysis
to, to Android.
The scope, defines a domain and context
of Android and its various frameworks and
components.
Android naturally is targeted toward
resource constraint mobile devices,
Where they may have limited power, limited
memory, limited processors.
At least limited, compared to laptops and
desktops or servers.
Limited network access, perhaps over,
wireless links,
perhaps over cellular networks and so on.
And there also may be some limits on, on
the
price point, People may want to provide a
range of different alternatives.
Some for the very high end users.
Some for the more bargain price sensitive
users.
Android's also focusing of course on touch
screen modalities.
Interacting by touching the screen with
your finger, with
various gestures, as opposed to
interacting with a physical keyboard.
There are some physical keyboards on
Android
devices, but they are distinctly in the
minority.
Android also provides a largely open
source vendor and hardware agnostic
eco-system.
And I say largely, because it turns out
there are some reasons, some good reasons
and some technical reasons why some parts
of
a=Android are not available in open source
form.
And the architecture of Android actually
applies scope commonality
and variable analysis to determine which
parts are fixed.
The interfaces for example, and which
parts vary,
the implementations for specific devices,
for specific censors.
Android is also targeted towards the
installed base of JAVA application
developers.
There's lots of people out today who
understand how to write JAVA applications.
It is possible to write C and C++ services
and applications in an Android using the
native development kit.
But that is not a common thing to do, most
people who are developing apps are doing
in a Java.
You can find out more about Android by
taking a look at this URL.
So let's talk about some of the
commonalities of Android.
These are the things, common attributes
that you will find
on all the different incarnations that
Android and its various frameworks.
At the core, are the common framework
components
we've talked about several times
throughout the course.
Things like activities, services, content
providers, broadcast receivers and so on.
And then there's a set of common
applications frameworks that, extend and
instantiate and enhance.
Build upon these core framework components
to provide
reusable services that you need on mobile
devices.
Things like, knowing where you are,
location managers.
Things for handling telephony services,
instant messaging through SMS or MMS.
Things like being able to download
packages
from an app store and being able to
install them on your phone in a, in a
secure and signed way, and so on.
And the Android also provides a number of
common infrastructure elements.
The intense framework which is used to
disseminate events between
producers and consumers using publisher
subscriber and observer like patterns.
The binder driver and binder frameworks
which are used for highly optimized
local interprocess communication between
application activities
and services running on the same device.
There's also common infrastructure with
respect to
the hardware extraction layer we just
talked about.
There's also common device driver
frameworks that
come from the Linux portion of Android.
So there's a lot of commonality going on
here, which is great, because it makes it
a
lot easier to learn Android, and to extend
it in very stylized ways for your
particular needs.
There also, of course, are some
variabilities, these are the
attributes that are maybe unique to
particular instantiation of Android.
For example there's a number of different
product dependent components.
Different vendors provides different kinds
of look and feel user interphase
to wrap their branded skins around the
more generic Android infrastructure.
There's also of course, a need to be able
to have different kind
of sensors or hardware devices, things
like different kinds of cameras and so on.
And there's a need to be able to have
different
types of drivers, possibly at the hardware
obstruction layer implementation.
That factor out these differences which
are often proprietary.
There are also a number of different
ways of assembling components that are
product dependent.
So for example, different vendors may
bundle different subsets of applications.
Some vendors may have their own maps
applications.
Some vendors may have their own email
application.
Some vendors may prefer to use the open
source versions that
come bundled with the Android open source
release and so on.
And, of course, there's also different
assemblies for
different types of telephony protocols
CDMA versus GSM.
Various kinds of hardware and software and
operating system configurations
based on footprint or price, performance
form factors and so on.
As you can see, the bulk of the discussion
we've applied so far for scope commonality
and variability analysis has focused
largely on macro-level
issues, sort of the overall architecture
of Android.
As we discuss this topic a little further,
we'll all start, we'll also start to drill
down
recursively and apply this commonality and
variability analysis to
the various frameworks and components to
Android as well.
Let's shift gears a little bit and talk
about how we could apply scope
commonality and variability to another
platform, In
this case, the adaptive communication
environment, or ACE.
ACE is essentially a set of C++ libraries,
and toolkits, and
frameworks, and so on, that we've been
developing for over 20 years.
ACE is designed primarily, its scope is
primarily in the layer of object-oriented
host-infrastructure middleware.
If you recall our earlier
discussions about middleware layers, host
infrastructure
middleware is the layer that sits on top
of the operating systems
and underlying protocols to shield the
higher level middleware services and
applications
from the accidental complexities and
diversity
of those lower level system APIs.
It provides a number of different
capabilities,
it encapsulates some of the tedious and
error-prone aspects of programming on
different operating
system by refactoring and providing a
portability visage.
And it also goes one step further
to provide a way of encapsulating and
enhancing.
THe C-APIs, with easier to program, easier
to
compose, easier to understand, object
oriented C++ interfaces.
Things called wrapper facades, that we'll
talk about in a moment.
Like Android, ACE is also available
completely in open source
form, it's got vendor and hardware and
operating system, agnostic ecosystem.
The main difference is that, unlike
Android, ACE is focused on C++ developers.
Primarily on developers who are trying to
build infrastructure
software, various kind of reusable
services, middleware and so on.
And or applications that have to run
in distributed real time embedded systems,
which are
typically mission critical and where the
right
answer delivered too late, becomes the
wrong answer.
You can learn more about ACE by taking a
look at this URL.
So let's talk a little bit about some
of the commonality, and the commonalities
in ACE.
Things that you're going to find on all
the different instantiations.
One of the things it provides is a
portability layer.
An operating system adaptation layer.
It provides POSIX-like API's that shields
the higher layers of
ACE and other middle wed that may rest
upon it,
as well as any applications developed
using its services and
components from the low level platform
specific details and dependencies.
On top of this obstruction layer, our set
of C++ wrapper facades.
These wrapper facades provide an object
oriented interface
to operating system services, things like
local and remote
inter-process communication, concurrency,
synchronization,
event demultiplexing, and the
multiplexing, file system interfaces,
dynamic linking and so on.
These wrapper facades implement something
called the wrapper facade pattern,
and we'll talk more about this later in
the course.
And finally, ACE also provides a set of
C++ frameworks.
These C++ frameworks handle a wide variety
of different design
dimensions that we've talked about earlier
in this, in this, course.
They handle things like synchronous and
asynchronous event de-multiplexing and
event handling.
Various forms of concurrency, layered
service
composition and processing, various forms
of
connection setup, and service handler
initialization,
static and dynamic configuration and so
on.
And it basically makes it possible to
write
a lot less application code, and let ACE
and
the frameworks do much of the heavy
lifting on
your behalf in a very efficient and
portable way.
There also, of course, are some
variabilties, there
are product and domain dependent
components in ACE.
Many of the implementations depend very
heavily on the specific
details of the underlying oper, the
operating systems and protocols.
And they try to factor out those, those
various diversities and heterogenaities
so that the interface is seen by the
application developers are common.
But naturally the frameworks and the
platform implementations have to
be full aware of these kinds of
diversities and variabilites.
There are also various types of product
dependent component assemblies with these.
Not all users want to use all parts of
this large platform.
So it's possible to go in and subset
different parts of ACE,
extract out the pieces you need, leave
behind the ones you don't want.
Which is important for people running in
memory
constraint and processor constraint, real
time and embedded
systems where they can afford the luxury
of
the whole ensellada of all these pieces of
software.
As with Android, we'll talk later about
applying scope
commonality and variability analysis to
other parts of ACE.
This has mostly been a macro-level tour to
high-level to the various pieces.
We'll also drill down later and talk more
specifically about
commonality and variability in its various
application frameworks a.services as well.
So to wrap up this section, scope
commonality and variability
analysis is an advanced technique for
insuring systematic software reuse.
This method helps developers alleviate
problems that arise when
maintaining lots of different versions of
the same product.
Especially when these products have large
amounts of similar software that was
often created in an ad hoc way to satisfy
new and diverse requirements.
And scope commonality and variability
analysis helps you to refactor a
lot of that commonality to make it
cleaner, easier to maintain.
As we discussed here, the frameworks that
are
provided in ACE and Android, for software
product lines
that enable the systematic software use,
across a wide
range of different apps and infrastructure
environments and platforms.