[MUSIC].
Welcome to the next part of the module on
Android
Concurrency Frameworks, which wraps up our
discussion of the handler class.
This part explains how the handler class
enables the sending and handling
of message objects via the message queue
associated with the thread's looper.
It also shows how Handlers are applied
in Android applications and its Hammer
concurrency framework.
The Handler class defines methods that
enable programs to send a message to,
or remove a sent message from, the message
queue associated with the Handler.
As shown at this link.
Unlike posting Runnables, which are
self-contained
commands, each message contains a bundle
of
data that can be sent to a Handler, as
described at this link.
This data contains a user defined code
that
recipients can use to identify what the
message
is about, as well as several integer
fields
and an arbitrary object sent to the
Handler.
This data with subsequently be processed
by the Handlers Handle message
hook method, which developers must
override by extending the Handler class.
The Handler and its thread specific looper
collaborate to DQ
each set message and dispatch its Handler
message hook method in
the context of the thread associated with
the handle, in
accordance with the message passing
variant of the Active Object pattern.
Which defines service requests and
components as the
units of concurrency and around service
requests on a
component in a different thread from the
client thread
that requests the service, as described at
this link.
[MUSIC].
There are three main categories of Handler
methods relating to sending and handling
messages.
For example, there are several variants of
the send message
method itself, some of which are
highlighted on this slide.
As with post, some send message methods
add a message to the front or rear of
the message queue, where they're processed
as soon as the queue is ready to do so.
Alternatively, a delay can be specified
using relative time, which indicates
how much time must elapse before the
message can be handled.
Finally, a delay can be specified using
absolute time.
Which indicates when the message should be
handled.
The latter two methods allow programs to
implement time-outs, ticks, and other
timing related behavior.
There are also several methods that insert
so-called empty messages, which only
contain the what value into the message
queue for immediate or deferred handling.
Several variants of the remove method use
the what value to
leave any messages that still reside on
the Handler's underlying message queue.
A second category of Handler methods
create
methods that are passed to send message.
These obtained message methods are
factories
that allocate a message from the global
message pool setting various fields of the
message as designated by their parameters.
In accordance with creational patterns
described at this link.
There are many obtain message methods.
Some of which are highlighted on this
slide.
The third and final category of Handler
methods
are used to dispatch and handle messages
via the
handle hook message which must be
overwritten to
receive and process messages, and queued
via send message.
Handler message runs in the context of the
thread specific looper associated with the
Handler instance.
In accordance with the message passing
variant of
the active object pattern, as discussed in
upcoming videos.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC].
Posting a runnable to a Handler is
straightforward.
Since the runnable defines a self
contained command,
whose logic is localized in its run hook
method.
Sending a message to a Handler is a better
more complicated, however.
Since the Handler must be extended and its
handle
message hook method overridden, to process
messages it receives.
This examples shows how to use a Handler
to send and process messages in several
threads.
For example, it shows how to send a
message
from a background thread to the user
interface thread.
Likewise, it shows how to send message at
period
time intervals from the user interface
thread to itself.
It also outlines how the Android handler,
looper,
and message queue classes collaborate to
use and implement
a different path through the hammer
framework than covered
by the previous post example in the
earlier video.
This example is based on the Android
countdown timer class
which schedules a countdown until a
specified time in the future.
As described at this link.
A CountDown Timer is onTick hook method is
dispatched at regular intervals by
internal calls to the send message delayed
method until its CountDown time period
elapses.
For example, a code in this slide creates
a 30,000
millisecond or 30 second CountDown Timer
in the user interface thread.
It's onTick hook method is dispatched via
an internal callback to
the handle message hook method every 1,000
milliseconds or one second.
At which point, the number of seconds
remaining is written into a text field.
When the 30 second time period elapses,
the onFinish hook method
is dispatched via an internal callback to
the handle message hook method.
At which point done is written into the
text field.
In this example a background thread called
start on the countdown
timer, which sends the message which
triggers the processing described above.
[MUSIC].
CountDownTimer is an abstract class whose
onTick and onFinish hook
methods must be overridden, as shown at
this path name.
This analysis is also fairly detailed, so
you might want to
download the Android source code available
at this link and follow along.
CountDownTimer's constructor stores the
future time
and countdown intervals in its data
members.
CountDownTimer also contains an internal
handler
that's associated with the thread's
looper.
This handler must override the handle
message hook
method to process messages, passed to send
message.
When a count down timer receives a message
via handle message, it invokes a call back
to the over ridden onTick or onFinish hook
methods in the thread where it was
created.
Its start method obtains and sends the
message to it's internal handler, via send
message.
SendMessage inserts the message into the
message
queue of the handler's looper, where it's
processed as soon as the queue is ready,
as shown at this path name.
The path through the handler, message
queue,
and looper code is essentially the same
as the path for posting and processing
runnables, as shown in the previous video.
The main difference is that the
handler's dispatch message method invokes
the overwritten
handle message hook method, instead of the
run hook method of the encapsulated
runnable.
Handler message runs in the context of the
thread associated with the handler.
When the countdown timer's handleMessage
method is
dispatched it checks to see if the
entire time period has elapsed, in which
case it invokes the onFinish hook method.
If the call back occurred too soon, the
send message delayed
method is invoked to schedule another call
back at a later time.
If the time interval has elapsed, the
onTick hook method is
invoked and the next time interval is
scheduled by a sendMessageDelayed.
CountDownTimer's hook methods all run
inside a synchronized statement to ensure
that calls to onTick never occur before
the previous callback is complete.
CountDownTimer is used in Android's
middleware and applications for various
purposes, such as lock screens, as shown
at these path names.
[MUSIC].
In summary, the sendMessage methods and
the Handler class.
Key portion of the Android HaMmeR
framework.
In particular, they provide the means to
end queue and later handle messages sent
from within a single thread to itself or
passed from one thread to another.
They're often used to send messages from
one
or more background threads to the user
interface thread.
The collaboration between the handler's
send message
methods and the handler's message queue
and looper
classes implement the message passing
variant of the
active object pattern, as described in
upcoming videos.
Unlike the handler's use of runnable
commands,
which centralizes the processing logic at
the point
where the post method is invoked, the send
message methods decouple client senders
from handle receivers.
Developers must therefore extend the
handle message hook method
and write explicit logic to handle the
messages it receives.
While there's an extra step involved in
writing
these handle message hook methods, this
decoupled approach
can be more flexible and parameterizable
than the
centralized model provided by Post's use
of runnable commands.
To showcase the message passing features
of handler, we analyzed an example of
the Android CountDownTimer class, which
internally sends messages to a handler
that collaborates with the looper and
message queue to schedule and dispatch
callbacks to the onTick and onFinish hook
methods in the user interface thread.
[MUSIC]