[MUSIC].
Welcome to the first part of the module on
Android Concurrency Frameworks.
In this part, we focus on the
pattern-oriented
structure and functionality of several
Android concurrency frameworks.
Which contain an integrated set of
classes.
That collaborate to provide a reasonable
architecture for families of
related concurrent applications and
services, as covered in earlier videos.
There are two primary motivations for
Android's Concurrency Frameworks.
The first motivation stems from accidental
complexities of the Android platform.
Which has several design constraints that
restrict how concurrent applications
and services can be developed, as
described at this link.
For example, if an application's user
interface thread doesn't respond
to input within a short time, typically
three to five seconds.
Android generates an Application Not
Responding dialogue.
Which gives users an opportunity to
manually shut
down a non-responsive application, as
discussed at this link.
One consequence of this design constraint
is that the user interface thread can't
block on any operations that may run for
an extended period of time.
Likewise, non user interface threads
should not
directly access components in Android's
user interface toolkit.
Such as structured layout objects,
controls,
dialogues and menus, since they aren't
thread-safe.
And should be accessed only from the
user interface thread as described at this
link.
Although the Java concurrency mechanisms
covered in the previous
module are used for starting,
synchronizing, scheduling, and terminating
threads.
They're intended for general purpose
concurrency
environments, hence the need for
frameworks.
The chill developers of multi threaded
software from these
tedious and error prone aspects of its
design constraints.
The second motivation for Android's
Concurrency Frameworks stems from
the benefits of concurrency described in
this earlier video.
Such as simplifying program structure to
avoid
overly complex and tangled event-driven
software architectures.
Increasing performance by overlapping
communication and computation
to run in parallel on multi-core
platforms.
And improving responsiveness by processing
short-duration
user-facing operations in a different
thread.
Then other long duration background
operation.
As we'll see throughout this module,
Android's Concurrency
Framework supply many POSA and gang of
four patterns.
Including command processor, active
object, half
sync half a sync, and strategy.
As summarized in this earlier video.
In later sections of this MOOC, we'll
cover these patterns in detail.
And show how they're applied in Androids
concurrency and communication middleware.
As well as in applications and services.
[MUSIC].
The Shield developers applications and
services.
Accidental and inherent complexities of
Android design constraints as
well as to enhance the software quality
attributes summarized earlier.
Android provides several concurrency
frameworks.
These frameworks allow certain
computations typically long duration
and blocking operations to run in
background threads.
And other computations, typically short
duration user facing
operations, to run in the user interface
thread.
For example, the image download
application discussed
in this video uses an Android concurrency
framework.
To spawn background threads to process
long duration blocking operations.
Such as downloading large images from
remote servers.
It then uses a synchronized message cube
provided by the framework.
To communicate results from the background
threads to the user interface thread.
Which then displays the image to the user
screen.
The user interface thread can also use
this framework to pass messages to itself.
For example, it can defer certain
processing
until a designated period of time elapses.
Android has two primary concurrency
frameworks.
One framework consists of handlers,
messages, and
runables, which we call the Hammer
Framework.
Which provides a loosely connected set of
classes that allow
long duration operations to run in one or
more background threads.
And then, publish the results of these
operations to
the user interface thread as described at
this link.
And shown by our image downloading
application outlined earlier.
Another concurrency framework is called
AsyncTask.
Which provides a more tightly connected
set of classes that
execute long duration operations in one or
more background threads.
And publishes the results to the user
interface
thread without manipulating threads,
handlers, messages, or runnables
explicitly.
As described at this link.
Each framework has pros and cons and both
are used extensively in Android's
middleware and packaged applications.
As we'll discuss throughout this module.
[MUSIC].
The Android Concurrency Frameworks
discussed in this module
are built using a number of reusable
classes.
Some of which are directly visible to
users,
while others are largely hidden below the
surface.
The design, implementation and integration
of these classes are
guided by many POSA and Gang of Four
patterns.
Go briefly outline the most important
classes and patterns
used in the frameworks we cover in this
module.
Some classes we cover are used by both the
Hammer and in AsyncTask frameworks.
For example a looper runs a thread
specific event loop that
waits for and dispatches messages to
handlers as described at this link.
The thread specific storage pattern
covered here is
used to ensure there's only one looper per
thread.
A message queue holds a list of messages
to
be dispatched by a looper as described at
this link.
Android's message queue class applies the
monitor object pattern presented here.
To enable thread's to in queue and dequeue
messages concurrently.
A message contains descriptions of a
message's type.
Or other information and an arbitrary dead
object, they could be sent
to a handler via its loopers message queue
as described at this link.
Messages are created via a factory method
pattern covered here.
Messages aren't added directly to a
MessageQueue, but through a handler.
Which allows the sending and processing of
message and
runnable objects in the MessageQueue
associated with a thread's looper.
As described at this link.
Handlers provide methods that support both
the
active object and command processor
patterns covered here.
To allow sender and receiver threads to
run concurrently.
Implementations of the Java runnable
interface represent
commands that can be executed by handlers.
In conjunction with the looper class as
described at this link.
The AsyncTask framework also uses several
other
classes from the Java util concurrent
package.
For example, future tasks can be used to
start and cancel an Async computation.
Query to see if the computation is
complete and retrieve
the result of the computation as described
at this link.
Finally implementations to the executor
interface execute submitted rumble
tasks either sequentially or in a pool of
threads.
As described at this link.
The AsyncTask framework uses these two
classes.
To implement the Half-Sync, Half-Async
pattern, explained here.
To decouple asynchronous and synchronous
processing,
to simplify programming, and enhance
performance.
[MUSIC].
The classes and interfaces in Android's
concurrency frameworks we just summarized.
Work together to embody the three key
defining characteristics discussed earlier
during the course introductions.
In particular, they provide inversion of
control, where
the framework is responsible for detecting
events that occur.
Multiplexing these events to the
corresponding handlers.
And then, dispatching hook methods on
these handlers to perform the intended
processing.
They also provide integrated structure and
functionality targeted
at the domain of concurrent programming in
Android.
Finally, they provide semi-complete
portions of concurrent applications.
That can be customized and completed by
inheriting from abstract framework classes
and interfaces.
And overriding hook methods to implement
application specific functionality.
We analyze all of these classes throughout
this module.
To show how they work, how they interact
with each other, and how they're applied
in Android.
We cover both the interface classes that
are visible to application developers.
As well as implementation classes that are
less visible to application developers.
This analysis shows by example.
How softer patterns are applied to guide
the design, implementation.
And integration of Android's concurrency
frameworks.
And applications that use these
Detailed coverage of these patterns and
their
application in Android appears later in
this module.
[MUSIC].
In summary, Android has several design
constraints
that restrict how concurrent programs can
be developed.
For example, it only allows one thread
to perform user interface operations per
application.
All components in the same application
process use the same
user interface thread to receive system
generated notifications in broadcast.
Interact with users and perform activity
life cycle methods.
Since components in Android's user
interface tool kit aren't threat
safe, they should only be accessed from
the user interface thread.
Likewise long duration operations should
run in background threads.
To avoid generating application not
responding dialogues if
they block for more than a few seconds.
To make it easier for applications and
services to conform to these design
constraints.
Android provides several concurrency
frameworks that
allow long duration concurrency operations
to run.
And block in background threads and
communicate with user
facing operations that run in the user
interface thread.
Once concurrency framework consists of
handlers, messages
and runnables which we call the Hammer
Framework.
This framework allows operations to run in
one or more
background threads that publish their
results to the user's interface thread.
The classes and the Hammer Framework are
loosely connected.
So, it's essential to understand the
patterns that guide their structure and
interactions.
The other framework is called AsyncTask.
Which also allows operations to run in one
or more
background threads and publish the results
to these interface thread.
Unlike the Hammer framework, however, the
AsyncTask framer
doesn't require applications to manipulate
threads, handlers, messages.
Or runnables explicitly.
Moreover, the classes in the AsyncTask
framework are strongly connected.
Which helps simplify the use of this
framework
since its design has a smaller surface
area.
Most frameworks apply patterns from the
Gang of Four and POSA books.
In turn, these pattern anointed frameworks
provide idioms that are
specific to the Android platform and its
concurrency design constraints.
An idiom is a pattern that focuses on a
particular context.
Such as development platform, programming
language, or
design method, as described at this link.
In addition to these common frameworks,
other frameworks
also exist for running computations
concurrently on Android.
For example, RenderScript is a framework
for
running computationally intensive tasks
efficiently on Android.
It can be used to parallelize work across
all processors available on a device.
Such as multicore CPUs, GPUs, or DSPs.
Render script is primarily intended for
data parallel computations.
Such as applications that perform image
processing, capitation of
photography or computer vision as
described at this link.
RxJava implements the .NET reactive
extensions for the JavaVirtual Machine.
Who combines data or prevent streams
the reactive objects and functional
computation.
RXJava events or model is a streams
of Asynchronous flows too which observers
ascribe.
The observable streams can be filtered,
transformed, and composed in various ways.
Before the results are emitted to an
observer as described at this link.
While these other concurrency frameworks
are interesting,
their beyond the scope of this MOOC.
So we just focus on the, the Hammer, and
AsyncTask Frameworks in this module.
[MUSIC]