[MUSIC]
Welcome to the module on Android
Concurrency Frameworks.
Although the standard Java threading,
synchronizer, and coordination features,
covered
in the previous module, provide
the foundation for android's concurrency
mechanisms.
They can be tedious and error prone to
use, and
don't shield application developers from
Android's design constraints, such as its
non-thread safe GUI libraries and its
limits on the amount
of time, the one and only user interface
thread can block.
Therefore, to ensure that concurrency can
be used
correctly, efficiently and scalably in
applications in middleware.
As well as to alleviate the complexity of
its
design constraints, Android provides
several concurrency frameworks, that allow
background threads to run in parallel on
multiple cores,
and communicate in various was with its
user interface thread.
This module focuses on two Android
concurrency frameworks.
First, we cover its Handlers, Runnables,
and Messages, or Hammer framework,
which provides a loosely connected set of
classes, that allow long
duration operations to run in one or more
background threads, and
then publish the results of these
operations to the user interface thread.
Second, we cover Android ASCII task
framework, which provides a more
tightly connected set of classes, that
executes long duration operations in
one or more background threads, and
publish the results to the
user interface thread without manipulating
threads, handlers, messages, or runnables
explicitly.
We'll explore the structure and
functionality of these frameworks,
and show how to apply them, to develop
concurrent programs.
Such as a threaded downloads application
that implements three concurrency
models, using the Android hammer, and a
sync task frameworks.
We also demonstrate how Android
concurrency frameworks are
applied to its middle ware and packaged
applications.
As well as how its frameworks are
enhanced, by the application of
Gang of Four patterns, such as Template
Method, Strategy, and Factory Method.
And POSA patterns, such as Active Object,
Command
Processor, Half-sync / Half-Async and
Thread Specific Storage.
[MUSIC]