[MUSIC]
We're going to start talking about one of
the patterns
that's very heavily used in the context of
started services.
We'll talk about a number of other
patterns later as
we cover other parts of the material
related to services.
And after we cover this pattern were then
going
to start talking about more detail, around
the bound services.
Keep in mind, up to this point, we've only
talked about the started services.
Now, we're going to go ahead and start
talking about bound services as well.
But before we do that, let's start talking
about the pattern, that we've been
covering here implicitly.
I've, I've mentioned this a couple of
times, but we
haven't talked about it as a pattern in
any detail yet.
So, the particular pattern we're going to
be covering is called the Command
Processor pattern, and this pattern
appears in a number of different places.
The original pattern with the name Command
Processor appeared in the book,
Pattern Oriented Software Architecture
Volume I,
which was about systems of patterns.
And it talked about a lot of different
architectural patterns.
There's another pattern that appeared in
the Gang of Four book.
It's called the Command Pattern, which is
related to
the Command Processor pattern, but it's
not quite identical.
The actual particular implementation of
this
pattern I'm going to be describing came
from yet another paper, which was written
by a couple of other folks.
And this is called Command Revisited.
And they attempted to take the, the best
of
the command pattern from the Gang of Four
book, the
command processor pattern from the Post of
One book, and
then they added a few new things and that
appeared.
And it's kind of interesting to think
about how this all occurred.
Why do we need to keep rewriting these
patterns?
And what happens, of course, is as people
get more experience trying to
apply patterns to a broader range of
context, to a broader range of
applicability
domains, then you get to realize how the
initial attempts at describing the pattern
were probably over constrained by the
original
context in which the pattern was
identified.
So, the folks who were doing the original
Gang of Four
book, were largely thinking about user
interface environments, graphical user
interface environments.
Where commands are largely used to run
various
kinds of actions when a user clicks a
button
or touches a screen or uses some other
type
of modality to interact with the, the user
interface.
So, in that case, the commands were really
sort of self contained objects
that were used to encapsulate a request to
a service as an object.
Like, open this file or delete this file
or something like that.
As people got more experience applying
patterns
to other context like distributed systems
for
example, or concurrent systems, it became
clear
that that original context was too narrow.
And so, from there grew the Command
Processor pattern, and
the Command Processor pattern is more
about taking commands and
passing them over to some kind of command
processor where
they're executed, typically in a different
thread or a different process.
You'd be pretty darn hard pressed to
extract that particular use
case out of the original Gang of Four
pattern for command.
The Gang, the Post of One pattern of
Command Processor did
a nice job, but it also was deficient in
certain ways.
And so, as people got more experienced
they
took shots at trying to write this stuff
down.
So, what I'll be talking about today is
kind of
an amalgamation of a number of different
perspectives on command.
And I think it turns out that the one
we're talking about here is very
nicely related to what we see in
Android, especially the intense, the
intense service framework.
First, let's talk over about the context,
though, in which this appears.
So, we're going to want to be able to
process some long-running action.
Where long-running in this context means
something
that would take, potentially, too long and
would end up blocking the UI thread such
that you would get an ANR call.
So, if we're going to download some kind
of image
from some place, from a, from a server
somewhere, that
might take a while depending on how big
the
image is, depending on how heavily loaded
the device is.
Depending, depending on how heavily loaded
the
network or the server, the server cloud,
storage, whatever it is, depending on the
load, it might take a while to download.
So, as a result, if we're not careful, we
can end up blocking in that download call.
The problem, as you all know, is if you do
blocking calls from the main thread of
control, the UI thread, that's going to
run
the risk of triggering the application not
responding dialogue.
So, something will go wrong, it will say
this is not
working do you want to shut it down and so
on.
So, that would be problematic, we don't
want that to happen.
Take a look here at this website for more
information about the, the
perils of ANRs and when they occur and
what to do about them.
So, the solution here, which we have
already talked
about, but not we are going to start
talking about
it more from a pattern oriented
perspective, is to
implement some kind of command processor
in order to encapsulate
a download request as an object that you
can
pass from an activity, that you don't want
to block,
to a service where that thing can run in
some kind of background thread and run at
its leisure.
So, this particular set of steps, this
process might work as follows.
You'd go ahead and implement a download
service, that would inherit
from intent service, and you'd have the
activity then creating an
intent, and into that intent, it would,
make the target of
the in, the intent be the download
service, its class file.
You could add in stuff like, the URI, that
you wanted, and the
call back messenger, if that's how you
want to communicate back, or the pending
intent, or the broadcast receiver, you
know, however you want to get the
information back, you could stick those
things as extras into the particular
intent.
Then, you go ahead and call StartService
with the intent of all
that stuff that's bundled in there, it's
target, it's extras and so on.
That will cause the Android Activity
Manager Service,
that we've talked about recently, to go
ahead and
spawn off the, the Service to start the
Service, the download survey if it's not
already running.
Since that thing is implemented as an
IntentService that will go ahead and start
a thread in the background using the,
the Service handler model we've looked at
before.
And then, of course, under the hood,
that'll end up calling the
on-handle intent method which will
download the image in a separate thread.
By the way, we had an interesting
discussion
on the mailing list about the thread pool
executor,
which is part of your current assignment,
and,
and what might be the benefit of using
that.
So, if you think about the IntentService,
the IntentService only lets there be one
thread at a time, the, the background
thread, that's being used to download the
image.
And that works for the very simple use
case we just described here.
You have one activity talking to one
service, which is downloading one file.
What might be the motivation for wanting
to
use some kind of thread pool executor
instead?
Anyone except Shawn.
[LAUGH] Christoph.
>> A list view filled with images so we
won't
have to go down as fast as your CPU
[INAUDIBLE].
>> Great, so, so one example would be that
you've actually
passed over a, a, a batch worth of things
to download.
And rather than doing them sequentially in
that one thread you want
to go ahead and maximize the potential
concurrency or parallelism in the system.
Modern Android devices often have
quad-core
processors, so why not take advantage
of all that processing power to go ahead
and do things in parallel.
That would be one example, another example
might be a situation where you're trying
to
write some kind of download service and
you
were going to have multiple things
connecting to it.
Some of which might be triggered from
background
tasks, some of which might be triggered by
user
interface interactions, some of which
might be triggered by
the list view thing that Chris [UNKNOWN]
talked about.
So, in any case, you have the potential
for multiple things to happen.
So, that would provide a good example of
why you would
want to have multiple threads running in
a, in a Service.
Be it in a separate process or in the same
process as the original client.
Okay, you can take a look here, of course,
for more information on IntentService.
We'll look at IntentService in more detail
later.
So, it turns out that this particular way
of arranging things is, as often is the
case, not just a random set of classes
thrown together just for the, the fun of
it.
But, this is actually an implementation of
a pattern, and the
pattern is the Command Processor pattern
as described in those resources.
POSA1, that paper I showed you, the Gang
of Four book.
And the intent of this pattern, and I'm
using, this is the, from the paper I
pointed
you to, is to package a piece of
application
functionality as well as its
parameterization as an object.
The ability to take the functionality in
and objectify it, if
you will, or encapsulate it and make it
usable in another context.
The word context here is meant to be used
loosely it doesn't mean
an Android context, such as in, a later
point in time, you might
put it in the queue and run it later or
you might use
it for example, to run in a different
thread or a different process.
So, you want to be able to defer what you
want to have
done from when it gets done and how it's
going to be done.
So, those things become different
orthogonal dimensions,
largely orthogonal dimensions in the
design space.
So, here's a picture of the pattern from
the
POSA4 book, which is a distillation of
various things.
We'll talk a bit more about the structure
in a second.
And there's a good link to go find
out more about this particular pattern,
the commandrevisited.pdf file.
So, when would you go ahead, when would
you want to apply this pattern?
Well there's a number of circumstances
where it would become useful.
One is a situation where you want to be
able to decouple the decision
of what code to execute from the decision
of when this code should be run.
So, you might want to be able to specify
what to run and the
be able to queue it and then execute it
later in some other context.
You also might want to be able to do
things in such
a way where you can change the
implementation of your Service without
breaking the client code that relies on it
you don't want to
have to go and change the interface for
example and recompile the client.
You want to be able to pass some kind
of more loosely coupled, loosely bound
message like abstraction that's
a bit more pliable, a bit more flexible, a
bit more adaptable to the particular needs
of your environment.
So you don't tightly couple things.
The key here is tight coupling you want to
avoid that.
Another reason which, not, is not commonly
used for our
use case, but is commonly used for user
interface things
like editors and document processors as
well as transaction oriented
systems, is the ability to undo or redo
various commands.
So, if you are a Microsoft Word user,
and you're typing along and you make a
mistake,
then you can go ahead and undo what you
just did, and it'll reverse what you just
did.
And then if you realize oh, I really
wanted to do that after all, you can
then go ahead and redo it, so undo and
redo work at the level of commands.
You can go even further with
this with various kinds of transactional
capabilities.
Things like the ability to roll back a set
of changes to a database in some way.
And those are all examples of how you
might use
commands as things that you can execute to
accomplish something,
as well as unexecute to undo it if for
some
reason you discover that the results were
not to your liking.
Some systems like GNU Emacs gives you
arbitrary
levels of undo and redo, you could have
those things go back to the beginning of
your editing session which could have been
days before.
It gets a little crazy after a while, mind
you but it's possible to do.
Other environments give you very little
undo.
For example, in PowerPoint, I think you
could
typically undo up to your last save, for
example.
So, you can't do arbitrary levels of undo.
Other systems I've worked on in the past,
like Frame Maker way
back in the day, you could undo the last
thing that you did.
So, people are obviously trying to figure
out
a trade off between devoting large amounts
of memory
to do something, versus giving you lots of
flexibility to undo and redo things at
your convenience.
Here's a picture that illustrates the
structure and participants in this
pattern.
Again, keep in mind, this is the, the
revisited, the command revisited version.
This is not exactly what you'll see if you
read the Gang of Four
book or the Post of One book, but I think
this is a good job.
So, you have something that you call a
command which
has an, a, an a bunch of operations on it.
And, typically in some way being able to
execute the command.
And then, you often have a way of being
able to customize
or subclass or somehow specialize the
original command to make a concrete
command.
Now, we'll see in Android that the
commands we're going to be passing around
in this particular environment are
intents, and
you typically don't inherit from an
intent.
Instead, what you do is you take an intent
and you add extras to it to add additional
fields and information that will be used
and stored
along with the intent when you send it
some place.
And we'll show some examples of this in
just a second.
You then have some kind of creator, which
is used to create these
commands as well as to pass them to
something to do the work.
In our particular context, the creator is
going to
be an activity of some kind, like a
download activity.
Then, we have an executor, or an executor,
it depends on whether your someone who
play first person shooter games or whether
you're someone who works as a bank
accountant.
And so in this particular case, the
executor is going to be the IntentService,
it's
going to be the thing that actually
executes
the work associated with the command it
receives.
And then, there's an execution context
which
could be a variety of different things.
I've chosen to map that to the context
that you get with
Android, but there are other things you
can map that to as well.
Okay, so that's the static view, so you
get from a structural perspective, you
get the key participants who are involved
and a brief description of what they do.
Keep in mind, as is always the case with
patterns, there's subtle variations
quite possible, and they may not line up
exactly what we're talking about here.
But it still may be the very same pattern,
and that's perfectly okay.
Let's now talk a little bit about the
dynamics.
That's how the structural participants
interact with each other.
So, in this case we have creator, like an
activity, that goes ahead and creates the
intent, and calls
StartService, well, it creates the intent
puts a bunch
of things into the intent, extras, data
and so on.
And then, it goes ahead and it calls
StartService, and that StartService call
causes the executor
to wake up and the executor then goes
ahead and runs the on handle intent
method.
And the on handle intent method is what's
going to be used to actually execute and
process the intent that was sent over to
the IntentService as a command from the
activity.
So, you can see how there's a pretty nice
mapping kind of one to one on the
various parts from the pattern description
in the
book into the parts that you find in
Android.
And as, as we've gone through this class,
I've been
amazed as I've looked more deeply into
what Android's doing.
The number of places in Android that map
pretty much almost perfectly onto patterns
that you commonly
find in the Gang of Four book and the Post
of books, and other books as well.
And that's, that's a good thing, because
it means that Android has high pattern
density.
It means people who designed it, either
intentionally or accidentally,
serendipitously figured out how
to tap into some really good time honored
ways of building these kinds of systems.
It also means that once you understand
these patterns, learning Android is
a lot easier and as you move to other
environments that are not
Android but also implement those patterns,
you'll be well disposed to be able
to port your knowledge of design
and architecture in much more interesting
ways.
By the way, it would be absolutely
fascinating to take a look and
see, what architectural patterns went awry
in the roll out of the Obamacare website.
I think that'd be really fun, somebody go
in there
and do some forensics and see what's
lurking under the hood.
I suspect you might find more anti
patterns than patterns, but
you'd still learn a lot of other stuff
like regression, load
testing is a good thing to do before you
go live,
that, that's that's a pattern that they
probably should of applied.
I think the anti pattern is, cross your
fingers and hope for the best, right?
That doesn't always work so well.
Okay, so there is a lot of different
consequences
of using this particular pattern, some of
the good things.
The client is not blocked for a long
duration of time.
So, if you take a look here you can see
here
just a little snippet of code we might
have that's going to go
ahead and start up an IntentService which
is going to handle
the request and then maybe reply via a
messenger, who knows what.
And the way we do this as you can see is
we, whoops, we
create the intent, we say we want it to
run with the download class, we
set the data, we create a messenger, we
stick that in as an extra,
and then we call StartService, and the
call to StartService does not block the
client.
It's not going to wait for that thing to
start.
It's just going to sort of fire it over
there and go
on it's merry way to be driven by further
call backs.
Another thing you can do with this
particular approach is you can allow
different
users to work with the service in
different way, via the commands that they
pass.
So, here's an example actually not too
dissimilar from some of the stuff that
you're doing for the latest programming
assignment
that's due tonight, where you might pass,
you
might have one implementation, maybe you
would
have an IntentService, maybe you'd have a
regular
service with the art, the OnStart command
hook method and you're going to get an
intent.
And that intent could contain extra
information that
could be used by the service
implementation in
order to figure out what concrete service
request
was actually being made by this particular
intent command.
So, for example, if we get a messenger
that might say, ha we're going to do a
messenger download, if we don't get a
messenger
than maybe we're going to do a broadcast
download.
We're going to download it then broadcast
it.
And, so on and so forth.
And, the cool part about this, if you
really think carefully about
what this pattern is allowing you to do,
it's giving you a common
interface, namely StartService, which
always looks
exactly the same and you're using that
common interface in order to be able to do
a variety of things.
And if you want to add more things to do,
you don't actually have to change the
StartService interface, you just change
the way in which you set up the intent
command that'll be passed to that
StartService interface.
Any questions about that?
So, that's a good example of a pretty wide
interface.
You can pass a lot of different kinds of
things
through there because you're essentially
passing a command object, and the
command object can have extras that go
with it to direct
what the receiving service does when it
actually gets the command.
There are some downsides of course in the
same way that it's nice that we can
have a wide interface where we can pass
all kinds of things through, it also means
that you as the implementer, the
implementer of
the service have additional work to do in
order to go about figuring out what it is
you need to handle to write that service.
In fact, if it's really open-ended, people
can pass
you intents that have extras that you
don't understand.
They could just throw various stuff in
there and either you ignore it because you
didn't know to look for it or if you get
it, you're like what's this thing?
I don't know what to do with this.
So, that's one of the downsides of a very
wide interface even though it
doesn't require many changes to the
interface
when you enhance and extend the service
capability.
The services over time become difficult to
understand,
because you don't really know what they
do.
Keep that thought in mind when talk
later about bound services, because bound
services,
as you see, are often, not always,
but often used with we're strongly typed
interfaces.
Where you know ahead of time what you're
passing.
And the writer of the implementation knows
precisely what it's getting.
That allows you to be a bit more strongly
typed.
And so we'll compare and contrast this
later with, with the broker pattern.
The other thing that you don't really get
with command,
is you don't get two way operations
without some additional work.
So, for our particular case and, in fact,
you
guys are seeing this in the current
programming assignment,
in our particular case, where you do need
to
get the result back you have to do
something else.
You have to create a messenger, and sen,
you
know, send or send back the reply to the
messenger.
You have to create a broadcast receiver
and then broadcast back to that thing.
You have to create a pending intent and
get that back, etc.
There's lots of different ways to do this,
but
you, the application developer, are
responsible for working these protocols.
It doesn't come pre baked into the
communication abstraction.
And think about that too, because when we
talk about
bound services and the Android interface
definition language could see
how those services give you additional
capability and additional ways
to do this that requires, less work at
face value.
There's some subtleties we'll talk about
when we get to
it, but at one level two way communication
becomes somewhat easier.
So, what are someones of the known uses?
Well the IntentService, of course, is a
great sample of the known use.
There's also other things you get in
Android that behave much like this.
So, the Runnable interface you get is kind
of a command, you kind
of make a Runnable and you can pass that
thing through to be processed
in another thread of control by the, the
message loop that's the looper that's
in that thread of control that's
associated
with the handle that you talk to.
Many user interface tool kits provide some
support for,
for commands in various ways, interpreters
for command line, programs
often do this, it can do Emacs, we talked
about before uses commands and so on and
so forth.
So, it's a pretty common pattern used in a
lot of different places.
So, to wrap up, the command processor
pattern gives
us a nice way to be able to communicate
information
between a sender and a receiver and to do
it
in a way that makes it easy to accomplish
asynchrony.
And of course, that's because you aren't
blocking, waiting for the response to come
back.
And you can have things be concurrent,
they can be networked and so on.
Obviously, in Android, you get kind of
concurrency that
goes between threads or between threads in
different processes.
Android doesn't, out of the box, give you
the command
pattern implementation for network
communication that goes to a server.
You'd have to use some other means like
the Apache libraries or something
like that in order to be able to do that
kind of communique.
[MUSIC]