[MUSIC]
What we're going to talk about now, is
something that, makes a lot more
sense, once we've gotten to the point,
where we're discussing, AIDL and Binder
RPC.
Because it's something that really figures
prominently in that context.
So, what we're going to talk about here,
is
we're going to start talking about, the
proxy pattern.
And as we'll see, the proxy pattern is a
pattern that appeared in a couple of
different places.
It appeared in the Gang of Four book,
where it's
focusing primarily on, a very simplistic,
way of doing proxies.
And then later, we'll see it appeared in
the POSA
1 book, where it was described a bit more
generally.
Focusing on communication that occurs in,
in
environments where you're going across
address spaces.
So, we're going to kind of merge these two
things together and we'll talk first about
the
pattern, and then we'll talk about how the
pattern gets applied in the context of
Android.
So, what's the context?
Well, the context is, in most environments
where you have to cross address
spaces, it's not really feasible to access
the, internal details of an object
directly.
If, if it's in a server process.
You just can't get to it from the client.
You're, you're separated from an
abstraction boundary that could be,
a logical boundary like you might have
with, say, Java.
Or it might actually be a physical qua,
physical boundary which is
protected by the hardware, where you have
things running in separate processes.
But whatever the case is, you can't get to
something directly.
And of course, Android provides this
Binder RPC mechanism,
which we can use to communicate, across
the, back plane
of the device, to talk between processes
that are always,
on the same device but in, in different
address spaces.
Another part of the context here, is that
as you start to develop your system over
time,
it's often the case that, you change your
mind about where you want your objects to
live.
Now, this is really easy to motivate,
when we start talking about a distributed
system.
In a distributed system, where you've got
networks involved.
You might start out with things perhaps
co-located in the
same address base or on the same machine,
for various reasons.
Simplicity of programming is the most
obvious one.
And then as your, customers start to scale
up or scale out, you
want to add more and more and more
processing to your, to your solution.
So, rather than putting everything
together in one address
space or in one machine, now you've got
multiple machines.
And so, in that case, you may start
changing where
things reside over time as your system has
to grow
or as you do profiling to learn where the
hotspots
are, where it slows down, and so on and so
forth.
But the point is that things are going to
change over time.
So what are the problems?
Well, one problem is that, manually
writing code to marshal and de-marshal
communication between address spaces, is
very
tedious, error prone, and just not
portable.
It's just a real pain, nobody wants to
write that code.
It's hard to maintain, and it's hard to
optimize.
So, you'd really like that to have to do
it yourself.
The second problem is, if you were able
to, rewrite a lot of code every time they
reconfigure, or redeploy their software,
to break things up
into different partitioning boundaries,
that's a lot of work.
And, if you program with lower level IPC
mechanisms, like sockets, for example.
The amount of work required to change,
from communicating between
things in the same address space to things
on, the
same machine to different processes, to
different processes on different
machines, it's a lot of work to do that by
hand.
And so, most people just give up very
quickly, they say to
heck with it, it's good enough, I'm not
going to worry about it.
So, these are they kinds of impediments
that we run into.
When we start trying to build systems that
have to be broken up, across different
address boundaries.
So, what's the solution?
Well, as you'll see there's a multi-part
solution here but one
piece of the solution, is to define
something called a proxy
and the proxy essentially acts as a
surrogate or an ambassador,
that gives a particular interface,
actually the same interface to the client.
And then, allows the implementation of the
interface to be some place else.
And that some place else could be, in
a different address space on the same
machine.
It might be, in the operating system
canal,
being accessed by an application running
in user level.
It might be another process on another
machine.
We don't really know, we don't really
care, all we
know is that, the proxy is allowing us to,
abstract
and encapsulate the details of where
things actually reside and
that'll allow us, a lot more flexibility
to move things around.
So, here's how you might do this on
Android.
You might go ahead and, and inherit a
remote
object from a Binder as we've been talking
about many
times and this Binder then allows you to
be able
to export that object to the, to the
receiver side.
Of course, the way in which you get a
proxy to do this thing is to
describe the interface to this via an AIDL
file, which says, what the methods are and
their signatures and so on, and then you
run that through the compiler, you get the
proxy, which is generated automatically
for you, and
then when a client invokes a method call.
On the proxy, it thinks, its accessing
something that's local.
It says, you know, service.download image
or download file or whatever.
It looks like it's making a local call,
when in fact it's actually calling
something elsewhere.
Now, where that thing resides, you can
control in
Android, by changing various directives in
the manifest files.
So, you control, whether or not the thing
is in the same
address space, or whether it's going to be
in a different address space.
You get some control over that, but the
point is that, whether it's in
the same or different, the proxy is
shielding you, from what's actually taking
place.
Now, as we'll see later, the proxy
pattern, is going to work together with,
the Android Binder RPC mechanism, in order
to implement the Broker pattern.
And we're not going to talk about that
quite yet.
That's going to come next.
But, be aware that, that's, that's kind of
where we're
headed on this thing, it's to talk about
Brokers.
The, the proxy is just piece of that.
If we were thinking about this in, broader
pattern concepts, we would say that the
broker was a pattern language, and the
proxy
was a, a piece of that pattern language.
And we'll, perhaps talk about that later.
Okay, so as always, these are not just
random assortments of classes thrown
together for adhoc reasons.
They, they fit in some grander scheme.
This grander scheme has been around for
quite a long time.
Some of the early work in this area, goes
back to, to 19, probably
the 1980's so it's been, you know, what,
30 plus years at this point.
For a lot of this stuff, it's has been
around for awhile.
And the pattern, is called the broker
pattern.
And the, I'm sorry, the pattern is called
the proxy pattern.
And the, intent of this pattern is to be
able to, provide a surrogate or place
holder for, an object to allow another
object
to access it, and control access to it.
You take a look here, for more information
about the proxy pattern.
There's a couple of different reasons why
you would use this.
The typical reason why you would use this
pattern is if you need to be able
to access, an object using something
that's more
powerful, than a simple pointer or a
simple reference.
Pointers and references that you find in
C++ and Java are great,
when you're talking to objects that are in
the same address base.
When you start having objects that reside
in
other address spaces, they don't work so
great
because they can't reach across those
address spaces,
so that's when we need to have proxies.
Another motivation here is to make it easy
to be
able to, change where the objects reside,
local versus remote.
Or co-located versus remote, without
changing the way that you
access them, so, those are the
considerations that might help you.
Another thing you might want to do here,
is if
you want to have some kind of strong type
checking.
Let me add that one just for fun.
Say, if there's say, when
there's a, benefit from having
strong statically-typed,
typed method invocations.
And what I'm really talking about here,
what I'm really comparing and contrasting
with, is
the approaches that use proxies, from
other approaches
that are based on more message passing
[COUGH].
We'll talk about those later.
Here's a quick synopsis of the structure
and participants in this pattern.
It's, it's pretty straight forward.
This is the, diagram from the Gang of four
book, we have a subject which is really
the
thing that's, that's the, defining an
interface, obviously in,
in the Android that's the thing that's
defined with AIDL.
We have the proxy, which is the guy that,
is shown to the client, which does the
magic under the hood, we'll talk about in
a
second, to get the, method turn it to
something
that can go over to the receiver side, to
the real object, the real subject, and in
Android,
that's of course handled by the, generated
code at
the STUB dot proxy, nested inside the STUB
class.
And then finally, we have the quote, real
subject, and in this case the real
subject would be some combination of STUB,
and
the actual implementation, in the context
of Android.
We start looking at this in a distributed
systems lens, or through a
distributed system lens, you'll see that
the Gang of four descriptions in this
pattern are a little bit meagre, and
there's other steps going on here,
to get to the other side, and turn it back
into a method call.
But for the purposes of our discussion
right
now, just think of the proxy being, the
local
surrogate, or local place holder, or local
ambassador,
to some object that may reside some place
else.
And when you invoke an operation on the
proxy, it does stuff, and
then it forwards the call, onto the real
subject to do the work.
This set of dyn, dynamics, diagrams kind
of illustrates
this point, in a little more detail so the
clients
starts out by getting a proxy from some
place, typically
from a factory of some kind, or the
factory method.
Once it's got the proxy, it then invokes
the method call on it.
As you can see here, most of the time,
you're using proxies to go across address
space boundaries.
Not always, but mostly.
And so, what's happening in this case, is
that the proxy, is turning
around and converting the method call that
was invoked on it, into some
kind of message stripping out, or taking
the bites that are coming in
as parameters, and turning of, the objects
that are coming in as parameters.
And, serializing them into, linear byte
sequences with a particular
encoding format and then somehow, and this
is the part
that's not talked about by the proxy
pattern, it's getting
it over to the real subject to do the
work.
And when the real subject is done, the
call returns.
Typically synchronously although you can
have various to do asynchronous
interactions.
And then it, takes the results back, puts
it in the message format, turns it back
into
whatever native format is responsible and
expected by
the caller and then returns, back to the
caller.
And so, either through return value, or
out parameters, or in out parameters or
something.
The results are updated and the client
gets the results back from the server.
So, it's basically method to message back
to method again.
That's kind of the way it works.
Okay, any questions about the steps,
either static or dynamic?
So, there's a number of interesting
consequences of applying this pattern.
One of the key ones, and then why it gets
used so much in distributed systems.
Is it allows you to, at least it, at least
in theory,
decouple, the location of an object from
the axis to that object.
So, you can change where that object
resides, without
changing other things, you don't have to
change the interface.
You don't have a lot of extra work to do
on your
behalf as a client application developer,
or as a server application developer.
You can also use it, to simplify tedious
and error-prone details.
This is just a little snippet of the code
that you would will see,
if you were to peek inside of the download
image proxy that's generated for you.
And as we looked at this before, it's kind
of messy and ugly.
Nobody in the right mind wants to write
that code and maintain it by hand.
It's just, just awkward.
So we'd much rather have it, be done for
you by the proxy writer [COUGH].
There are also, some potential overheads
however,
there's some potential liabilities or
downsides with this.
One of which is, you are at the mercy, of
the writer of the proxy generator.
If the writer of the proxy generator does
a good job, then you're in pretty good
shape.
It's probably equivalent to what you could
do by hand.
If the writer of the, the generator of the
proxy code does a bad job, you've
got lots and lots of overhead and there's
not a whole lot you can do about it.
Unless your middleware, gives you the
ability to, hand craft your own proxies
and plug them in, in place of the ones
that are automatically generated.
So, this is one of those topics that has
gone back and forth, and back and forth
for decades.
There was a time when, interface
generators were really bad.
And so, people did a lot of work on
optimizing things either by hands or by
writing better generators.
Just like everything else, over time
people get smarter about this stuff, and
so a well-written generator should be,
competitive
to code you would write by hand.
In fact, there was some interesting work
done, maybe, gosh, 15 years
ago or so by some folks at University of
Utah, on a.
Technique called flick, which was an IDL
compiler that was heavily optimized
to generate code that would be very fast
and it used programming language,
transformation and optimization techniques
to, analyse the code that needed to be
generated and come up with optimized ways
of generating the, the proxy code.
Interesting stuff.
Another potential downside, and this
really comes back to the issue I, I
added to the slides a second ago, having
to do with strong typing.
One of the other potential concerns with
proxy is, it will overly
restrict the type system, that you have
available, on the client side.
Now, this is a sort of subtle point and I
want to have some
discussion about it, to see what other
people's insights and impressions are
about this.
So, when you start using proxies, you're
really saying ahead of time, these
are the valid types, that can be passed
to, methods with a particular signature.
And here are the results that can come
back.
You're, you're tightly coupling those
things.
Now, when you write normal Java code, you
write
normal C++ code, you do that all the time.
So, that's not really an unusual thing to
do, at one level.
But when you start moving into, a
distributed environment, or an environment
where you're
separating out client and server, so that
multiple clients, are accessing a common
shared server.
All of a sudden, things get more
interesting and there was a, a fair amount
of backlash a number of years ago against
strongly and statically typed proxies in
middleware, for
distributing computing systems and the,
the alternative approach,
which you see by the way all the
time in, Things like SOAP and other
message
based or message oriented messaging
systems, XML based
messaging systems, is stuff where it's
more dynamically typed.
Where you actually create a message, you
build up
a message piece by piece, usually using
some kind of
internal coding, where you keep track of
the type tag,
like, like a tag in XML, along with the
data.
So they are self describing messages.
And you end up, instead of having an
interface
with lots of different methods with very
strongly typed signatures.
Instead, you have one interface called
send, that takes a message.
And the message can be done in some
arbitrary self describing way.
So, in fact if you take a look at the
messengers in Android, that's kind of the
way it is right?
You create a messenger.
And it's got a send method, it takes a
message and you
put bundles into the message, to put
anything you want into that.
So, does anybody want a hazard, an opinion
about,
the trade off and pros and cons between,
the
proxy like approach, which is more
statically typed and
the message based approache, which is more
dynamically typed.
Why would you choose one versus the other?
What are the pros and cons?
>> I like the static typing, because you
get, most of URLs upfront from the
compilers.
>> So, when you use a statically typed
approach, you're
letting the compiler and the other tools,
in the language
processing tool chain, determine early on
when you have inconsistencies
between the types that you're creating on
the client side.
And the things you're passing over to the
server side.
So, so strong typing, removing errors,
another thing
that comes along with that is often
optimization.
The more typing information is available,
you
could, the more you can optimize things.
With strong typing, you often don't have
to
send over, the type information, you can
basically have
the sender and receiver agree ahead of
time and
so the type information isn't sent with
the message.
Only the data is sent with the message, so
that amount of data that's used on
the network goes down and the amount of
data to be processed goes down and so on.
So those are, those are arguments in favor
of the strongly typed approach.
But there's another point of view.
I'll never forget, when I first started
programming back
in the mid 80s, I was reading about
Fortran
Programmers and C Programmers who didn't
like PASCAL and
they would always say, strong typing is
for weak minds.
[LAUGH] So, so what's the downside with
the,
with the proxy based approach, with the
stronger typing.
>> It's less flexible.
>> Less flexible, so what that really
means in this context is, as your
services evolve over time, if you have
strong typing and as your service evolves.
All the clients that rely on that service
have also
be evolved, to take advantage or to
utilize new type information.
And so, as a result, it becomes quote,
inflexible, because now you gotta go out
and change all the clients, and there
could be a lot of clients, and a
lot of those clients, you may not have any
control over, because they're belonging to
some other organization, some other
development team, some
external group, you have no knowledge of
whatsoever.
So, in those environments, especially if
you try to
do things like, large scale enterprise
system integration, its often
useful to have a, a model where you keep
the messages dynamically typed, so as you
evolve your services,.
Then, you can simply have your new
clients, new,
do new things, add new parts to the
message.
And when they send to the service, the
service will say, aha, I got
a message from a new, from a new client, I
know how to process that.
But, the old messages for the old clients,
will
still be handled without requiring changes
to the clients.
So, there is a lot of issues there
about trade-offs between forcing changes
to the edge
to the system, which is what you need
to do, if you have strong typing through
proxies.
First is to having the, typing decisions
done
by the service, which gives you more
flexibility
and dynamism, but, is typically slower,
has more
time and space overhead and also, leads to
surprises.
As, as Christoph was just saying, you
often don't really realize until the
system
is running, that people are sending you
gobbledygook that makes no sense at all.
So, there's all these interesting
tradeoffs.
So, that's a key thing to remember and
probably a good quiz question, that what
are the trade offs between, the strong
typing
and dynamic typing in the context of
proxy.
We'll see, we might or might not see
later, there, there's some use of this
in Android, but it's not, big enough to
maybe warrant as a full blown pattern.
There's a pattern called extension
interface which is widely used
in Microsoft Calm, and it some parts of
Enterprise Jacobean,
where you, basically have these things
called components and a
component is basically an object
on steroids, that exposes multiple
interfaces.
And each of those interfaces exposed by
the
component, are strongly tight and they
have proxies.
And what you do, is you have this little
kind of 20 questions, negotiation takes
place between the client
and the component, where the client goes
out and it
queries the component and says, do you
support this interface?
Oh, you don't okay, do you support this
interface?
You do, okay, thank you.
And so it takes what it gets back, and
then it makes method calls.
So, the, the so called extension
interface, is kind of this hybridization
between
static typing you get with proxy and more
flexibility that you get with
messaging, so it's, it kind of gives you
the best of both worlds,
or the worst of both worlds depending on
how you look at it.
Another problem you have with, with proxy
is
the fact that it's very difficult to
entirely
shield the application client, from the
fact that
there is a boundary, between sender and
receiver.
So, you might like to pretend as though,
it's invisible.
But invariably it's not.
And when things go wrong, there, there are
errors that occur, when you start running
things
in different address spaces, that do not
occur,
if things are co-linked in the same
address space.
If you make a method call on an object in
the same address space, network
unreachable is unlikely to occur, right?
Whereas, if you're running in something
that's
going across the Internet, then, you know,
someone might, cut the, network cable with
a back hoe or something like that.
Or the storm might blow down a wireless
tower and you lose connectivity or
whatever right?
So, these are things that you have to
be prepared for when you start programming
clients
using proxies, that you wouldn't have to
be
prepared for, if you were just making
normal calls.
There is a number of known uses here.
Most of these known uses are actually much
more interesting in the context of
the broker pattern, but they also use
proxies, so I'm just mentioning them here.
We'll talk about them later.
These son-RPC or the so called
open-network computing
RPC, or procedure call, model which
started back
in the middle 80s, which was a, a
successor to something that came out of
Xerox park.
On remote procedure calls by, Andrew
Berell and Bruce Nelson.
There's also the distributing computing
environment, DCE,
which came around the late 80's which was
kind of the, the end of the line,
a very convoluted, complicated C based,
RPC mechanisms.
What came next, was the combination of the
peanut butter of
distribution with the chocolate of
objects, to form distributed object
computing.
And you get things like sun rp, sun remote
method invocation,
or Microsoft's a decom, or the common
object request broker architecture, there
is kinds of object request brokers, in
this context CORBA and so
on, lot of stuff done there, they all use
proxies very heavily.
And in now a days, now were, you know,
20, 30 years down the road this stuff
resurfaces again,
but this time in the context of
communication between
processes, using the Binder mechanisms for
local inter process communication,.
On a, on the same device in Android
[COUGH].
And it's worth also noticing, if you click
on this link here you'll be
taken to, a little STUB that describes,
where the Android Binder framework came
from.
It actually came from, an earlier work
done
by BOS and I think maybe even Palm OS.
By a group of people led by Dianne
Hackborn, who's got the
coolest name of the programmers in the
world [LAUGH] born to hack, right?
We actually have a guy in ISIS named Doug
Hackworth, so he is a worthy hacker I
guess [LAUGH].
And so, they basically wrote this Binder,
and then that, they got bought, or they
conjoined the Android development some
part later, and
that's what the Android binder is based
on.
It's called something called the Open
Binder.
As I wrap up this section, and then we'll,
we'll migrate to the next topic.
I want to make some interesting
observations about proxies.
So, proxies are a great microcosm, of a
trend that's been going on in computing
for decades.
Ever since the very beginning of time and
that
trend is that, useful patterns evolve over
time into features
provided and supported automatically by
various kinds of language processing
tools, either programming languages or by
tools like AIDL components.
Here are some examples.
If you go back far enough in time, you'll
see
that, the early developers of Assembly
code, were using certain patterns
of writing Assembly code and those were
things that later found
their way into the, second generation
languages like FORTRAN and C.
Where they had things like, closed
subroutines, or IF/ELSE statements,
or switch statements, or loops or various
kinds of things.
Those things all started out by assembly
lines which programmers were saying, gosh,
if we
organize our assembly codes in these
patterns,
it will be easier for us to maintain.
And smart people like, John Backus who
invented the first
FORTRAN compiler, said, you know, we could
actually automate that.
We can build a tool, that does that for
us.
It's kind of funny if you go back in,
in the early days of compilation and
second generation languages.
There was all kinds of controversy between
the super duper assembler language
programmers, who
knew how to write really tight assembly
code and register, do register allocation
by hand.
And all these new fangled developers who
were
trying to write compilers to automate that
stuff.
There was a lot of controversy, people
said, you'll never be
able to write, a compiler that can
generate code, you know,
better than I can write in Assembly and so
on and
so forth, which always amazes me and
amuses me to no end.
Whenever new technology comes along,
that's threatening
to the status Quo, people always start
out up by, by downplaying its relevance
and then later on they go oh, well.
You know maybe, maybe it solves a few
problems but it
doesn't solve all the problems, and then
at some point, they've been
completely overwhelmed and overtaken, and
you don't even think twice you just,
you just do it without even, even stopping
to think about it.
By the way that meta pattern or mega
pattern is described very nicely in
a series of books by, Clayton Christenson,
who writes about the innovators dilemma
and the so called disruptive technologies,
that come along, I won't go into
it in detail right now, but, it's worth
looking into because it's great stuff.
So the point there is that, what was
once patterns then find their way, into
language features.
Another set of examples, if you go back to
the,
so what I just described was from the
early 60's.
You go back into the early 70's.
There were still a lot of people writing
code in Assembly language,
and a lot of people writing code in C at
that time.
And they were beginning to write bigger
systems.
And they had to figure out some way, of
hiding information, so that
their application developers, which were
using themselves,
because the programs weren't all that big.
They wouldn't end up making tight
coupling, on
implementation details that were likely to
change over time.
So, if you recall when we, when we do
2-51, we talk about stacks, and we talk
about
different ways of hiding the
representation of the stack
to avoid writing code that relies on
particular implementation.
So, what happened there, is people began
to come
up with patterns for hiding information,
so like in
C, you make stuff static, or you could
find
header file with a bunch of functions and
so on.
And what grew out of that, information
hiding approach.
The patterns of information hiding, really
turned into the language features
for things like classes, packages, and
other ways of being able to.
Automatically and with, through automation
and through automatic checking and
language
tools, be able to make sure that things
really do stay private.
You can't access stuff, you can make
access control checks, to keep things from
happening.
When C++ first started out and for
actually at
least a decade or so after it started out.
It didn't have any support for
premoridized types.
Which was, uncomfortable and inconvenient.
Java was the same way for a long time by
the way.
So, back in those days, people
would, follow patterns of preprocessor
directives.
Or writing little tools with said and oc
and so on, in order to, annotate
their code with, template-like syntax that
would
then be, pre-processed and turned into
actual code.
That experience with Mac or these other
tools, led to people
writing, templates and adding them to C ++
as a template feature.
There's lots and lots and lots more
examples, so, people doing things like the
iterator pattern that we learned in 251,
we've talked about here a little bit.
The iterator pattern is something that
used to be done by convention.
Nowadays, you take a look at Java, you
take
a look at C++ 11, they've baked the
iterator pattern
into the language, with things like range
based for loops,
or the for each loop in Java, and so on.
So once again, you see this never-ending
trend, towards moving stuff from,
convention into automation.
And there's pros and cons, for that of
course.
[MUSIC]