[MUSIC]
Okay, so today we're going to continue
talking about
the Broker pattern, focusing on the
implementation of Broker
in the context of Android, as well as
talking
more generally about what it means to
implement Broker.
And we're also going to talk
about another pattern called the
Publisher-Subscriber pattern.
And we'll talk about how those things are
realized in Android as well.
So first let's talk about the Broker.
If you recall, last class, at the end of
last class, we talked about the Broker,
and I
talked about how Broker is a pattern
that's used
to shield clients from communication
mechanisms and infrastructure concerns.
When they talk to services implemented in
servers, which
typically run in processes either, either
on the same machine
or in a separate machine, and we talked
about how
the Broker takes care of all the low level
details.
Things like connection management, data
transfer protocols, concurrency control,
synchronization,
threading, some fault tolerance thrown in
there, memory management, all
that kind of good stuff, that low level
stuff, is sort
of hidden from you and encapsulated by the
underlying Broker mechanisms.
And, so we talked last time about the good
and the bad about the Brokers.
And sort of the applicability and so on.
And now what we're going to do is we're
going to talk about how you might
implement a Broker.
And of course, we're going to do it in the
context of Android.
So one of the first things you need to do
is
figure out what is your invocation
interface going to look like?
Now, there's a couple of different ways to
ask this
question, and one way to ask the question
is what's the
client application's interface going to
look like, and do you
want to make it as transparent as possible
from the client?
So, if you want transparency, you're
going to want to use some Broker, or
some proxy like mechanisms, and we're
going to get to that in a second.
What I'm thinking about here is a little
bit lower level than that.
It's, what's the interface that a proxy,
or
an application that wants to program a
little
closer to the metal, going to use in order
to pass something to the Broker itself.
So how does a client invoke an operation
on the Broker?
And so, basically what we're going to do
is
come up with a way to allow somebody,
either
the client or the client's proxy, to pass
a message from the client over to the
server.
And if you take a look here, you can see
the way this is done in Android, is
something that's actually provided for
the, by the underlying infrastructure,
it's this, this transact method, and
transact is, is used to send the data.
It's, it's something that's exposed by the
binder class, which is the
lower level mechanisms that does
communication
in Android, a lower level mechanism.
There's lower levels in the binder, we'll
talk about in a minute.
But basically it provides a method called
transact, and you call transact with
the code, which is basically the method
that you're calling, as well as
a parcel that contains the data that you
want to have sent to
the server, as well as how you want the
reply information to come back.
And so that information, plus some other
flags, are actually used to send the data.
And when you call, when somebody calls
transact,
which turns out typically to be the proxy.
Calls it under the hood and it ends up
calling the on
transact method, and that will get
delivered over to the server side, and
there's an on transact method that gets
called back on the stub,
and that's how the data gets up called to
the, to the server.
We'll talk about that in a second.
If you take a look at the binder code in
Android, if you take a look at
binder.java, you'll see this
implementation and it looks
more or less like what I've shown you
here.
The next thing you need to do is you need
to select and implement the marshaller.
If you recall, there were sort of three or
four main things you have in the Broker
pattern.
You've got the client, obviously.
You've got a requester, which is the
client side part that invokes an
operation.
You have the marshaller, or demarshaller,
which
is responsible for serializing and
unserializing the
messages, and you have this thing called
the dispatcher, and those are the key
pieces.
And that's responsible for dispatching the
request to
the servant, which is what actually
implements things.
So, the marshaller has different pieces to
it but, this
is typically what's handled for you by the
proxy pattern,
so I'm not going to talk a lot about here
because
we just covered that in length in the
proxy discussion.
But in a nutshell as you all know, the
AIBL compiler generates the code to
do the proxy operations and it basically
takes a look at the data types you
define in the AIBL interface, and then it
creates the appropriate calls to the lower
level Java code to marshal and demarshal
things from native data types into these
parcels.
So as you can see here, for example, if
we're
using our download image stuff, then
there's going to be
this write string call here, which is
going to go
ahead and take the, the URL, the URI or
whatnot.
Oops, that should be URI and it's going to
go ahead and write that
thing into the parcel, and then the parcel
will be passed over as part
of the invocation with the transact method
on the remote binder.
So we've already covered a lot of that
stuff but what we're about to
cover though now is a little bit deeper
than what we covered with proxy.
Proxy kind of stops at the point where
things start to get interesting.
So proxy is responsible for turning a
method call into
a message of some kind, a parcel in
Android's case.
But then it has to deliver that parcel
somehow.
How does it get there?
Well, there has to be some kind
of protocol to communicate between sender
and receiver.
And, inevitably, these protocols typically
use some kind of low level,
byte screen or record oriented
communication mechanism, some type of
transport.
There's different choices, different
middleware cakes that implements Brokers.
Some dataware uses datagrams or
connectionless communications where you
don't set
up a channel, or you don't setup state and
send and receiver
ahead of time, you just send the data out
and you either
assume it gets there, or you don't care if
it gets there.
Or you have some kind of retransmission
protocol that is
used at a higher level to make it get
there.
That's conectionless communication.
Android doesn't do that.
Much more common in certain kinds of
middleware, especially object oriented or,
not object oriented procedure call
environments,
is to use connection oriented protocols.
So the classic example of a connection
oriented protocol
would be something like TCP/IP, where it
sets up
a connection and establishes state on both
the sender
and receiver, and then the data begins to
flow.
Does anybody know why TCP/IP sets up state
on the sender and receiver, and the kernel
of the sender receiver protocol machines,
prior to
starting to try to deliver the actual
data.
What's, what's the reason why the state
is, is setup?
First of all, does anybody know what
TCP/IP does?
Can someone explain to me what TCP/IP
does?
>> It establishes a handshake between two
endpoints.
>> Right handshake to handshake is
established, but whats, whats the
handshake doing?
What's it, what's it getting you?
Why, why do we need it?
Or, what-
>> Sequence numbers.
[INAUDIBLE].
>> Right, exactly, reliability is the
reason.
So, if both sides understand the data that
will
be past, then they can keep track to see
if anything got dropped along the way by
keeping
track of sequence numbers and
acknowledgements and so on.
And by exchanging that information ahead
of time and kind
of presynchronizing them, the starting
sequence numbers and so on, then
it makes it possible to not only route the
information more
efficiently, but also to be able to do it
more reliably.
So if something gets dropped, the receiver
knows
it was expecting it and it didn't get it.
And so, there's a protocol that goes back
and forth
to try to retransmit the data if it gets
dropped.
And there's a whole bunch of other things
that get added to
TCP/IP to make it work in a variety of
different [UNKNOWN] products.
So that gives you reliability, that's what
we use for the internet.
In Android, we use a little bit lower
level mechanism that's implemented
as part of the OS kernel by something
called the binder driver.
And the binder driver is more of a
proprietary proprietary's the wrong word,
kind of a
purposed, customized protocol design for
high performance communication
between processes that run on the same
machine.
And, under the hood, it's implemented with
some low
level system calls called IOCTL's, or
I-O-C-T-Ls, IO controls.
And there's a bunch of different sort of
header information that gets passed back
and forth.
There's certain flags that get sent.
This thing called binder.
Write and read is the flag that's passed
into the
IOCTL to inform that data is being sent
back and forth.
There's also a struct called binder
transaction data,
that keeps track of a bunch of fields.
Things like what the buffer is that
contains the bytes
and some other information that is used by
the lower level.
A binder driver transport to move the
information back and forth.
And so that's kind of what's going on
under the hood.
This is not something you would typically
use
in a network environment, it's really
intended for
the relatively low latency back plane that
you
would find if you're running in the same
device.
It's sort of optimized for that kind of,
kind of world.
There's a nice paper that you could read
about, or
a nice presentation that I have a link for
here
that gives a lot more information about
the low level
details of how the binder driver is
implemented in Android.
It's actually part of the Android Linux
kernel extensions.
Now, the next thing I'm going to talk
about here, I colored it
red because it doesn't apply directly to
Android but, most Broker implementations
are running in, or many Broker
implementations are actually running in a
network environment, not a stand alone
back playing connected by a bus
environment.
So if that's the case, you have to have
some kind of network communication.
And there's a bunch of things you need to
think about in that case,
about the protocols you use to talk across
the network, which are often TCP/IP based.
And then other, just mechanisms you might
want to add.
Things like acceptors and connectors and,
reactors and so on.
And, and these are things we're not really
going to cover here because Android
doesn't have that capability.
But if you start studying networked
communication, and networked programming
environments, things like ACE, or Python's
Twisted, or other parts of Java like
Jedi and Neti and so on, you'll find lots
of examples of
these kinds of patterns used as part of
the network communication layers.
But we're not going to really cover them
right now.
The next thing you have to think about if
you're trying to
build a Broker is think through the issues
related to resource management.
So, resource management is an important
part of any
system, especially as it scales because
you want to make sure
that these resources that are in high
demand, but
somewhat scarce supply, are properly
allocated and de-allocated by something.
The operating system, the middleware or
some combination.
And the key point here is that you don't
have an infinite amount of this stuff.
What are some good examples of resources
that
you don't really have an infinite amount
of?
In, in the context of a Broker or some
kind of communications system.
>> Ports?
>> Ports.
Great, great example.
So ports are typically end points of
communication
that queue up data that goes to them.
They're, it's, they're addressable
somehow.
And you don't have an unlimited number of
ports, you'll eventually run out.
Of course, why do you eventually run out
of ports?
But what's the other resource that you
only have
so much of before you run out of it?
>> Memory?
>> Memory, right.
So there's only so much memory.
So you have to manage memory.
You have to memory, mem, manage ports.
Other things you typically want to manage
would
be connections, which are often related to
ports.
Threads, that's a big issue.
You don't want to have, you know, you
don't want to start spawning
threads just endlessly, because you will
quickly run out of them.
And if you don't run out of them, you'll
run out of
memory and then you'll have all kinds of
thrashing and props like that.
So, there's a bunch of different patterns
that people
have used over time to implement effective
resource management.
And, these are protocols.
These are services and so on.
So some examples that you might want to
use in the
context of a Broker would be things like
caching and pooling.
Which at first glance sounds similar, but
they have a little bit different purpose.
So oftentimes, we use caching on the
client side in order
to have information held open, even if
it's not currently being used.
So a good example of a cache might be some
kind of connection cache.
Where you might share a connection to a
server, and as
you allocate those connections, you might
cache them on the client.
So, if you have multiple threads that are
trying
to write, they can share access to the
cached connection.
So that's one example of something.
A pool might be something like a pool
of threads, where you preallocate a bunch
of threads.
You have them running say on the server
side.
And when a request comes in, the incoming
binder driver picks a
thread out of the pool and gives it the
work to do.
So pooling and caching are really both
designed in
order to preallocate and or allocate and
remain allocated resources
so that things don't have to be set up and
torn down from scratch every time, thereby
improving overall throughput.
So a good, good quiz question would be
what are some examples of resource
management and
what do they buy you, in the context
of the Broker pattern, or something like
that.
There's some publications you can see
these appeared in a POSA3 book.
You can also take a look at them on the
website
of the authors of the POSA3 book talk
about pooling and caching.
Another thing that you need is some kind
of registration interface that's
used by the dispatcher to be able to
register and unregister servants.
Servants, keep in mind, are the things
that actually
get requests dispatched to them, by the
underlying Broker middleware.
So, in the context of general purpose
distribute computing people
have defined things like object adapters
to do this kind of stuff.
In the context of Android, we have
something that's called, the binder.
And one of the methods that the binder
defines is called attatchInterface.
And you pass into that some information
about the interface, and
this gets stashed away so you're, you're
able to know about
it and you can find a way to get back to
it later when you need to do call backs on
it.
And you can take a look, all of the source
code is available here.
Another thing we need to be able to do, if
we
want to implement a Broker, is figure out
some way of being able
to communicate between the client and the
server, so the client
gets access to the servants that the
server is managing and owning.
So how do, how do you communicate that
information back and forth?
There's lots and lots of different ways to
do this.
In more traditional distributed Broker
environments, you typically
use some kind of naming service, or some
kind
of dictionary or directory service to be
able
to map names to object references or
something else.
And that's needed because we oftentimes
need to look these things up more like you
would search things with a Google search,
you want to type in a bunch of properties,
and then you get back a bunch of options
and you choose one or more
of them to, to invoke, in the case of
Android, it's a little bit different.
It's a little bit more tightly coupled.
So, there's a protocol that's defined here
that has a couple of parts to it.
One part is the onBind factory method
that's
defined by the server who implements the
binder object, and that is responsible
for giving back to the caller, which is
ultimately going
to be the client an, reference, an iBinder
to the binder.
So iBinder is interfaced to a binder and
you can use it to invoke operations.
And you can take a look at the service
interface to find out more about that.
The other thing is to find on the client's
side is a
hook method called onServiceConnected to
get this binder back from the server.
Or the service, and then stash it away
someplace on the client side, so it's
available for being used to invoke these
two way operations, or one way operations
later.
So there's kind of this multistep
protocol, as you
may recall, where you do a bind service
that causes on bind to get called on
the server that passes you back, a binder,
object.
That binder object comes back to you
through onServiceConnected.
The hook method.
You get that thing and then you can use it
to invoke operations.
So that's how Android gets the information
back to the, to the client.
And you can take a look here, for
much more information about the service
connection interface.
Another thing we need is some kind a
mechanism
to be able to transform these request
messages that
are coming in from the requester into up
calls
that are dispatched on a method defined by
our servant.
Now, keep in mind in, in the case of
Android, the servant
is basically whatever, typically
anonymous, object
subclassed anonymously from stub, and then
fills
in the various methods that have been
defined on that stub in
order to carry out the work that was
described in the AIDL interface.
So, in this particular case, this is
handled by the stub.
When the generated stub comes out, it has
a, an onTransact method, and that
onTransact method will
take a look at the particular code that
was
passed over by the transmit, or the
transact call.
And that transact call will then end up
dispatching the onTransact callback, which
looks at the
code, which tells it how to demarshall the
various fields that are passed over in the
parcel.
And then that's turned into native data
types, in this case, which
are then passed to the up call method, to
the actual servant implementation.
In this case, we are doing the download
image method for our download interface.
Our download interface.
So that just gives you a sense of how
those things fit together.
So that kind of illustrates all the
different pieces that
are involved, a client invokes a method on
a proxy, the
proxy turns the method into a message,
calls the transact method
to pass it down to the Broker, through the
requester portion.
The requester sends it across using
that binder driver communication protocol,
comes up
on the receiver side, the dispatcher
receives the request, takes a look at
it, figures out who it's for using the
lookup mechanisms that were defined
by the registration interface we looked
at,
and then ultimately, finds the right stub.
And then invokes the operation on that
stub to go ahead and, and
call back on the, the servant's
implementation method to get the job done.
So that's kind of the steps involved.
And then there's also a reverse order
going the other direction if there's a
reply.
Something else you need to do if you want
to start implementing Broker is
figure out whether or not you're going to
support asynchrony, or just simply stick
with synchrony.
Traditional Brokers tended to only support
synchronous communication, because
they were trying to mimic two way,
procedure call interfaces.
So, a regular procedure call is a two way
call.
So, for many years, remote procedure calls
were kind of two way calls.
And early versions of Corba were like that
too.
If you didn't like that, you used kind of
one way calls, but that had some down
sides.
Later on, people began to realize, this is
kind of limited.
We really want to support asynchrony as a
first
class citizen in the type system of the
Broker.
And so people started adding new support
to that.
In Corba they have something
call asynchronous method invocation for
example.
And asynchronous method handling, which
are used to
be able to give you better support for
asynchroni.
Microsoft Com has something similar, along
those lines as well.
In Android, they don't really build it
indirectly, but you can do it, by pattern
convention, where you pass a callback
object to the, via a one
way operation on the the interface, the
ideal interface that goes to the server.
That callback object is stashed away
somewhere
and then is used later, either in the
same thread or some other thread, to
invoke a one way call back to the client.
So you have to decide how to do it.
Android doesn't really give you a lot of
sophisticated support for this, but
it is possible to do it, and I find it a
very useful feature.
And then the last thing to think about if
you're trying to implement a Broker,
obviously there's more stuff than this,
but this is the key things to think about,
is whether or not you want to try to do
colocation optimizations for cases where
you're invoking a method on something
that's
in the same address space as the caller.
So if you end up having your servant in
the same address base
as your client, you want to do something
to, to match those things up.
And as you can see, the generated methods
called
as interface actually have some checks to
see whether
or not the call that's coming in is
actually
resolvable in the same address space as
the client.
And if it is, it just returns back the,
the interface directly to the
caller, and you can invoke a method call
that goes straight to that thing.
If it's not colocated in the same address
base, then it ends up making a
proxy and returning the proxy, and when
the proxy's called, that does all the
things
the proxy does, due to marshalling of the
data and then the transmission of it
through the binder mechanism and the
binder driver
and so on, over to the receiver side.
Any questions about any of that?
Some more information here at this link
about colocation optimizations, just
talking about the overall concept and
showing the speed ups involved.
So now that we've kind of seen the Broker
pattern implemented
in various steps and kind of walked
through how Android does
it under the hood, let's give some
examples of some
pretty cool sophisticated uses of the
Broker pattern in Android itself.
So this particular example uses the
network settings activity, you
can see here thanks to Kristof, we have a
screen
shot that he, managed to purloin through
torturous path to
get a screen shot of what this app looks
like.
And basically what it does is it goes out
and it searches
for cellular networks, like, you know,
CDMA or GSM or multiple providers which
you may or may not have, depending on what
kind of service you
have, if it's locked, unlocked, carrier
provided, where you are and so on.
But basically here's what it does.
There's a activity side of this thing
called network settings,
and that invokes start service, and that
causes the causes the
activity manager service to go ahead and
start up the network
query service using the activator pattern
that we talked about before.
And then that goes ahead and
initializes the it initializes that
particular service.
[COUGH] And then here's kind of the quirky
part.
Right after it calls start service, the
network settings
activity, then makes a call to bind
service, which
is a little weird because it's, it's kind
of
this Frankenstein monster that's a little
bit of both worlds.
It's a started service, that our, the
network query service is what they started
service
because start service was called, and a
bound service, because bind service was
called on.
And the basic idea, the basic reason that
they did this, does anyone want to
hazard a guess as to the reason why they
actually did it this way?
What was the reason?
Blows the motivation for this in Android.
Yes, sir?
>> Do bound services die when there's
nobody else that's bound to it?
Or if you start it first, then it's a
started
service so it's not going to die unless it
has to?
>> Right.
So they want it to be able to keep this
service running around even if nobody was
talking to it.
Which is kind of funny.
That kind of flies in the face of a lot
of what they say in Android about not
doing this.
But this is sort of a system disease
service, so I guess they figured that
it was okay for having it running
there in the background and consuming some
resources.
So yeah, that's exactly right.
So start service causes it to be launched,
and because it
was started, it won't shut itself down
automatically, but they want it
to be able to make AIDL calls to it so
they
used bind service in order to get back the
appropriate binder mechanism.
Yeah, there's some other things they could
of done to do
that, but that was the most
straightforward way to do it.
So that calls the onBind method, which
goes ahead and grabs the binder.
Returns it back by the callback to
onServiceConnected, and it goes ahead and
onServiceConnected actually
turns around and invokes a method called
loadNetworksList,
which is a method running in the activity.
And this method turns around and calls to
the MBinder object in the service,
and it invokes the start network query
method, which is a one way call.
And then that goes ahead and starts this
lookup process, where its checking to see
whether or not the, the underlying network
service is, is changed, or what it's
doing.
And this actually requires some, some sort
of registration
with the low level radio interface layers
service mechanisms,
which will actually deliver results back
via handlers at
some point down the road to the network
query service.
And when this stuff comes back at some
point
down the road, then there's another
callback that takes
place in the handle message callback which
is being
driven by low level stuff from the radio
interface layer.
It invokes a callback to invoke the on
query complete method,
passing back the list of network providers
that are out there.
Which are then displayed so you can see
what they look like.
So it's, it's just this really
interesting,
totally asynchronous use of the Broker
pattern.
Illustrating activator, illustrating
proxy, illustrating
the Broker, you know all
this stuff that we've been talking about
all kind of comes
together, and there's both, and it's
basically using an asynchronous
communication mechanism to make everything
work together and not block anything.
One of the most important reasons why you
would use asynchroni of course is to avoid
blocking.
Because that's a downside where you don't
want the main throw to control the block.
Okay, so to summarize the Broker, you have
support
in Android via the binder and AIDL for
Broker.
You have support for started services,
which use the command processor pattern to
do message passing, and in some sense
then, Broker and, and
command processor or pattern compliments,
you can use them in different purposes.
They sort of compete with each other.
And if we talk about last quiz, you would
choose one over
the over depending on the circumstance of
which you find yourself arising.
It is your job, or the job of whoever
you work with, to understand the tradeoff
between these patterns.
And one of the nice things you get from
understanding this stuff as patterns, as
opposed to just
understanding them in terms of the
features that Android
provides, is that it gives you a bird's
eye
view of the tradeoffs between
architectural alternatives and, ironically
enough, as you switch between platforms,
as you switch from Android to iOS,
as you switch from smartphones to clouds,
or whatever you move to, you'll find that
these patterns exist in almost all of
those different contexts.
And once you understand the design
alternatives and tradeoffs in terms of
patterns,
it's a heck of a lot easier to navigate
through the design space.
Whereas if you understand them only as
specific details of one platform like
Android
or Jedi or Nedi or Corba or DDS or
whatnot, then as you start
moving around, you'll, you'll have to
relearn
everything from the details up, which
takes
a long time and you may miss some of the
important commonalities that exist there.
[MUSIC]