[MUSIC]
So what we're going to do today is
we're going to start talking about various
patterns
that are associated with different binder
mechanisms,
different AIDL mechanisms, different bound
and unbound services.
If you recall, we talked about the command
processor
pattern in the context of started
services, and now we're
going to start talking about some of the
other patterns associated
with both started services as well as with
bound services.
The first pattern we're going to talk
about
is a pattern called the activator pattern.
As you'll see, this pattern appear in a
couple of places.
It appears in a paper, that I wrote, that
has
appeared in a couple of different venues
over the years,
that I was a coauthor on, and a small
snippet
of this particular pattern appears in the
POSA four book.
When we redo the POSA two book next
summer, this pattern
will appear as a full blown pattern in the
POSA two book.
So here's the context of this pattern.
It's often the case when you're building
software
that you run in, in a resource constrained
environment.
Where, it's not necessarily appropriate to
preallocate a lot of resources.
For example, in many smartphone
environments random
access memory, RAM, is a fairly precious
commodity.
And even though we've got a lot of memory
now in Android and iPhone, you
never can have enough, so you have to be
careful to, to over-allocate this stuff.
In older versions of Android particularly,
they
were much more memory constrained, they
only
had, you know, hundreds of megabytes, not
gigabytes worth of memory back in those
days.
And so as a result, it was even more
important to think carefully about how
many resources were available.
The problem of course is if you're in
a memory constrained environment it's not
really appropriate to
have all your services running all the
time,
if they're not actually being accessed by
the clients.
Because if they're running and nobody is
using them, then you're chewing up
resources, and
if resources are precious, in other words
you don't have a, a large amount of them.
Then when someone comes along to run the
next
application and there is already a bunch
of services that
is taking up memory but are not being
used, then
the next service to be launched may very
well fail.
Even though there's plenty of available
space, if you were to reclaim
the stuff that isn't being accessed on a,
on a regular basis.
So you can see here, we have a couple
of different services that are running,
and when the
next service comes along, there's not
enough room, even
though they're not all being accessed at
the same time.
There's more discussion about memory
management on Android.
Here, at this particular link, and
there's, specifically, some
discussions about services that we'll talk
about in a second.
So, what's the solution to this particular
problem.
Well, it turns out to be pretty
straightforward, and it's something that
Android does.
It's something that a lot of environments
do,
a lot of middleware does this kind of
stuff.
A lot of networking programming, toolkits
and environments do this kind of thing.
It's something called the Activator
pattern.
And is used to activate and deactivate
services on demand.
So basically if you have service that, to
do work, don't
bother running it if there is nobody there
to access it.
And that's pretty much how the android
services work.
If you think about it.
Started services, get started when someone
evokes
start service, it passes it in an intent.
Bound services get started the first time
they're
accessed, and they run as long as the
client has a binding to them, and once
that binding goes away, they evaporate
into thin air.
naturally, somebody, either you, or the
middleware has to be responsible for
keeping
track of these services, to make sure that
they get shut down appropriately.
So they don't end up leaking resources
when when nobody's using them.
Or you don't end up you know, keeping them
around and leaking resources.
And doing silly things that make it
difficult to reclaim the, the memory.
And we'll go through this particular
diagram a little bit more detail later.
As you can see here basically what happens
in android is whenever
you evoke bind service, be it a starting
service or a bound service.
It'll go ahead and check to see if the
service is running.
And if it's not, it does this by
talking to something call the activity
manager service.
And the activity manager service act,
plays the role of the
activator, and it's got some other stuff
we'll talk about shortly.
And what it does is it goes out and checks
to
see if there's a process running that is
running this service already.
If so, it goes ahead and basically says,
you're it do your thing.
If it's not the one, if there's not one
running it goes ahead
and starts it up, and then at some point
later, say we're doing
a 2-way communication with AIGL on the
binder, then when the invocation takes
place it gets routed to the service that's
up and running at that point.
But Android has started that service
on-demand.
And, there's some more information here at
this URL that talks about,
how to manage service life cycles
appropriately in Android to conserve
memory.
Now, is always the case when we start
talking
about these kinds of arrangements of
software, this is not
just a random collection of classes, put
there for some
arbitrary reason, there is some thinking
that went behind it.
And that thinking is something that's been
something
documented in the literature, called the
activator pattern.
And the activator patterns intent is
essentially to automate the scalable on
demand activation and deactivation of
service
execution contexts, which is just a fancy
name that means, a process, a thread, a
container or something, to run
services that are accessed by clients
without requiring the consumption of
excessive resources.
'Cause things aren't actually running
unless they're used.
So you take a look at this link, you'll
get a paper that talks
about activator, and as I've said there's
other places to learn more about it.
So when would you apply this pattern?
Well, you typically apply this pattern in
situations where you have services in a
system
that really don't need to run, unless
somebody
is actually accessing them at that
particular time.
Now, here's an interesting question.
And we'll talk about this a little bit
later when we get to the consequences
section.
But is it the case that, every service is
such that you can start
it on demand, or are there some services
that may need to be prestarted?
Does anybody have any thoughts about that?
Why wouldn't you just always launch things
on demand?
What would be a reason for that?
>> They take a long time to launch?
>> If they take a long time to launch,
right.
Some things take a while to start up.
Back in the sort of the bad old days of,
of Java,
before people did lots of clever
optimizations to the VMs and so on.
When you first started the java
application, it took a lot of run,
because it had to load in all the classes
in the class library.
And that took a while.
And you know, imagine what would happen if
you wanted
to launch an application in your android
phone, and you push
that icon, and you have to wait for five
seconds
for the thing to load, right, you will be
pretty frustrated.
So, so clearly, you know somethings have
to be able to be [SOUND] ready
to go, hit the ground running, People have
solved that problem by various ways.
Typically the trick is either to load
things partially, so they start out and
then they load incrementally, or to
preload
them, to pre-load some things from the
beginning.
What are some other reasons why you might
want to, to not have things launched on
demand?
So starting up the, it, it's all, it's all
related to the idea of taking too long to
start.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
So certain kinds of real time operations
where you're sampling the temperature
of a nuclear reactor core, you probably
want to make sure that you
have very high accuracy or your checking
some condition in your anti-lock
braking system to see whether you car is
skidding, or something like that.
You don't want to sit there and launch
these services on demand, they've gotta be
up
and running because they may be part
of the safety critical, or mission
critical part.
So the point of this is, is
that this patterns not always applicable,
it's applicable
when there's situations where, you only
need
to consume resources if somebody's
actually using you.
And also if the client can benefit from
being shielded from where services
are located, how they're deployed, when
they're deployed, how their life cycle's
managed.
In other words we can decouple the client
from some of these bookkeeping
life cycle kinds of issues, and sometimes
that's possible, and sometimes it's not.
So you have to kind of decide in your
environment what's the appropriate
consideration about latency of startup
time, re, reaction time, and, and so on.
And we'll talk more about that a little
bit further along.
So here's a view of the structure and
participants to this pattern.
And there's a lot of pieces.
But they're all fairly straightforward.
So, especially in their mapping onto
Android.
So there's a client.
And the clients, whomever's going to do
something that requires a service to run.
So, in our environment, that would be like
an activity, that
wants to start a service, by start service
or bind service.
And then we have some way of identifying a
service,
and there's lots and lots of ways to
identify services.
If, for example, if we were programming
some kind of internet application, we
would probably
identify the service by some combination
of
IP address or hostname, and a port number.
That's how we might identify a service.
So the FTP services is at port 21, and so
on, the http services at port 80, and so
on.
In the case of Android, we identify
services by intents.
And we either do it through explicit
intents or
we say, please go run this particular
.class file.
Or we do it through so called implicit
intents where
we say, here's an action I want you to
perform
or, here's some data, go find someone who
knows how
to launch a URL that starts with,
maps.doogle, .google.com, alright?
You can, you can do it different ways,
that's how you identify services.
There's then something called the service
proxy, which
is what the client sees, in order to
be able to do an operation, that will
eventually cause a service to start up and
run.
And in Android that's typically done by
the context.
Right, so you have operations like bind
service, or start service, which are done
through the service proxy, which is the,
which is the proxy, the context
information.
Then you have the activator itself.
The activator itself is really this agent
that interposes itself between the
client, who wants work done, and the
service, that wants the work to be done.
Think of the activator as sort of a, like
a Hollywood mogul,
whose job it is, is to connect producers
with movie stars, right?
You don't necessarily call the movie stars
directly, you call their agent.
Think about, you know, sports, sports
stars.
You don't call the person directly, you
call their agent, right?
So there's this intermediary role.
That's the activator.
And the activator makes use of something
called the activation table.
And the activation table keeps track of,
who's out there, that's actually up and
running, to be able, to handle, the new
request that came in from the client.
And then we have something called the
service execution
process, oh, and, and the activation table
in, in
Android for what we're talking about, is
something that's
part of the activity manager service
called the service map.
And the activator in this case is
the activity manager, or activity manager
service.
And then we have the service execution
context.
That's where the actual work gets done,
that's
the context in which the work gets done.
In the case of Android that's a LINUX
process, or more precisely a thread
within a LINUX process, but it's something
that's managed by the underlying operating
system.
And then, finally, we have the service
itself
that does work on the behalf of whomever.
And so, an example of this would be some
subclass or
some implementation that intent service,
that's actually going to do the work.
So that's a nice, quick mapping of the
contents of the pattern onto
all the various mechanisms that Android
provides in order to carry that out.
What's so cool about this is, is it's
really not a stretch at all.
I mean these are really all fairly
straight forward mappings of Android
classes, Android mechanisms, directly onto
the things that are on the pattern.
But the pattern was written, you know,
many years before,
many years before Android was even a
glimpse in someone's eye.
Showing once again the generality of
patterns.
Here's an interaction diagram that kind of
shows the
dynamic communication between the
different roles and responsibilities here.
The client starts out by invoking an
operation, and
perhaps unbeknownst to the client, perhaps
beknownst to the client,.
There's an activator that's actually
interposed between the
client's request and the actual service
that gets run.
In the case of Android, it's kind of
obvious that
there's somebody going in there, because
you call start service.
Or you call bind service, so that it's
kind of, it
kind of makes it clear that somebody's
doing something to get things running.
In other environments, such as internet
application development, where
you are connected to port 80, or to port
21, or what not, it's not quite so obvious
that there's somebody is getting involve
as an intermediary.
And yet other middleware like Corba, as
we'll talk about in a second.
It's totally hidden from you, that there's
some intermediary that's getting involved.
So the degree in which the client actually
know about this might or may
not be directly visible to the application
programmer, but the middleware knows
what's going on.
When incoming requests arrive, the
activator actually
handles them, and it goes and it checks.
It looks up in its activation map or table
and
says hey, is there somebody here who's
already handling this thing?
If so I'll just route it to them.
Otherwise I'll have to go ahead and
activate the service execution context.
So that might involve forking a process,
or spawning a thread, or loading a
container.
There's a couple different ways to do this
type of thing.
The activator also can decide what the
granularity
is it wants to activate and passivate
things.
So it might for example, as is the case
with, with start service.
It might go ahead and launch the service
every time start service is called.
You call start service and it's probably
going to launch something on your behalf.
conversely, with things like bound
services, it'll launch it the first time,
and then a bunch of methods can be made
back and forth.
And as long as the client hasn't gone away
or as long as there's some
client that maintains a binding to the, to
the service, then the service will remain
running.
So there's this granularity issue.
Do you launch things on a per method call
basis,
do you do it on per binding, or
connections, basis?
And there's no one right answer.
It's just the pattern gives you different
tradeoffs between different
forces of fine grained versus coarse
grained launching of activities.
The activation table's actually what keeps
track
of all this stuff, it's implemented in
Android
as you'll see as a map, or several maps, a
couple of different hash maps.
And then finally we actually have the
service
itself, which is the thing that does the
work.
An android that really is something called
a service.
In other environments it could be a
function call, or a procedure call, or a
method call, or something that gets run in
response to an indication by a client.
So that's kind of a quick tour through the
pattern.
Let's talk a little bit about the
consequences.
What we're going to do here is come back
later,
next class and talk about the
implementation details of this.
And I'll kind of neck down into how
Android implements some of these things.
So for right now let us talk about the
consequences.
So there's some good things about
activator.
It utilizes resources more effectively.
From the point of view of not allocating
stuff that isn't
actually being accessed by a client at
that particular point in time.
So your, you're launching things on demand
rather
than having to pre-spawn and keep them
around.
Another thing you get from this is sort of
a coarse grain concurrency,
so your launching processes your launching
threads and those guys are able to run.
And if you've got a multicore machine, if
you got an operating system and middleware
that supports concurrency and, and
parallelism, then you're
actually running those things at the same
time.
But it's a fairly coarse-grained approach,
it's typically not at the finer
level granularity of thread, it's usually
typically more at the level of processes.
And of course, the minute you start
building your system out of
pieces that are more service-oriented,
more
modular, then certain things get easier.
Testing becomes easier, because maybe you
can test these things in isolation.
You can also, perhaps, be able to reuse
stuff.
It's easier to understand because you're
not building
a gigantic system, with lots of pieces
that
are all wound together, like a big ball of
mud or a big ball of spaghetti.
But instead, their more modularized.
So this allows you to think about things
in isolation.
So those are some of the benefits.
There are some down sides.
One of the down sides is the
fact that the system becomes somewhat less
deterministic.
So sort of, when stuff starts to run,
depending on the order in which clients
make requests.
So your system may not always have the
same resource utilization, sometimes it
may take more memory, sometimes it may
take less, depends on the load.
So that's why certain kinds of real-time
systems tend
not to use activator because they don't
want nondeterminism.
They want to know what's the worst case
execution time.
What's the worst case utilization of
memory, so we can
pre-allocate those resources and make sure
that we always have enough.
Whereas some systems say, you know, if we
get
a big Bertha load, it'll slow down for a
while
till the load gets done, and then we'll
kind
of back out and, and go back to normal
processing.
Some other tricky things, because you're
spawning
things dynamically, there's potentially
issues for security.
If you're not careful, someone might slip
in a trojan
horse, so that when something gets spawned
dynamically, rather than spawning
the official version of a service, it
might actually end
up spawning some other sort of, malicious
version of the service.
It might be a trojan horse, it might have
some malware
or some other bad behavior, and that's
just a little easier.
The more dynamism you give into your
system, the easier it becomes for people
to slip in, trojan horses and back
doors, without people really noticing
what's going on.
The other thing, of course, is when you
start spawning things dynamically,
you often don't know what your system's
going to do until it runs.
And there may be some subtleties about
interactions between different services.
That will cause problems if they happen to
get
spawned in a particular order at a
particular time.
So this is the, the feature interaction
effect problem, and so things may work
fine when you test them in isolation in
the lab, but when you combine
them altogether in to the final integrated
system, and you start spawning them and
they're coming up and going down and so
on, you may have some surprises.
There's all kinds of subtleties that go in
there.
And of course the other issue is the
whole issue of, just, there's more stuff
going on.
You've gotta have this extra, activator
thing that sits around,
you have to configure it somehow, you have
to manage it.
You have to know how to use it.
And so, people have to learn a few more
pieces of the puzzle.
And so it's not always as easy just
starting a service manually.
You may have to register it will some type
kind of daemon
or some kind of manager that keeps track
of this stuff for you.
So there's a number of interesting known
uses.
One of the earlier known uses of
this particular pattern is something that,
system administrators
are well versed in these days, but end
users are typically not really aware of.
And it's something called INetd, which is
often referred to as the internet super
server.
The internet super server provides two
different kinds of services.
One different kind of service is internal
services that
are linked in statically when the system
starts, like on
a, on a server that's an INetd server, the
echo service and the daytime service are
typically internal services.
Then there's also external services.
Services that can be dynamically forked
and exact, or created on demand.
So things like HTTP demons are typically
forked on demand.
Eh, FTP, Telnet, they're secure,
SSH-equivalent
versions of these kinds of things.
These are processes that are spawned
on-demand, by the super server.
It listens on all these ports, and, and
spawns them, when requests come in.
So that's often called, a port manager, or
a port listener, or a super server.
You can take a look here, at this link for
more information about Inetd.
It's very cool capability.
Another feature, that, another thing, is
something that's called the CORBA
Implementation Repository.
And so this is a very cool feature
that makes it possible to write
application code.
Where the client has no earthly idea where
the
service actually run, all it knows is it
gets
an object reference, which is basically a
URL on
steroids, and it evokes an operation on
that object reference.
And that ends up going and talking to this
thing
called an implementation repository, which
is basically a super server.
And that guy keeps track of everybody
who's registered.
Using a, an activation table.
And it checks to see whether or not
there's a
server running to handle this, and if not
it starts it.
And then the server passes back an
address, which is called
an object reference, which is, again, like
a URL on steroids.
And that gets back to the client and its
cached away internal to the client.
And the call is actually redirected so it
ends up going
over to the actual server, the one that
was launched on demand.
That does it's thing and then sends the
result back.
Any subsequent call to that service is
directly routed
to the server without going through the
implementation repository.
So CORBA has this really cool mechanism
that optimizes
things so that the first time you use it.
It figures out where the correct
implementation resides.
Launching it if necessary, and then
redirects
the client, henceforth to go there without
having to make a trip through the
service, the implementation or repository
each time.
And then of course the last piece of the
puzzle that we already talked about.
Is Android's activity manager service.
So, as you can see here, that works by
bind service, which goes ahead and checks
out the
service map that's run internal, which
we'll look at
next time, and it starts the service by
calling process.start.
Getting all the information it needs to
load itself.
It starts up, loads in the various,
components it needs and the
entry point and so on to it's activity,
and, it, or it's service.
And away it goes.
The life cycle methods get called back
etcetera, etcetera.
And then the calls you make get dispatched
as appropriate, there.
So to summarize activator it basically
allows you to free
the clients from the responsibility of
activating the resources themselves.
They don't have to worry about that.
They just, say bind service, or they just
make a call and everything happens under
the hood.
And it makes it look to them as if the
resources were always available.
Now, how many people here have taken the
Operating Systems course here?
Okay, so, so a few of you.
So do you remember the concept of virtual
memory?
That we talked about, hopefully you talked
about
Operating Systems course, depends who
taught it of course.
But, depending on who taught it,
you hopefully learned something about
virtual memory.
So virtual memory is this concept that
says, I'm going to give the
processor an address, and I'm going to
pretend
like there's a really large address space.
Think about how big the address spaces are
today with 64-bit processors, right?
They're huge.
But I'm actually not going to have that
much
main memory, even though there's a lot of
memory you
could have nowadays, I'm not actually
going to have, you
know, whatever, 2 to the 64 minus 1 memory
ranges.
I might have eight gigabytes or something
like that.
So, what you're doing is the, as
the processor runs, it takes a virtual
address.
And it translates that into a physical
address,
and through a bunch of low level hardware
magic, it goes and it checks to see
if that particular address is currently in
physical memory.
And if it is, you, you run out of the
memory, you're fine.
I mean, you run in that memory.
If it's not there, then what happens?
There's a fancy name for something that
happens when, when you look
for something in, in the virtual memory
system, and it's not found.
this, this is very depressing to think
about
what you didn't learn in the operating
systems course.
So what happens is you incur what's known
as a page fault.
And a page fault basically goes out to
secondary storage, like the
disk, or some special, you know, battery
backed up RAM, or whatever.
And it reads in, that page in memory,
stores it into
the main memory, fiddles around with the
page tables and then
it goes ahead and gives you back something
that is actually
that real place to run, and it's brought
it in on demand.
So, virtual memory is an example of the
activator pattern in a sense, it's, it's
a lower level more systems-y concept of,
basically, on-demand activation or, lazy,
acquisition of resources.
You only acquire something when you
actually need it, Back, way
back in the day, way back before we had
ATM cards.
And, overdraft protection and stuff like
that.
If you want, if you are a student at
college and you
wanted to get money, you would go to the
local student center, and
you would write them a check, and
invariably the check you were
writing was probably for an account that
didn't have enough money in it.
Back in those days, that was okay because
it took a few days for the check to clear.
So what you would do is, this is the
activator pattern, the same idea.
You'd write a check, give it to the
student union.
They'd give you back, you know, 50 bucks
or whatever it was.
Then you'd rush back to your dorm and call
your folks, and you'd
say, deposit money in my account, you
know, in the next 24 hours.
And, and assuming that they were happy
with you and
your grades, they would deposit the money
in the, the account.
And wala, the check would clear,
everything was happy.
So that was a good example of doing things
on demand, right?
You didn't actually have money in your
account when you wrote the check.
But it gave you back the, you know,
you got something back that looked like
you had
the check, and by the time the check
actually cleared, the resources were there
to, to manage
it.
Activator also can be used to ensure that
activating and reactivating a
resource will incur minimal overhead,
which is,
is very important we, you, you don't want
to, to
have to do a lot of work to reactivate
stuff.
So you might for example have the
activator, you know pre-cache state for
you.
Activators can do others things too,
depends on
how fancy and sophisticated you want to
make them.
Activators could actually take part in
some
kind of replicated, cluster or cache
management
system, or it could load balance, the
activator might actually do load balancing
for your.
So you would ask the activator start me
a service and the activator would look
around and
go, yeah, that guy over there, there's not
much
load over there, I'll redirect the request
over there.
And so, then you would get back something
that you would use but it
would actually be running on some lightly
and loaded resource in your particular
cluster.
So and you could also, you know,
preallocate
stuffs so that when things were
reactivated [SOUND] it
was ready to go and kept those things in a
cache and so on and so forth.
And so we take a look at the
pattern description, take a look at the
Android documentation.
And they talk a bit more about all those
various things.
Okay, any questions about the, the
activator pattern?
So you can see that pretty much everything
we've talked about so far
having to do with services, touched on
activator in one way or another, right.
So we talked about, we talked about the,
the
started service, that was activator, to
start it up.
We talked about the intense service.
Again, sort of activator, starting things
up.
When we talked about bound services,
activators being used
under the hood to start things up on
demand.
And you see that over and over again.
And that's basically because Android is
trying to be
cons, conservation oriented in its
utilization of resources, especially
memory.
And it's trying to do things, you know, as
it needs to, and
then get rid of those things so you don't
clog up the memory system.
[MUSIC]