[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]
What I'd like to do now is give you a
little bit
more detail about how the command
processor pattern is applied in Android.
And this is going to be somewhat a review,
but we're just going to look a little bit
more
in terms of the steps involved and kind of
map
this for the pattern on to what's an
Android.
And it'll also give you a chance to
see another visualization of how these
things work.
So the implementation steps, so step
number one is to define
an abstract class that will give you the
interface for passing commands.
In many environments you have some kind of
execute
method that you're going to use to do the
work.
And Android, it doesn't quite work that
way, but it's along those lines.
There's an intent and the intent is
parcelable, which
means you can turn it into something that
can
be sent across a network and reconstitute
on the
other, or across, the processes between
different processes on Android.
And then reconstitute it on the other
side.
We then have, the need to be able to add
state so you can pass, information, data,
along with the command.
In many cases that's used by sub-classing
from a command interface and
filling in a bunch of fields to do the
bidding of the sub-class.
In the context of Android it's a little
different, but it's along the same sort of
lines.
We have a bunch of operations to set data,
and get data, which work on URIs.
As well as be able to put extras, and get
extras to be able to work on other kinds
of, of data, strings, ints, bundles,
things like that.
We also then have to define and implement
the creator, the thing
that actually creates the stuff that we're
going to use with the commands.
So in our particular case, that's
typically done by an
activity where we might have some kind of
click handler.
Which when you click on it, it will go
ahead and make an intent.
Connect it either, implicitly, or
explicitly to some
kind of service, or other, or other
component.
And then you stuff the various extras into
the intent.
And then you call start service.
Which as we've seen, doesn't block.
We then have to define the context.
In this particular case, we'll just grab
the
context that we get from the Android
context, which
on the activity side of the world, gives
you operations to do a whole bunch of
things.
On the service side of the world, gives
you some other things.
You can do things like send broadcasts.
Or be able to register receivers for
broadcasts, start
activities, start services, and so on and
so forth.
Those are various things you can do in the
context.
And then the final thing, of course, is
to implement specific command
functionality in sub classes.
So in the context of, of our pattern,
implementation in Android, what that's
going to relate
to is inheriting from intense service and
then
filling in the on handle intent hook
method.
Which as you all know when it gets called
back, will be running in a separate thread
of control.
Here's another way to look at this stuff.
This is how this might be applied in the
context of your programming assignment.
So, we might have a, a download activity
process which has a download activity.
And we'll, let's assume we're using the
messenger variant of things here.
And we go ahead and send the service to
the Activity Manager service.
It starts up this particular thing, and
the intent service will then, unhandle
intent method.
We'll go ahead and grab that information
and then reply back to the messenger.
As you can see in this particular
case, the service connection portion is
not used.
So I'm going to go ahead and just zap that
from the picture here.
We'll talk about this just, in just a
second when we start talking
about, bounded services because they end
up actually using this kind of stuff.
Here's a little bit of the code, just to
illustrate this.
So you can see we go ahead and
create an intent, put some information
into the intent.
And here's the receiver.
We go ahead in this particular case, get
the bundle of extras out
of the intent, go ahead and look up the
URI, get that back.
And then we go ahead and, and get the
messenger, that was also bundled
in there, download the file, and then send
the message back to the client.
Okay, so that's basically the coverage of
the intent service.
Are there any questions about that stuff?
[MUSIC]
[BLANK_AUDIO]