[MUSIC]
So, we have one more pattern here.
I think we can probably cover this first
part
of this pattern in the next 15 minutes or
so.
And that'll leave for us for next time the
second half of this pattern we'll talk
about the implementation.
Artifacts of this pattern and will also
talk about a couple more patents.
And then we'll get ready to move on to
something new.
So what we're going to do now is we're
going to kind of take the proxy
and stretch it out a little bit and put
something in the middle.
And that something is called the broker.
The broker pattern is a pattern that
appeared in the
[UNKNOWN] one book, and then it's been
revised various times
along the way because the original
description needed to be
enhanced as people got better insight
about what brokers really were.
And so we learned a lot about what brokers
were over the years.
So the context for this is some kind of
system with.
Multiple objects that are potentially
remote, they may be remote, they may not
be remote, and these objects have to
interact with each other, synchronously or
asynchronously.
And in the case of Android, of course,
this would be over binder RPC.
The problems here is we don't want
application developers to
have to think about a number of accidental
and inherent complexities.
We'd like them to not have to worry about
these details to the extent possible.
We don't want them to have to think about
low level message passing, in other words
taking their native data types and
manually encoding
them linearizing them, doing all the
things proxy do.
They don't, they shouldn't have to worry
about that.
That's basically what proxy does by the
way.
But there's some other things we'd like
them not to worry about either.
We'd like them to have to not worry about
various types
of diversity or heterogeneity that pop up
In the underlying infrastructure.
They shouldn't have to worry that the
client side and the server side
are written in different programming
languages,
Java versus C++ versus prolog versus C.
We shouldn't require them to worry about
what operating systems
these platforms are, these applications,
clients and servers are running on.
They shouldn't have to worry about the
networking
protocols, the type of the hardware and so
on.
That should all be shielded
and encapsulated from application-level
concern.
We'd also like to try to shield them
as much as possible from other more
inherent complexities.
Things like partial failure, security
implications, maybe latency, other kinds
of
things that may be issues in a system
that's getting bigger.
We'd like to try to shield them as much as
possible.
You can't always shield people from these
things.
If the network gets cut by a backhoe, you
may just have an outage, right?
You just may not be a way to get around
it.
But often there's ways of taking
alternative paths or being able
to have replicas, or redundancy, or so on
built into the system.
And it shouldn't be the application
developer's job to think about this.
I've written a lot of stuff about this
topic over the years, and you can
take a look at those many, many sources of
information on my website about it.
So, what's the solution?
The solution is to basically separate out
the communication concerns
that are sort of in the infrastructure
from the application concerns.
And use a broker in order to kind of
mediate between those two roles.
The systems the infrastructure kind of
stuff and the application kind stuff.
Now, how is that done in the Android?
Well, you probably know by now it's done
by using the binder and the AIL mechanism.
So we implement a binder object, the
client's can't get to directly.
We get a proxy back to that via
the various means we've talked about using
on-service connected
and so on and that client proxy is
then used by clients, like activities, to
invoke operations.
And those operations then travel through
the system,
after first being converted into parcels
by the underlying.
A proxy, and they travel through the
binder framework and pop out the other
side
to the stub, where they're converted back
into data types and passed to an up-call.
And that up-call is what actually does the
real work to
do the logic that's defined by the service
binder implementor developer.
And then they can pass the results back if
it's a two way call.
So the key thing here is that the binder
is combining a bunch of things.
It's combining proxy, it's combining
broker,
it's combining activator, it's combining
adaptor.
It's about, you know, eight different
patterns, we're just talking about broker.
As we'll see later, broker is actually a
pattern language, it's just
a bunch of other things that come along
with it for the ride.
So, the intent of the broker pattern is to
try to connect clients with remote objects
in a way that allows broker to mediate
the interactions with the clients to the
remote objects.
Without requiring the client or server
developer, application developers, or
service developers
to have to know anything about how this
works underneath the hood.
So you would typically end up applying
this pattern if you want
to be able to support local or remote
communication in a consistent way.
You want to be able to make the handling
of various fault issues.
Shielded from the application developer.
We want to shield the application
developer from things like, memory
management,
connection management, data transfer,
synchronization, concurrency
control, so on and so forth.
I should probably list some of these thing
out.
Low, low, level system details
such as memory, management, data,
lets see connection management,
synchronization, and threading.
You know, you think about it, there's a
whole
pile of things that you gotta think about
if you
write all these pieces of code and you'd
like
to all be hidden from you as much as
possible.
Different implementations of brokers by
the way go to
different extents to hide you from some of
these things.
So here's basically the structure of this
pattern, and
I'm pulling this particular structure from
a couple different places.
I wasn't really happy with any one
description
of this stuff from the literature out
there.
So here's one I kind of came up with based
on a few things.
So basically you have a client, which is
like
an activity in Android, the guy making the
call.
You have some kind of infrastructure like
the binder RPC framework, which is broken
up
into requesters that send things and
dispatchers that
receive them and process them and upcall
them.
You then have DeMarshalers, De.
Marshalers, de-marshaling and marshaling.
And they do the serialization and
de-serialization.
That's what typically think of as being
the proxy.
And then you finally have the guy that
does the
real work, which is called a servant in
this particular context.
Sometimes people call these things
executors,
but we'll call them servants for now.
So those are the, the main components that
you would typically find in a broker.
And if you take a look at this paper it
gives you a flavor of this.
It uses slightly different names, but its
the basic idea.
Here's a picture that kind of illustrates
how all this stuff works.
A client, sorry a server registers an
object either through some kind of
configuration script, like a manifest
file,
or dynamically through some kind of API.
It says you know, here's an object that
needs to be accessed remotely.
That's what the starts out, so everybody
knows that exists.
Then a client is going to get back an
object reference or some kind of service
identifier to this object and it's
going to
go ahead and invoke an operation on it.
Via a proxy and it'll call this on the
requestor.
The requestor will set up a connection if
it doesn't exist already, do
the marshalling, send the data over the
data goes over via the broker.
The broker might or might not be a
separate process or separate thread.
These might be libraries that are linked
together,
there might be some intermediate, mediator
that's separate
from the client process and the receiver
process
really depends on a lot of different
things.
Scalability, fault tolerance, memory
utilization, battery power.
All kinds of different considerations come
into play.
The dispatcher takes the request,
basically works with the
demarshaller part to crack open the data,
extract out
the message fields, turn them into data
types, and
then make an up call back to the object.
The object does its work, the method on
the
object does its work, and then it sends a
response
back, which goes back by the inverse path
of
how it got there, in the first place, most
typically.
So those are essentially the dynamic steps
with the broker.
This obviously maps very nicely onto
what's going on in
the context of Android for a whole bunch
of different reasons.
And we'll talk about those next time, when
we
talk about implementing this pattern in
the context of Android.
We'll look at the steps and interactions.
There's a whole bunch of different
consequences
of using this particular pattern a bunch
of
good things, location and dependence, you
don't
really know or care where the objects
reside.
They might be in your address space, they
might be some place
else, as Nolan was talking about, so that
gives you more flexibility.
There's a clear separation of
concerns, the infrastructure, the broker
implementations.
Doing all this heavy lifting for you, so
you don't have to worry about
it in your application, unless there's a
bug in the broker but that's another
story.
And if you make changes to the
implementations,
the clients typically shouldn't be
effected by that.
And then there's also a whole part of
other benefits.
If you implement brokers using standards
like CORBA for example,
or other technologies in that space like
SOAP and so on.
Then what you'll end up with are ways of
being
able to get portability, you'll be able to
get modularity.
You get portability because you'll have
common interfaces, you're standardized to
open specifications.
You will get modularity because you can
break your
system up into pieces and you can test
them individually.
You get reusability because you can reuse
both the broker infrastructure, as well as
services you build on top of it and
objects you build on top of it.
And all of this stuff has many, many, many
patterns galore to make it all work.
There are some downsides.
For many years, especially in
performance-critical
environments, requirements, environments
where the wrong
answer delivered, the right answer
delivered
too late becomes the wrong answer.
Those kinds of mission-critical or
safety-critical environments.
People had a perception that brokers added
too much overhead relative to hand coated
solutions.
That has changed over the years, people
have
gotten really good at implementing very
high performance brokers.
But sometimes if you're in certain
environments, there may be too much
overhead.
Potential issues with reliability,
reliability is something that's very often
hard to define in a completely generic and
common way.
Because different applications have
different reliability needs that are often
not well served by a one size fits all
solution.
So if you're not careful, you might end up
compromising your reliability requirements
to use something that's defined off
the shelf by a broker and it might not
work as well as something you might hand
craft yourself.
Having said that, you know, it takes a
lot of work to hand craft these things
yourself.
And of course anytime you start having
layers
of stuff involved and many of the
different
components you quickly realize you got a
big
issue as far as you know, debugging and
testing.
The minute you got distribute anything or
concur
anything there's a lot more stuff running
around.
And you probably already seen that as
you're trying to debug your programs here.
If something goes wrong, you know, is it
because the
service didn't work right, is it because
the client work right.
Is the, you know, God help us if, if
Android's not working right.
You know, that might happen once in a blue
moon.
But you just have to be very thoughtful
about where things are going wrong.
There's a number of known uses of Broker.
Once again, the early days were the
procedural, procedure call base brokers,
DCE, ONC or some RPC, CORBA probably the
predominant example of a broker.
CORBA so much a broker, it brokers its
middle name.
it's the common object request broker
architecture, it's right there.
And the name and then of course nowadays
we get Android.
I want to talk briefly about this whole
issue of manually doing things, versus
automatically doing things.
And as I kind of alluded to before,
there's
always this paradigm shift that occurs in
any, any domain.
Any field as things that used to require
human expertise are gradually over taken
by automation.
I was just reading the other day that
apparently, it used to be the case
a couple of years ago that humans aided by
computers could beat computers at chess.
And now it's probably no longer the case.
Computers are so good at playing chess
that you don't need humans to help
them play a better job than a human
playing with a computer can do.
So I thought that was interesting you know
one
more thing humans aren't good at, right
compared to machines.
I would argue there's an awful lot of
things humans aren't as
good as machines are, but there was a time
when they were.
And whenever people tell me the, those
things and
by the way as you go through your
technology
career, you will see the following mean
pop up
over and over again as new stuff comes
along.
Cause at first it won't be that good and
people will proof it.
And over time it'll get better and better
and better.
So my favorite example of this phenomena
which
is really at the heart of the innovator's
dilemma.
The claimed Christians don't like talk
about is the famous story of John Henry.
Does anybody remember who John Henry was?
What was John Henry's like great feat?
>> He laid down railroad.
>> He was a railroad worker and his great
thing was he was a big strong guy.
And he could take like a sledge hammer or
an ax and he could
sort of single handedly chiseled through
massive
amounts of rock to make railroad tunnels.
And so there's a great story where John
Henry goes out and he
competes against the steam drill and in
those days, the technology wasn't very
good.
And so you know, they have this contest
they start, the steamed drilling and John
Henry starts.
You know, chopping away with his, with his
sledge
hammer and the steam drill keeps, you
know, breaking down.
And they have an army of technicians
running around trying to fix it.
It sounds a lot like software sometimes
and so
what happens, anybody know what happens in
the story.
Who wins?
John Henry wins, right?
He gets through that mountain first, but
what happens to John Henry?
>> He dies.
>> He dies, right?
So, there's a metaphor there that says
through superhuman
effort you can sometimes beat the machine
at certain points.
But it's often not worth it, right, you
may pay a big price for doing that.
So the, the real thing to do of course is
not to try to beat
machines, it's to write better machines,
right that's how you make it, make it big.
Be you know, wealthy, popular and famous.
Okay, so that's it for the lecture for
today.
What we'll do next time is finish off
Broker
implementation and we're also going to
talk about observer, cause that's
the last, I think that's maybe the last
big
pattern that we've been talking about in
all this stuff.
And then we'll be get ready to start
talking about content providers.
[MUSIC]