[MUSIC]
Okay, any questions about any of that
stuff?
So what I'll do next is talk about how
the pattern, the proxy pattern has applied
an android.
Some this is a recap so I'll go through it
quickly.
I just wanted to put it here for
completeness but I won't spend time on it.
So, in Android, they basically, you
know, implement this by automatically
generated code.
And, here are some of the implementation
considerations
you have to think about when you're using
proxy.
So one is, are the proxies automatically
generated like, like
a robotic assembly line, or are they
something that's hand crafted?
And they're trade offs for the most part,
people rely on auto generation now.
Another question is you can potentially
use a proxy
to cache certain information that is
stable or immutable.
Things that don't change, item potent as
they sometimes say.
If you get the same result if you call an
operation many times.
You can actually have the proxy cache that
information
locally so when you need it it's right
there.
You don't have to actually make a remote
call to the other side.
I kind of think of, any time I think of
cashing, I
think of hamburgers at a fast food
restaurant in a heat lamp, right?
So when someone comes in and says I want,
you know, a Big Mac.
You don't have to cook one.
You just reach back to the heat lamp and
the cache and say, here it is, it's right
there.
There's no need to go back and talk to the
cook.
You've got it in the cache.
So, for things that are stable, things
that are cooked frequently, things that
are worth being precooked, then a proxy
can give you access to that.
Another implementation consideration some
languages give you some
pretty cool support built into the
language for proxys.
C++ for example has this interesting
feature called delegation
operator or operator arrow, sometimes
called the smart pointer operator.
And basically what you can do with the
operator
is you can use it in such a way where.
You can invoke something, through a proxy
using operator
arrow that looks like it's actually making
a method call.
But in fact what the operator arrow is
doing is
it's basically intercepting the original
call, doing something else, and
then returning a result, and then the
compiler generates code
to redelegate that call to that object
returned to the proxy.
And there's lots of cool use cases of
this.
It's used in thread specific storage, it
can
be used by a variety of other techniques
for
being able to make proxies look like
pointer
access, thereby hiding the details from
the application developers.
So lets take a look at how you might
implement this particular pattern in the
context of Android.
So this is an Android example using Java.
We've seen this already, so I won't spend
a lot of time on it.
So you run your IDL compiler on your IDL
interface and you get stubs and proxies.
The stub is basically the thing that
you're going to inherit from,
and fill in the details to implement later
through extension through sub classing.
There are a bunch of helper methods that a
stub has things that are used
to register the stub object or the
binder object with the underlying binder
frame work.
There is also something that can be used
to convert a binder object
into a proxy so you get a proxy back when
you call that.
The proxy is something that's also
automatically generated, and
you can use this in order to be able to
indicate who the binder is that you want
to
talk to the binder option you want to talk
to.
And also has the code that marshalls and
demarshalls,
the parameters and sends them across the
other side.
The other side of course ends up being
call back on a method called on transact.
And that's the guy that does the inverse
operation from the proxy.
That's the guy that pulls all the various
pieces out
of the message, turns it back into
strongly-typed data types
and then passes it as an upcall to the
implementation
method that you define in your subclass of
the stub class.
So, we've talked about that stuff before
so I went through that quickly.
So, in a nut shell, android defines the
proxy pattern
and it implements the proxy pattern using
it's generated proxies.
It allows you to do various kinds of
remote method
implication using the broker mechanism
we're going to talk about later.
By using this mechanism there's no API
difference between
talking to something local and talking to
something remote.
There may actually be a semantic
difference
if you're talking to an object that
is co located it will wind up running in
the same thread as the caller.
Whereas if you're talking to an object
that's running remotely in another
process, that will
be running in a different address space
and that'll be running in a different
thread.
So there's some different, semantic
differences to
some extent in terms of where things run.
But from an API perspective they look the
same.
Yes?
>> So when you're writing a proxy, do you
assume that you know
where that resources that you're going to
be interacting with.
Like, do you write a proxy such that it's
going to always
be communicating with like, a remote, like
off you know what I mean?
>> Yep.
Great question.
So the question basically is does whoever
create the
proxy which could be a person or a
generator right?
Whoever makes the proxy what assumptions
should they
make about where the target object
actually resides.
And it turns out that there are actually
two answers to that question.
The naive approach makes everything just
go through the proxy
even if youre co located in the same
address space.
And I should say naive approach and or the
approach that want
to has, wants to have semantic consistency
of behavior even when colocation occurs.
So that's, in that case, you don't
differentiate.
The optimized approach, which potentially
is more intelligent, but may also
be semantically different with respect to
what thread contacts you run in.
In that case, what the, what the proxy
typically does,
is it takes a look when the call is made.
And it asks the question, is this object,
target object, in my address space or not?
If it's not in the same address space then
it goes ahead does
all the normal things and sends it own its
merry way using a broker.
If it is in the same address space, it
does a short circuit.
And it goes ahead and just makes a direct
call.
So you could imagine that would be way
faster than doing all this other overhead.
But it also requires, you know, a little
bit more checking to take place.
Yeah, that's a great question.
And of course the other benefit you get
with proxies are that you can
make some changes in the way in
which you've configured and deployed into
your system.
You partition your system into pieces and
screw them around through the processes
in the system without really changing the
way things are really designed and
implemented.
So what you're doing is you're differing
until deployment time where things preside
as opposed to having to prematurely commit
yourself to one deployment over another.
And that's another such a great
flexibility
if you want to build systems that
can be sort of auto scaled without
making radical changes to the underlying
implementation.
[MUSIC]