[MUSIC]
So we're going to start the next topic
which will be a
continuation of the activator pattern that
we started talking about last time.
Now we're going to talk more about the
implementation aspects of the activator.
And then we're going to spend some time
talking about some other patterns that
we've been discussing as we've been
covering
the various bound services, Proxy and
Broker.
So first let's talk about the second half
of activators.
So what we're going to do here is talk
about how the activator pattern can
be applied in the context of Android
or how Android apply is the activator
pattern.
As you may have remem, remembered from our
last discussion, the Activator pattern
participants and the structure maps very,
very nicely onto Android capabilities.
And, as we start talking about the
implementation
steps in the Activator pattern, once
again, it's
remarkable how many of these things map,
kind
of, one to one onto what Android does.
It's also kind of fun if you take a look
at the pattern description, you'll see
that there's a number of different design
alternatives that are described in the
implementation section.
And as we go through the implementation
part here,
I'll illustrate both the generality of the
implementation approaches, as
well as describe how Android addresses
those particular implementation
choices in the things it does that pertain
to activators.
So the first thing to note that you do
when you implement the pattern
is you figure out what the services are
and how do you identify them.
And you also figure out what the service
identifiers
are which are the ways you actually
identify the services.
So of course the idea is
to encapsulate units of self-contained
application behavior,
in the context of something called a
service, that's the generic concept that's
important.
In Android this is really easy because
services are things that
inherit from the service base class or
from the intent service class.
So services are real easy to figure out
in, in Android.
There's a one to one mapping between the
concepts, and the
pattern and some realization of those
concepts in the context of Android.
And if you take a look at this link, or
this path name, you can
find the code for services in Android,
which is kind of fun to look at.
The only real method that you have to
implement is the onBind method, which is
done
for you by the intent service, but
otherwise
you have to fill it in to return null.
And that's a way for it to
tell the difference between different
kinds of services.
There's also the question of service
identifiers.
Now, in conventional networked
applications that use the activator
pattern and we'll talk about a bunch of
those later.
Typically, you identify services via some
kind of identifier scheme like universal
resource identifier or universal resource
locator or an inoperable object reference.
Or a TCPIP host name or host address and a
port
number, those are classic ways
of identifying services in those
environments.
In the context of Android of course we
identify services via intents.
And there's a couple of different elements
in an intent
that are used by the Intents framework in
order to be
able to figure out which services are
being referenced, when we
go ahead and do a start service or a bind
service.
And some of those elements include things
like what's the name, which is optional.
You don't have to give it a name.
You can leave it up to the Android Intents
framework to
figure out which service matches based on
other things beside the name.
If you use the name then it's basically an
explicit intent, it's explicitly naming.
Says this thing goes with that particular
entity.
There's also other things like the action.
What's the action that's being used?
So is it some kind of action that relates
to, you know, viewing something, or
editing something, for example?
Or you know, is it a URL action, you
going to download something?
There's also the data that goes along with
the action.
This would be things like a URL, or some
other, URI, or
path name that identifies either a local,
or a remote piece of content.
So that's another thing that can go into
an intent,
to help identify which service is
responsible for processing the intent.
Yet another thing that can go into an
intent, is something called the category.
For example, there is a category for
launchers which are
things that get up on the basic
application launch screen.
There is other kinds of categories of
applications as well.
So, these are the kinds of things that are
actually
used by the underlying Android system in
the Activator framework.
The activity manager frame service, which
is the Activator part of Android.
In order to figure out, who gets launched,
what
service to run when something gets, gets
sent out.
You also then have to decide which
services
do you want to activate and deactivate on
demand.
And not every service that you might have
in your
system is worthy of being activated and
deactivated on demand.
So you have to kind of figure out a couple
things, you have to figure out
things like what's the overhead for being
able to activate something on demand or
not?
What's the downside to keeping something
running for a long time?
There are also, I think I should mention
this too.
There are also security implications.
[SOUND] So, some services are really
important,
and you want to make sure they're always
there.
You don't want people being able to
dynamically change them.
For example, I don't think it's the case,
that you can, dynamically activate
the radio portion of Android, the part
that does the actual phone management.
That's the sort of turned on by default
and
you don't activate and deactivate that you
could image
that would cause all kinds of problems
with probably
missed calls because things would take too
long to launch.
So you have to figure out what it is that
you want to be able to run dynamically,
and control dynamically.
Some of the services we're seen on Android
that do this, things like email media
playback services, services for sending
and receiving
various kinds of messages, short messages,
multimedia messages.
Alert services that get puh, going to pop
up when calendar
timers expire and elapse and you have to
alert someone
that something is about to happen so they
can go
make a call or join a meeting or something
like that.
So there, those are some of the services
that the Android
developers have deemed relevant to start
and stop in a dynamic way.
If you take a look at packages.
The packages apps directory you will find
lots more examples of bound and started
services there, and there is a bunch of
Android as well in the frameworks part.
The next thing you need to do is figure
out
what the service activation, and
deactivation strategies out to be.
And one of the keys considerations there
is what is
the context in which a service gets
executed, gets routed?
And there's a bunch of different choices.
If you are programing in lower level
operating system environments.
Things like the Linux, inetd or Unix
internet d, inetd that
we talked about briefly last time in the
super server model.
In that particular case, you're probably
going to have
a process be the unit of, of activation.
That's the service execution context.
You're going to launch a process when
something happens.
In other environments like if you're
running in some kind of
embedded system that doesn't have
processes, you might spawn a thread.
If you're running in the context of
something like Android, if you think about
what's
being launched here, which is basically a
service,
that's really not a process or a thread.
It's really more of a middleware-centric
container of sorts,
so it's an abstraction that it hosts some
application logic.
And actually it can run in a process or
not, or it could
run in a thread, or not, but
it's basically a somewhat higher level
abstraction.
So you have to decide what the right level
of
granularity is, obviously Android does it
as a middleware container.
You also have to figure out how the
service
is going to register itself with the
activation framework.
Is it going to do it dynamically, by some
kind of API call like register service?
Is it going to do it more statically,
by defining various things in a manifest
file?
So that when things get started, the, the
system knows which, which place to launch,
and how to dynamically load the various
resources
in it and so on, those are decisions.
Android typically goes with a static text
file approach with the manifest file.
You also have to decide whether the
activation framework
is going to be responsible for
initializing the service or not.
And there's a couple of different cases
here.
If a service doesn't require any
initialization, it just starts.
Then obviously the framework doesn't have
a whole lot of work to do.
If the service requires a certain state.
Then it's up to the developer of the
activation framework, as
to whether the activation framework is
responsible for initializing the state.
Or whether the service that gets started
is responsible for initializing its own
state.
In Android, anything that's important,
gets done by the service.
It's not really done on a service basis by
the underlying middleware.
There's, also, another set of
considerations
about how do we deactivate services.
So, activating services is just half the
battle.
In the Activator model, once you activate
something, you
have to figure out how to shut it down.
Of course you could keep it running for an
indefinite period
of time, but to some extent, that would
defeat the purpose of
an activator, because you really want to
reserve, or preserve resources,
or conserve resources by shutting things
down when they're not being used.
And there's a couple of different
techniques you can use here.
You can have the service trigger the
deactivation.
The service can say I'm done, I'll shut
myself down.
That's kind of the way intent services
work.
You could have the client trigger things,
some
client can say service stop yourself,
that's another model.
And then you could also have things where
the activator decides to shut stuff down.
And that could be based on a variety of
different things.
Android supports all of these different
models in various degrees, right?
So with started services when the service
starts to run, it will
run indefinitely and it has to stop itself
by saying stop self or.
So that's that's the service trigger
deactivation model.
Or another component could say, service, I
want you
to stop yourself, so that's a client
triggered approach.
And of course the Android runtime system
might start
to notice that memory is getting low and
it may
say, hey, you know, you gotta, you gotta
shut
yourself down, so that's kind of the
activator trigger model.
With bound services, typically the way
things work is that multiple
clients can connect to the service and as
long as some
of them or one of them is available and
has a
binding open to that service, the service
will remain in memory.
We'll see some interesting, sort of hybrid
approaches
in a minute when I show you some
of the implementation code that appears in
Android,
how they deal with some of these issues.
It's kind of cool.
So you can take a look at the website,
there's a
link here that gives you more information
about service life cycle.
But, be aware that Android gives you all
the tools to do the different
kinds of deactivation strategies, and it's
up to you to figure out what to do.
The key thing you typically don't want to
do is not let the service
run indefinitely if nobody's using it
because
that, that would be overly consumptive of
resources.
Some other things you need to do.
Figure out how you're going to
interoperate between the activator
and the service execution context and the
service itself.
So, how do these things interact with each
other?
The key thing here is the interaction
between the service execution context.
Which is typically either a process or a
piece of middleware container.
And the service, which is the thing that's
doing
the business logic that is defined by the
end programmers.
So there's a couple of different
alternatives here.
One thing that you typically have to do is
come up with some way
for there to be call backs, either from
the execution context to the service.
Or from the service back to the execution
context to do various kinds of things.
Android supports both of these means of
course.
The most obvious set of ways these
interact is with the life cycle
call back hooks, that are dispatched
automatically by the Android run time
framework.
When a service starts, to call on create.
When intent shows up.
Via on start command, when you do the
various bind
service calls which trigger the onbind
method and so on.
So this is a bunch of callback hooks that
you can define and
those are interactions between the Android
container
infrastructure and your service and your
hooks.
And of course, your service can also make
call backs into
the Android container infrastructure to
ask it for various things as well.
But that interaction is something that's
very stylized and important to understand.
Then you also have to figure out how to
implement the activator.
Actually do the activation.
And in Android this is done by something
called the activity manager service.
Which you can take a look at, it's
very, very complicated, piece of code,
very large.
And it handles activation for lots
of things, activities, services, broadcast
receivers.
And so on, and so forth here.
It plays multiple roles.
Even though it's got the name, Activity
Manager Service, it manages other things,
besides activities.
There's a couple of issues to consider
here.
When you design the activator, do you want
to have a singleton activator or
a share activator that's use by all
the services running in infrastructure and
environment?
Do you want to have one that's exclusive
on a per service basis?
Do you want to have some kind of
distributer activator where you may have
some centralize node that's keeping track
who gets to run and where to run?
And so on and again there's no one right,
one, one size
fits all or one right solution to all of
these different design considerations.
The trick is to figure out what the
alternatives
are and make the choices that make sense
for you.
In Android they have essentially a
singleton or shared activator.
The activity manager service is the guy
that
is the role, the component in Android, the
service.
The super service, that activates other
things.
Another consideration here is what is the
degree of transparency with respect to
activation?
Is this something where the application
client has to make a special
call to get a service started, and then it
does other requests?
That's what's called explicit activation.
Or, is it something where you just make a
method
call and the underlying activation
framework activates the service
implicitly?
And without you having to think about it
directly and do something special.
So the way it works in Android which is
different from other pieces of middleware
by the way.
Is you have to do explicit activation.
You have to say start service or bind
service, and that triggers the service to
be started and then once that happens,
then you can send messages back and forth.
Now, you can also, to some extent, kind of
do
a little hybrid thing where you can pass
in an intent.
Or extras with the intent that goes along
with the original service, so there are a
few kind of things that, that straddle the
line between implicit and explicit.
But in technologies like Corva, we'll see
later there's much more support for
implicit activation.
You just make a method call and boom
something
magic happens under the hood to get the
job done.
So what I'd like to do now is take a tour
through a
piece of an interesting service in Android
that demonstrates the use of activator.
And I'm just going to look at a part of it
now.
Later, when we talk about the broker
pattern,
we're going to come back and look at the
full blown glory of this stuff, because
it's
really cool and it's got lots of
interesting interactions.
This implementation, by the way, actually
has a lot in common
with the download file stuff you're doing
that's the asynchronous version.
Because it relies on passing in
asynchronous callback objects using one
way
methods that will not block the caller
while things are taking place.
What this thing is, it's a network
settings activity.
And you can use it, if your phone supports
it, in
order to be able to find out what carrier
networks are available.
You know, so like you don't often see this
too much
when you're in the U.S. usually you're
with a single provider.
You know, your phone just starts up and
it's
running with Sprint or it's running with
AT&T or Verizon.
When you go overseas, however often times
you're roaming, and there
will be a range of different network
providers to choose from.
And so this particular network setting's
app, or activity allows
you to be able to see the networks that
are available.
And then you can, conceivably choose one
that you want to use.
So here's basically the way this works.
And, and by the way all the source code is
available.
You can take a look at that if you're
interested.
So they have this NetworkSettings
activity.
And it has an on create method and so when
you launch
this thing, it turns around and it makes a
call to start service.
And it invokes start service to go ahead
and launch the network query service.
And it, but it doesn't talk to that
directly,
of course, it talks to that activity
manager service.
And the activity manager service takes the
request and all
the other things and then it goes ahead
and then launches.
The process to run the network query
service if it's not already running.
So that's really the activator part right
there.
So it's activating it on demand.
And then what happens is there's an
opportunity
the service gets to initialize itself via
its on
create hooke method, it's lifecycle method
and it
goes ahead and goes what it needs to do.
And then what's interesting, and we're not
going to look at this in any detail right
now, but we'll come back and look at this
later when we talk about the broker.
The next thing that the activity does
after it
calls startService, is it turns around and
it calls bindService.
So, this is kind of an unusual model.
It calls startService followed by
bindService.
Which looks a little weird, right?
So far we've only looked at services that
called start service, which
are started services, or services that
called bind service, which are bound
services.
But this is an example of something that
does both.
And if you read the comments in the code,
it basically
says it does this so that when we call
start service.
The service will remain running
indefinitely.
So you'll want the service up and running
all the time.
And then we call bindService so we get
back a binder object and we
can interact with the service by using
asynchronous binder communication via one
way AIDL calls.
And we'll look at that in a little bit
more detail later.
But I thought that was kind of an
interesting example of
using startService to explicitly activate
something that will remain around and then
use bindService immediately after that, in
order to get back a
proxy that the client can use to invoke
methods on the service.
So it's sort of a hybrid approach.
But, the key point there is that it has
that it
has the examples of the activator that
launches the serves on demand.
Any questions about that?
So again, if you're curious take a look at
the source
query, it has a bunch of really cool
things going on there.
It registers uh,handler with the
underlying radio interface layer, which is
the part that actually keeps track of the
service, the, the
carriers and the network availability and
when things change the call
backs that get made in the service, it's,
it's really cool.
So look at that later.
Okay, so to go ahead and summarize this
particular
discussion, Android started and bound
services use the activator pattern.
And as you can see here, they, they use
the
stuff that, that pretty much straight out
of the book.
Looks just like what you'd see there.
These services can be run in different
execution contexts.
Most typically if you don't do anything to
the contrary, they end up
running into the same process as the
caller, which is typically an activity.
But without too much effort, you can tweak
the manifest file
to say, I want this thing to run on a
separate process.
So it can then be launched in a separate
execution context than the context that
was originally calling it.
And, if you want to be able to do threads,
and have
the service run in a thread, then you
could program that by
inheriting from IntentService or doing
something else not unlike what you guys
have done for your programming assignments
to implement multithreading on the service
side.
Okay, so that's basically activator.
You know, to recap what we talked about
last time, activator's a pattern.
That makes it possible to launch things on
demand, and
we talked about sort of the pros and cons
of that.
Then we just saw some examples in Android
where it gets used in order to work
with launching bound or started services
to do
various behavior processing on behalf of
the client applications.
[MUSIC]