Welcome to the next part of the class.
In this module, we're going to be
providing more information on patterns and
frameworks, to extend and augment material
that we'll be covering in this course.
If we went back 20 years ago or so and
taught this
class, we find that there was much less
material back in those days.
There were some early papers on patterns.
Peter Coad had published a paper in 1992.
Ralph Johnson had published a paper about
documenting frameworks with patterns in
1992, and of
course, the gang of four published their
first
collected paper on patterns in ECOOP in
1993.
Work on frameworks goes back a little
further.
If you went back about 25 years ago or so,
you'd see that there were
some papers by Ralph Johnson and Brian
Foote
talking about frameworks from the 1988
time frame.
And there was a lot of classic work done
by Taligent, which were some of the early
promoters and
evangelists for frameworks, talking about
the work they had
done developing frameworks for building
operating systems and user interfaces.
This module provides a tour through some
of the landscape
of literature that has appeared over the
past two decades.
Of course, the classic works in the field
we've covered in
depth, the Gang of Four book, and the POSA
One book.
There are also four other volumes of the
POSA series.
The Pattern Oriented Software Architecture
series.
And these books talk about many other
dimensions.
Many of which have a lot to do with
concurrent and network software.
For example, the POSA 2 book, which I was
the first
author on, talks about a patterned
language for concurrent network software.
And we will be talking about many of these
patterns throughout the course.
There's also a book called POSA 3, which
deals with a pattern language for resource
management.
Patterns for dealing with resources,
allocating
resources, deallocating resources, and so
on.
POSA 4 combines over a hundred patterns to
focus on a pattern language for
distributed computing.
And what makes this particularly
interesting is that the real
emphasis of the book is not on the
individual patterns and
isolation, which to some extent is the
focus of POSA
1, POSA 2 and POSA 3, and again, a four
book.
But, it really focuses more on the way in
which those patterns work together.
So, well over half the book is talking
about interactions
between patterns as opposed to talking
about the patterns by themselves.
POSA 5 provides a tour through the concept
space and the foundational themes
and ideas and abstractions underlying
patterns and pattern languages.
And it talks about relationships between
patterns, pattern complements,
pattern compounds, pattern sequences and,
of course, pattern languages.
They are other books that are very
important to get an architectural
view of patterns, and even though the
books don't have the words pattern
in the title, they still deal with many of
the same kinds of
abstractions that we've seen in other
books in the pattern body of work.
One of the best examples of this
particular type of book is
the book Software Architecture,
perspectives on
an Emerging Discipline, by Shaw and
Garlan.
And they talk about many of the
fundamental patterns
and architectural styles that exist in
build large-scale software systems.
There are also a number of other books
that talk about
various aspect of patterns that are worth
taking a look at.
The late John Vissides wrote an excellent
book called Pattern Hatching.
Which grew out of some columns he'd
written for
the C++ report magazine, while I was the
editor.
And many of these patterns either were
patterns that didn't make it
into the Gang of Four book because they
were incomplete at the
time, but he completed, or there are
additional patterns that he described
based on his experience applying the Gang
of Four Patterns in different contexts.
For example, the discussion about
destroying singletons was something that
came out after he wrote the Gang of Four
Patterns.
There's also a number of patterns
and other domains pertaining distributive
computing.
And Middleware is book on patterns for
programming J2EE.
There's patterns for enterprise
integration.
There's even patterns about component
middleware and patterns for
brokers and patterns for remoting that are
worth looking at.
There's also patterns for how to program
parallel and distributed systems.
Trying to take advantage of multi-core and
multi-processor hardware, effectively.
The pattern is that we're trying to build
systems that
will be resilient in the face of failures
and attacks.
And there's also patterns that deal with
how to write code that will be secure.
That will be able to operate, even when
you have adversaries that will try to
break in to your system and attack your
network, steal your data and so on.
One of the things that happened when I
first
got involved with patterns in the 1994
time frame
was we had a series of conferences called
pattern
languages of programming, and these
conferences would bring together
both experts and novices for several days
at Alcuin
Park in Illinois, where we would sit
together and
work on how to improve the way we were
documenting our designs and our
architectures and our software structures.
And from these conferences came a series
of books that collected
together, revised, and it edited versions
of the papers from these conferences.
That are now known as the Program Pattern
Languages of Program Design, PLoP D books.
And there are five of these in all.
And they give kind of a nice, kind of,
broad view of
the thinking of the pattern community from
1994 to about 2000 time frame.
There are some excellent books for people
who are trying to
build software that have to run in unusual
or constrained environments.
So-called small memory software, which is
often
the case for embedded systems which don't
have the luxury of gigabytes worth of
memory or high speed processors or
unlimited power.
And of course, one of the other classic
books in the field
of concurrency for patterns is Doug Lea's
book for concurrent programming in Java,
which talks about many of the different
ways of trying to devise
Java concurrent programs and many of the
patterns for effective use of Java.
You'll find that many of the ideas that
are
documented as patterns in Doug Lea's book
have found their
way into the Java class libraries for
concurrency, as
well as into frameworks we've talked about
such as Android.
If you take a look at the Hillside
website, which is
dedicated to all things patterns, you'll
find a more extensive list
of many of the books related to the
patterns, the community,
and, and work on patterns, and the body of
knowledge of patterns.
There are also a number of books on
frameworks.
One of the early contributions of
frameworks as I mentioned before
was from the Taligent Group, which was a
company that was building
frameworks to try to encapsulate low level
operating system details and provide
a higher level programming abstractions to
make it easier to build applications.
And there's a book called Inside Taligent,
by Cotter and Patel, that has a nice
chapter that describes the philosophy of
frameworks that
came with the approach that they were
doing.
There's also a series of books that were
published with
some colleagues of mine, relating to
building patterns and applying patterns
in the form of frameworks, having
frameworks applied in domain
specific ways, frameworks applied in more
generic ways and so on.
And you might want to take a look.
These are collections of papers from
people who had
experience either building or trying to
apply frameworks in practice.
Speaking of applying patterns and
frameworks in
practice, along the way over the past 20
years or so, I've also developed a
large number of frameworks, heavily driven
by patterns.
Many of those patterns were documented in
the POSA 2 book, but I've also published a
series of books that talk about the
application
of these patterns in the ACE framework
environment.
And so you might want to take a look at
some
of the books that describe the frameworks
that are used in ACE.
I mentioned before the pattern languages
of
programming conference, PLoP, which
started in 1994.
It's been ongoing for years, and, in fact,
it is now
generalized and grown beyond its initial
focus in the US, at
Alcuin Park to be an international
sequence of conferences that take
place in Germany, South America,
Scandinavia and other parts of the world.
The main benefit of going to a PLoP
conference
is it gives a chance for pattern authors
to get
feedback on the patterns that they're
writing down from
experts, in the form of something called a
writer's workshop.
A writer's workshop is a format derived
from the
poetry and writing community where you
have people sit around
in a circle, listen carefully to a
description of
the, of the pattern or the work that's
being discussed.
And then they take turns providing
feedback to the author, things that
worked, things that didn't work, things
they liked, things that could be improved.
And it could provides invaluable feedback
to people who are trying to
codify their design expertise and write it
down and disseminate in pattern form.
There's also a series of information about
pattern
conferences that's also found on the
Hillside website.
There's also a set of mailing lists if
you'd like to learn more about patterns.
There's mailing lists that talk about the
Gang of Four Patterns, the various
Siemens'
POSA patterns, patterns for interprocess
communication, patterns
for business and other types of topics.
If you take a look at the Hillside
website, you'll find a
way to subscribe to the mailing lists that
are of interest to you.
And, finally, I have also produced quite
an amount of information over the
years that I make available on patterns
and frameworks through my website at
Vanderbilt.
I have some information here that talks
about the books I've written, on patterns
and
frameworks, the presentations that I've
recorded in either
podcast or video form on patterns and
frameworks.
I've also taught many courses on patterns
and frameworks,
at the various universities I've been a
faculty member of.
All that material, the slides, the
assignment descriptions, and
the syllabi and so on, are all available
online.
And of course, I've not just talked about
patterns and frameworks; I've
also built, and helped build, millions of
lines of code, largely written
in C++, some written in Java, that
implement many of these patterns
in frameworks that you can download and
apply and use in your projects.
So take a look at my website, explore the
links, and feel free to use
this material in a way that you see fit to
make your projects more effective.