[MUSIC].
Welcome to the next part of the module on
Android concurrency frameworks.
Which begins the coverage of the AsyncTask
framework.
This part examines the structure and
functionality of the
AsyncTask Framework, and shows how Android
uses this framework
to access the call logs database
concurrently in a
background thread, to avoid blocking the
user interface thread.
The looper, handler, thread, message and
runnable classes in the
HaMer framework discussed in previous
videos, are relatively loosely connected.
Which is flexible and works well for
simple use cases.
Such as posting runnable commands from a
background
thread to run in the user interface
thread.
However, these loose connections also
require users of the HaMer framework to
understand the patterns that guide the
structure of, and interactions between,
it's classes.
Especially if they want to implement more
sophisticated concurrency models.
Such as pools of threads that take
advantage of multi courtship sets.
Likewise, application developers must
write and rewrite message types
and message handlers, which is tedious and
error prone.
Therefore, to provide a more cohesive,
usable and scalable
concurrency model to application
developers,
Android defines the AsyncTask Framework.
Which provides an integrated set of
classes that
execute long duration operations in one or
more background
threads, and publish their results to the
user interface
thread without explicitly manipulating
threads, handlers, messages or runnables.
Though the AsyncTask framework uses them
internally, along with
several other reusable Java concurrency
classes, such as FutureTask.
The classes in the AsyncTask Framework are
strongly connected.
Which simplifies it's usability by
reducing
the surface area of it's interface.
In particular, this framework exposes it's
capabilities
to application developers, by the
AsyncTask facade class.
Which provides a simplified interface to a
complicated
body of framework code, as described at
this link.
[MUSIC].
There are two main categories of methods
in the AsyncTask class, that
provides the facade for the AsyncTask
framework, as described at this link.
The first type are public methods that are
invoked by applications.
For example, the Execute Method runs a
task with a specified parameters.
Conversely, the Cancel Method attempts to
stop the execution of a task.
The second type of methods are protected
methods,
such as, OnPreExecute, doinBackground,
onProgressUpdate, onPostExecute, and
onCancel.
Which are hook methods invoked by the
AsyncTask framework at different points in
time, and
in different contexts, such as in the user
interface thread or one or more background
threads.
Framework users must extend AsyncTask
baseclass and
override one or more of its hook methods,
as shown by this example from the
threaded downloads application we'll
discuss in upcoming videos.
Execute can only be called once on an
instance
of AsyncTask by code running in the user
interface thread.
Execute is implemented as a template
method
described at this link, which collaborates
with other
parts of the AsyncTask framework to run
its
hook methods at the appropriate time and
context.
After Execute is called, the AsyncTask
framework invokes the onPreExecute hook
method in the user interface thread, which
can perform initialization activities.
Such as displaying a progress dialogue to
the user.
The framework next calls the,
doinBackground
hook method in a background thread,
where long duration operations can run
without blocking the user interface
thread.
As long as doinBackground is running, it
can call publish progress to
publish updates on the user interface
thread by the onProgressUpdate hook
method.
When doinBackground completes, it returns
a result, which the
framework delivers as a parameter to the
onPostExecute hook method.
Which can display the results of long
duration
computations in the context of the user
interface thread.
[MUSIC].
Now that we've shown the hook methods
invoked by the AsyncTask framework
during normal execution, we'll examine
what
it does when an AsyncTask is cancelled.
A call to cancel attempts to stop the
execution of an AsyncTask instance, which
will fail
if the task is already completed, already
been
cancelled, or could not be cancelled for
some reason.
After an application calls cancel.
The framework will invoke the on cancel
hook method
in the user interface thread after doing
background returns.
I also ensures that on post execute is
never invoked.
AsyncTask cancellation is a cooperative
process, so
the doinBackground method should
periodically check the value
return by the isCancelled method and
finish
as early as possible, if it's been
cancelled.
Similar to the methods for stopping
threads, discussed in an earlier video.
The asynctask class provides three generic
parameters used by its hook methods, to
identify the types sent to the task that
runs in the background thread.
The type of progress units published
during background computations, and the
type
of the result returned when doinBackground
finishes executing in a background thread.
An application instantiates these
parameters, extends
AsyncTask, and overrides any or all of
its hook methods as needed, to customize
their behavior, to meet its concurrency
needs.
As shown by this snippet of code derived
from the example at this link.
[MUSIC].
Now that we've shown the key methods in
the AsyncTask facade class.
We'll show an example of how Android
extends
and uses it in the Call Log Async class.
That's part of the Android phone
application, shown at this path name.
Several call log Async methods use
AsyncTask to access
the call logs database concurrently in a
background thread.
Which is necessary, since database
operations can
take a long time to run, depending
on the system's load, so they can't be
called in the user interface thread.
The CallLogAsync class is typically used
within
an activity, which creates a new
CallLogAsync object.
And populates a list of call arguments.
Such as the caller information, phone
number, and call time and duration.
These arguments are then passed to the
call log Async
Objects add call method, which creates and
executes addCall task.
Which is an anonymous instance of an
AsyncTask subclass that
concurrently saves this call information
in the call log database.
AddCall tasks doinBackground hook method
invokes the
static addCallmethod of a callLog calls
class.
Since doinBackground runs in a background
thread, it can safely block when the call
data is inserted into the call log's
content provider, as shown at this path
name.
After the call log data has been inserted
into the content provider, the
doinBackground method returns the
array of uniform resource identifiers that
were added to
the underlying SQLite database, shown at
this path name.
This array is passed as a parameter to the
onPostExecute hook method.
Which runs in the user interface thread
and performs a sanity
check, to ensure the call data was indeed
written to the database.
Call log async also uses an AsyncTask to
get the last outgoing call concurrently.
By creating and executing an anonymous
instance of getLastOutgoingCall task.
The doinBackground method of this
AsyncTask subclass runs
in a background thread and invokes a
blocking operation
to the underlying content provider and
SQLite database
to get the last outgoing call from the
database.
It's onPostExecute method passes the last
outgoing call number to the last outgoing
call hook method, which was registered as
a callback object by the activity earlier.
This example shows how Androids AsyncTask
framework makes it straightforward to
execute operations
currently in background threads, and
process
the results in the user interface thread.
[MUSIC].
In summary, AsyncTask provides a powerful
framework,
containing an integrated set of classes,
that
applications can use to execute long
duration
operations in one or more background
threads.
And publish their incremental and final
results to the user
interface thread, without explicitly
manipulating
threads, handlers, messages, or runnables.
AsyncTask embodies key characteristics of
frameworks, covered in this earlier video.
For example, it supports inversion of
control, by having the
framework involve its hook methods at
certain points and contexts.
It also supports domain-specific structure
and functionality.
Such as synchronized message cues and
thread pulls.
Finally, it provides semi-complete
portions
of applications, where the AsyncTask
base class must be subclassed before it
can be used.
Subclasses will override at least one
method,
doinBackground, which runs in a background
thread.
Performs long duration processing, and
returns results.
Subclasses also often override a second
method, onPostExecute.
Which can publish the result to the user
interface thread.
AsyncTask is used extensively in Android.
Especially in its applications, as shown
at these path names.
The onProgressUpdate method is not as
widely used
in Android as the other AsyncTask cook
methods.
Although there are some example usages, as
shown at these pathnames.
[MUSIC]