[BLANK_AUDIO].
Welcome to part two of the module on
the benefits and limitations of patterns
and frameworks.
In part one, we went through the benefits
and limitations of patterns.
In this part we're going to con, continue
our
discussion, focusing on the benefits and
limitations of frameworks.
There's a number of benefits of
frameworks.
One of the most important ones, which is a
nice
segue from our discussion of patterns, is
that frameworks help to
guide application developers through the
steps that are necessary to ensure the
successful creation and development of
software, by emphasizing design reuse.
And invariably, this design reuse is
captured
and characterized in the form of patterns.
For example, when we developed our
implementation
of real time CORBA, by that point,
myself and my design team was very
well-versed in the patterns for building
communication middleware.
And so when we went to build our
implementation, we used those patterns as
a guide to help us address key
common recurring themes, roles,
relationships, interactions and
conventions.
That we learned from other domains and
apply
them into the domain of real-time
communication middleware.
But reuse of design is not enough, as we
had
talked about before in the last part of
this module.
Reuse of design is crucial, it's
necessary, but it's not sufficient.
And the reason, of course, is it takes
too much work to reimplement those designs
by hand.
So one of the nice things that frameworks
do, is they go one step
further, and they provide a reusable
collection
of components that are integrated and work
together.
To provide a reusable architecture and
implementation for a family of related
applications.
So in other words, the frameworks actually
take the
patterns and other aspects of design and
other insights.
And they actually allow you to create
working software that leverages
prior investment, prior implementation
work,
prior optimization efforts, and so on.
Thereby helping to amortize the software
development costs.
So, of course, when we went to build our
real time
core middleware, we had the benefit of not
only the patterns.
But we also had the reification or the
instantiation of those patterns in the ACE
frameworks.
And so many parts of our middleware
was implemented using ACE, which provided
some of
the lower-level infrastructure components
for event handling, concurrency,
synchronization, service access and
control and so on.
And that was one of the reasons why we
were able
to produce such a high quality solution in
such a short time.
That was so portable and so optimized,
because we weren't starting from scratch.
Another very important benefit of
frameworks is the
ability to reuse the validation and
testing efforts.
What are the things that makes it hard to
build software?
It's not hard to build software.
It's hard to build software that's going
to be correct.
It's going to be portable.
It's going to be portable to different
operating environments.
Portable to different configurations of
the operating
systems, the network protocol stacks and
so on.
And then making sure that you've shaken
all the legs.
All the errors out of the error legs, and
gotten the problems out of the code.
Well, needless to say, this is a very
tedious and time-consuming set of quality
assurance operations.
And so, one of the great things about
frameworks is they help to
amortize the QA activity, the quality
assurance activity, the testing and the
validation.
And one of the things we've done
extensively in our work with frameworks is
we've
built automated regression tests
environments, such as
the one that's shown here on this slide.
Where we run our software, middleware,
frameworks, on
a whole variety of different test
platforms with different
operating systems, different compilers,
different configurations, turning on
threading,
turning off threading, and so on and so
forth.
And then having the ability to
automatically
determine, through testing, which of our
regression
tests are working, and which ones are
failing at any given point in time.
And of course, by displaying all of this
information in a nice
web accessible dashboard-like manner, it's
easy
for the development team to track this.
To make sure that if a problem
occurs, it's quickly identified, quickly
remediated, thereby allowing
the end users of the software the benefit
of all this automated or semi-automated
regression testing.
Once again, frameworks are invaluable if
you
build this kind of infrastructure, because
that
amortizes those tedious and error prone QA
processes and the effort required to do
them.
There are, however, a number of
limitations with frameworks.
And we have to be front and center about
this, so people don't get
fooled into thinking it's a magic panacea
to solve all the problems of software
development.
One of the key challenges with developing
and
applying frameworks is that many
application developers find
it difficult to use them, because they're
not
necessarily familiar with some of the
object-oriented language features.
Like, inheritance and dynamic binding, or
even in some cases parameterized types,
templates.
And, they may also, not be familiar with
some of the patterns that the frameworks
embody.
Which means that they've got an awful lot
of complex surface area to try to
navigate.
Another key challenge here, is that the
way in which you build frameworks.
Which is a process called scope,
commonality and variability analysis,
requires a
great degree of design expertise and
domain knowledge from the development
team.
And sometimes software developers,
especially those who have
a language-centered view of the world, may
be
very facile with C++ or Java, but they
may not be familiar with the issues of
multi-threading.
Or they may not be familiar with the
issues of real time processing
or dealing with partial failures, or
causal
ordering, or distributive deadlock and so
on.
And a good framework is by very nature
domain specific.
And that implies the people who build it
have a great degree of knowledge of the
domain.
Another challenge with frameworks along
these lines,
is that if you have the situation of
trying to implement and apply a framework
in
a non-object-oriented language, things can
get very complicated.
Because a lot of the things you would take
for granted
in a language like Java or C#, or python,
or C++.
In terms of abstractions like inheritance,
dynamic binding, parameterization and so
on,
are often missing or done in
a very different way in
non-object-oriented languages.
So there's going to be a lot more code
that you're going to have to write and
learn.
And the language itself won't always guide
you as cleanly to make
the right implementation and design
choices,
thereby making the results more complex.
It's just a very simple example of this.
This isn't really a complicated framework.
It's just an illustration of the use of
the strategy
pattern applied in the context of C for
the standard C
library function qsort, where you can
strategize the way in which
comparisons are done by passing in a
pointer to a function.
If we were programming this in STL or
Java,
it would be much easier to make this
solution type
safe, easier to understand and so on, once
you understood
the patterns of STL or the patterns of
generic programming.
When we do it in C, it's a little
bit lower level, it's a little more error
prone.
Accidental complexity can rise up and bite
you when you least expect it.
So it's not that you can't implement
and use frameworks written in non-object
oriented languages.
It's just that the surface area is much
more complex, and there's
a lot more dark corners and sharp edges
you have to contend with.
Let's say that you're not trying to build
a framework, you're just trying to apply
one.
Well, there's some limitations and
challenges here as well.
It's often a nontrivial task to figure out
how to
evaluate some framework you're considering
for use, in terms of its
applicability, it terms of its quality, in
terms of its
footprint, in terms of its cost, etc, for
a particular domain.
This takes a while, sometimes people don't
have funds to spend time
doing the trade study analyses to figure
out what's the right solution.
Even though, inevitably, there probably is
one somewhere.
Either in a closed or open source manner
they could apply to some other problem.
And that takes time.
Another potential problem, or limitation
with frameworks, is that their
use of so called inversion of control, can
make debugging somewhat tricky.
Inversion of control is one of the key
driving characteristics
of a framework, and what it typically
implies, as we've
talked about before, is registering some
kind of function, or
object, or component which gets called
back by the framework.
When something interesting happens that
the framework has detected.
And that's typically the way that
frameworks are organized, by inversion
of control, rather than self-directed
applications that are driven by callbacks.
Well, this is very powerful, but it also
means that when
something goes wrong, and you're stepping
through your code and debugger.
You'll often find long sequences of
backtraces that you know little or
nothing about, and may not even have the
source code to adequately debug.
Because the framework was written by
someone else, and they
own the main focus of control for most of
the application.
This takes a little getting used to.
It's one reason why open source techniques
can often be very appropriate because you
can actually dig down if you need to and
find out what's going on.
It's also a good place to use common tools
such as
valgrind that can be applied to detect
memory corruption in your software.
Sometimes, you'll have a mistake in your
code
that won't manifest itself until the
framework does something.
And then it looks like it's the
framework's
fault, but it's really because the objects
or
the functions or the data has got, have
gotten corrupted somehow from some other
application-level mistake.
This leads into one of the other
limitations with frameworks.
Even though I mentioned before that it's
possible to
do a lot of validation reuse, run
regression test
suites, be able to do various kinds of
validation
and verification in an automated way to
amortize those costs.
Sometimes, especially in a highly
parameterized framework, it's
very difficult to know that the framework
is
correct or not, because it only manifests
problems
when you instantiate the framework
components in particular ways.
And if you don't account for those
different
variabilities in the test suites that you
do,
there could be latent bugs, latent defects
lurking
in your framework code for a long time.
That only manifest themselves when some
unsuspecting application developer applies
thing in a way not anticipated by the
testing team.
This of course is just another variation
on the
old cliché that you can't test correctness
into a program.
Testing only finds the presence of bugs,
it doesn't prove the absence of bugs.
So this of course argues in favor of other
techniques, model
checking, static analysis, very thorough
regression test suites based on
automation.
The use of continuous integration
facilities, like cruise
control and other, other tools to automate
the testing.
It also argues in favor of the use of
test-driven development methods, where
you write your regression tests ahead of
time, prior to writing the software.
Many of these concepts are very popular in
the
agile world, but they apply to other
methodologies as well.
And another problem you often run into
with
frameworks is that performance can be
degraded, due to
the very complex internal structures and
many levels
of indirection that are often baked into
the framework.
This is not inherent, there are many
frameworks that have been
highly optimized for a wide variety of
demanding mission critical domains.
Distributed real time embedded systems,
cyberphysical systems and so on.
But if you're not careful, especially if
you
use languages that don't really force you
to
think carefully about all the optimization
considerations, you
could end up with a fair amount of
overhead.
That's one reason why people sometimes are
reluctant to use off-the-shelf
frameworks, off-the-shelf middleware for
these mode
mission critical real time embedded
systems.
Because they're afraid that the additional
overhead will prevent them from
being able to meet their end to end
quality of service requirements.
I've written a paper that you can take a
look at, at this
link, that talks in great detail about the
benefits and limitations of frameworks.
And provide pointers to other literature
and other
places you can find more information about
this topic.
So to summarize this particular discussion
of frameworks.
Key insight, key advice: don't blindly
apply frameworks, don't blindly apply
patterns.
The abstraction and indirection that they
provide, which are good, often,
can sometimes lead to increased
complexity, cost, confusion.
One reason why it's so important
to document your software frameworks using
patterns.
As a general rule of thumb, understanding
patterns can be very
effective to help learn how to better
develop and apply frameworks.
I've done this throughout my career.
This is a, this is a synergisttic process.
As you build more frameworks, as you build
more applications
with frameworks, you'll understand
patterns
better, you'll discover new patterns.
Those patterns can make you more effective
at being able to develop new frameworks.
A lot of the work that we've done over the
years with ACE
and the ACE orb or Dow
has involved applying frameworks, learning
the patterns.
Using the patterns and insights of
patterns to improve and
enhance and extend the frameworks, it's a
nice control feedback loop.
You can also view patterns as essentially
abstract descriptions
of frameworks, that enable broad reuse of
software architecture.
Architecture has a number of different
definitions,
one common one is it's basically
describing
the key components and their interactions,
their
structure and the control flow between the
components.
And patterns do a great job of being
able to identify and justify why those
interactions occur.
Likewise, frameworks can be viewed as
concrete realizations of patterns, or more
likely, pattern languages, that facilitate
direct reuse of detailed design and code.
So you can see why these two techniques
work together so effectively.
One gives you the abstraction reuse, the
other gives you the implementation reuse.
Apart they have, certainly have benefits.
Together, they're even more powerful.
It's also important to remember that
patterns and frameworks done right, is
even more challenging and complex than
trying to do good object-oriented design.
Good object-oriented design is something
that takes years to master.
Knowledge of patterns is crucial, but
knowing how to
discover and document common useful
patterns and how to
instantiate those patterns in the form of
efficient, portable,
extensible frameworks, is even more
difficult than doing designs.
So it should be no surprise that this is
something that takes study.
One reason why, hopefully, you're watching
this
course, so you can learn also to navigate
through the maze
of complexity to become a much more
effective developer.
[BLANK_AUDIO]