[MUSIC].
Welcome to the next part of the module on
Android concurrency frameworks.
Which analyzes a threaded downloads
application that implements several
concurrency models.
Using the Android HaMeR and AsyncTask
frameworks.
Earlier videos in this module examine key
classes in these frameworks and showed
examples
of how these frameworks are applied to
portions of Android applications and its
middleware.
While these examples illustrated
industrial strength
usage of HaMeR and AsyncTask in practice.
They don't really lend themselves to
comprehensive
dissection and experimentation in your
Android development environment.
Therefore, this part of the module
provides a detailed analysis
of the structure and functionality of the
threaded downloads application.
Focusing on how it concurrently retrieves
images from
remote servers, and displays them to the
user's screen.
This application demonstrates three
different
ways to download an image concurrently.
Posting and processing runnables, sending
and handling messages, and executing
AsyncTasks using the concurrency idioms
supported by the Android concurrency
frameworks.
The application prompts the user to enter
the URL for the desired image.
After entering the URL, the user
can initiate the download concurrently by
clicking
a button from the menu of buttons
configured via an XML based resource file.
A progress dialog is displayed while the
requested image is downloading.
After the download completes successfully,
the image is displayed on the screen.
The user can return to the default image
by selecting the reset image button.
The rest of this video and the next one
explore the implementation of
this application, whose source code and
metadata
is available on GitHub at this link.
So you might want to obtain it and follow
along.
[MUSIC].
Before describing the concurrency models
supported
by the Threaded Downloads application,
we'll
first analyze the overall structure and
functionality of the Threaded Downloads
project.
Each Android project contains three key
elements.
First and foremost it contains the Java
source code.
Second, it contains resources such as
bitmaps, user interface layout definitions
and internationalized
strings that provide additional files and
static content used by the Java code.
As described at this link.
And third, it contains an XML manifest
file.
Containing information that Android needs
to execute
the application, as described at this
link.
The Android manifest file for the threaded
downloads application contains several
pieces of essential information.
For example, it grants the application
permission to use internet.
It also indicates the application's main
activity, called
threaded downloads, and declares which
intents it handles.
The layout of the application is specified
by the contents of its main .xml resource
file, which dictates how the text view,
edit text, and buttons appear on the
screen.
This file also specifies which methods in
the
threaded downloads class are mapped to
which button clicks.
There are four buttons with labels run
runnable, run messages, run Async, and
reset image.
Clicking on these buttons triggers the
corresponding hook methods.
In the threaded downloads class, which
then downloads the
image requested by the user, via the
associated concurrency model.
These button objects are connected to the
corresponding threaded
download methods, by the Android on-click
attributes, in the main.xml
file, which avoids hard coding the text
view, edit
text, or button objects into the threaded
downloads class itself.
[MUSIC].
The one and only activity in the Threaded
Downloads application is
the ThreadedDownloads class, specified in
the Android manifest file shown earlier.
This class extends the Android Activity
base
class and contains several data members
used by
the concurrency models to determine which
URL to
download and how to interact with a user.
In particular, its data members indicate
which URL to
use by default, where to store the URL
requested
by the user, where to store the downloaded
image
and how to display the progress of the
download.
ThreadedDownloads on create hook method,
sets the
content view specified in the main.xml
file.
And then caches references to the edit
text and
image view objects in data members to
optimize subsequent access.
All the concurrency models share the
download
image method, which runs in background
threads and
can thus block without incurring an
application
not responding dialogue from the user
interface thread.
Download image connects to a remote
server, downloads
the contents in the image, and provides
access to
it by an input stream using the get
content
method of the URL class described in this
link.
The bitmap factory's decode stream method
described at this link then
converts the image stream into a bitmap
object described at this link.
Download image returns the bitmap object
if decode stream succeeds.
If the download fails, however, a warning
is
displayed to the user via a toast message.
Which automatically disappears after a
short time out, as described at this link.
Although download failures occur in
background threads.
The toast must be displayed in the user
interface thread.
Download image, therefore creates a
runnable command and
calls the activities run on UI thread
method.
Which uses the HaMeR framework to post
this command to the user
interface thread via an internal handler,
as shown in this earlier video.
The runnables run hook method then uses a
toast to inform the user
that something has gone wrong with the
download, so they may try again.
[MUSIC].
In summary, the Threaded Downloads
application
displays images retrieved from remote
servers.
Using three different concurrency models
based on
the Android HaMeR and AsyncTask
concurrency frameworks.
This video analyzed the overall structure
and functionality of the Threaded
Downloads project, outlining key elements
in
its Android manifest and resource files.
As well as explaining several key data
members
and methods in the Threaded Downloads
class itself.
A simple use of the HaMeR framework was
shown.
Which posted a runnable command containing
a toast message
to display in the user interface thread
when downloads fail.
Other methods in the class use additional
Android
HaMeR and AsyncTask framework capabilities
to download the
requested images via several concurrency
models, which we
analyze in the next video in this module.
[MUSIC]