Welcome to the next module of the course.
In this module we'll talk about some of
the benefits and limitations of patterns
and frameworks.
We'll start by focusing on the benefits
and limitations of patterns.
It would be great if I could tell you that
using patterns will make all your software
development problems magically disappear.
But of course that's not the case.
However, there are a number of benefits
that patterns provide to the soft
development process.
And let's start by summarizing those.
One of the key things that patterns help
with is to capture and
abstract recurring software roles and
relationships
to facilitate systematic reuse of
successful designs.
I had my first major experience with this
benefit back in the early 90s.
I'd been developing software components
and frameworks for networking
concurrent systems, and I'd developed a
framework called the reactor.
Which essentially allowed you to abstract
away from low
level synchronous event demultiplexing
functions like select or pull.
And provide a more object oriented
extensible and easy to use framework,
where you'd register event handlers that
would get called back when events
occurred.
And had been detected by these low level
operating system mechanisms.
I've wrote several papers, one of which
you can read at the URL below.
And had a fair amount of experience
developing this particular
way of handling events in a, in a network
system.
When I would go out and explain this to
people
however, they would always get wrapped up
in the implementation details.
We'd be talking about using arrays, or
file descriptor sets, or linked lists,
and so on, and we'd often miss the more
fundamental design abstractions.
When I became a reviewer for the Gang of
Four book and learned about patterns,
I suddenly realized that I could recast my
reactor framework in the form of a
pattern.
Thereby helping to more effectively reuse
the key roles and relationships
that were endemic for many different
realizations of this particular approach.
And so from there the reactor pattern
description was born.
You can find a description of this pattern
at the URL below.
And of course it also appears in various
books such as the POSA 2 book.
The key benefit of looking at things from
a design
pattern perspective was that it helped us
to be able
to de-emphasize the unessential
implementation details, and focus more on
the key abstractions that application
developers would use to shield themselves.
From the low level details of event
de-multiplexing mechanisms provided by the
operating system.
Patterns also help to record engineering
trade offs and to be able to
systematically evaluate design
alternatives, to thereby
enhance development and sustainment of
software systems.
Towards the end of the 90s, I got
my first real experience with these
benefits of patterns.
At the time we were developing an open
source implementation of
real time CORBA, called The ACE ORB or TAO
for short.
And we were confronted with some design
trade offs.
Having to do with the way in which we
would
structure the underlying concurrency
mechanisms
for our real time CORBA implementation.
And by that point I was pretty well versed
in, in patterns but I'd been looking at
them primarily in terms of design
abstractions and what
we were confronting here was of course
about design.
But it was also about performance.
Predictability, quality of service,
avoiding various hazards
of real time programming such as priority
inversion.
And so we took it upon ourselves to look
carefully at some of the
design patterns available at the time to
determine which of them would most
appropriate.
To structure the tradeoffs between
different implementation and
design approaches for our implementation
of real-time CORBA.
The two alternatives that we ended up
settling on were known as the
Half-Sync/Half-Async model of concurrency
which is
based not surprisingly on the
Half-Sync/Half-Async pattern.
We'll talk more about this pattern later.
But in a nutshell, this pattern basically
makes
it possible to separate your software into
several layers.
One of which waits for events, in a single
thread.
And then passes through a synchronized
queue up to
a pool of threads that can process the
events concurrently.
And the benefit of this particular
approach is it's very scalable.
The downside is tends to incur some
overhead
for context switching, synchronization,
data movement and so on.
The alternative approach is based on
something called the leader followers
pattern.
And this pattern allows a pool of threads
to take turns waiting on an event to
multiplexer.
For activity to occur.
And when activity occurs, the leader
thread is responsible for handling the
data
associated with that activity while one of
the follower threads becomes the new
leader.
The benefit of this particular approach to
concurrency is that
it makes the predictability much higher
and it reduces context switching.
Synchronization and data movement
overhead.
The downside is that it's harder
to implement certain queuing mechanisms
because
of the way in which the pattern structures
the various roles and relationships.
What we did ultimately for our particular
use was choose the
leader followers pattern, because the real
time predictability and performance was
paramount.
For the sponsors we were working with.
But the key point here was we were able to
use patterns as a way to systematically
evaluate the trade offs
between alternative approaches and be able
to document them in a
way that could be usable not just to build
the software.
But also, to serve as a guide
for future sustainment and evolution by
other developers
who might not have remembered the original
reasons why we made the decisions we did.
There's a paper here at this URL that you
can take a
look at, that provides more information
about these tradeoffs between the two
patterns.
Another benefit of patterns is that they
help to improve a shared design vocabulary
between
members of the team, thereby making it
easier to understand the architecture and
the design.
Make it easier to do engineering and
re-engineering efforts.
Make it easier for the team to
communicate, because they have a
common way of expressing the key
design abstractions in their particular
design space.
I learned this lesson many times
throughout my career.
When we were building our implementation
of, of real time CORBA.
There were lots of other implementations
of
CORBA we were competing with at the time.
And many of those implementations were
built by teams of developers who had
a lot more experience than myself, my grad
students and my research staff.
But because we had based our solution on a
family of patterns.
And we had documents, papers, books,
annotated source code that captured those
patterns clearly, and we had frameworks
like ACE that embodied those patterns.
It made it possible for us to
develop very efficient, very portable,
very predictable middleware.
Much more rapidly and at much less cost,
thereby allowing us to compete with other
groups
that didn't have the benefit of a pattern
oriented software approach to what we were
doing.
If you take a look at this URL you'll find
many other papers that document our
experiences using patterns to convey the
design of our software to other people.
Another benefit of patterns is they
provide a basis for automation.
In earlier sessions, we've talked about
the proxy
pattern, and how the proxy pattern is a
great
example of a recurring theme throughout
the history
of software development and programming
languages, and computer science.
Where conventions and patterns at one
phase that prove useful,
later become automated in order to be able
to provide built
in language features and tools, that do a
lot of the
work more efficiently than having to write
all the code manually.
Certainly this is one example of how
patterns provide the basis for automation.
There are also other examples that are
becoming popular as well.
Examples based on paradigms based on model
driven engineering,
which use so called domain specific
modeling languages to capture
key structures and behaviors in a domain
specific way
using tools that can then perform various
kinds of analysis.
And synthesis of code, without requiring
the application
developers to have to write all that code
manually.
Now obviously not all patterns lend
themselves to automation.
But for those that do, and for those
paradigms,
like model drive engineering that support
such an automation.
It's a very powerful technique to improve
productivity and reduce many of the
tedious
and error prone software defects and
errors
that occur when writing code by hand.
There's an article I wrote a number or
years
of ago that describes model driven
engineering and places it
in the context of middleware and computer
aided software engineering
and patterns that you might want to take a
look at.
For, for more information on this topic.
Another benefit that patterns provide is
they help us to transcend biases that
often arise when people are overly wedded
to a particular programming language.
If you've got a bunch of software
developers together for any length of
time.
One of the most interesting and
controversial topics
you can bring up is their favorite
programming language.
Just as people around the world debate
ad nauseum their favorite basketball
player or
the greatest football or soccer player of
all time, or the greatest guitarist or
singer.
So too, do people like to debate their
favorite programming languages.
And that's all great when it's in good
fun.
But often times you find people who get so
wrapped up
in the details of the programming language
and the features of
the language and certain ways in which
they can express certain
concepts and design intent through a
particular set of syntax and semantics.
That they lose sight of the bigger
architectural issues.
And this is where patterns come in so
handy.
Because patterns often help us to
emphasize
what's really important, which are those
recurring roles
and relationships at the design phase,
which can
often be implemented in many different
programming languages.
And with many different implementation
techniques.
For many different purposes.
But focusing on the design helps
us transcend language-centric bias and
myopia.
The other main benefit of patterns is they
help to abstract
away from non-essential implementation
details at the right point in time.
For example, in the design phase.
It's not always the case that you have to
be
overly concerned with what operating
system platform you're going to run on.
Or, whether you're going to use an array
versus a linked list
to implement some of the internal data
structures of a reactor.
Those are decisions you can defer 'til
later on in detailed design.
Or in the implementation phase.
Or even during maintenance and
sustainment,
if you architect your system properly.
And the nice thing about patterns is they
help to separate concerns.
They help to focus on design as design.
Be able to communicate more effectively,
so people can think more clearly about
how their software needs to unfold without
being distracted by lots of issues.
That won't become necessary to consider
until further downstream.
There also of course, are limitations with
patterns.
One of the main limitations of patterns of
course, is that even though they help you
become a more effective architect and
designer, they
help you to communicate more effectively
with your team.
They may even make you more fun at
parties.
But they require human effort to
implement.
Patterns don't write the code.
Someone has to write the code that embody
those patterns.
And that can often be a Sisyphean effort
that is very tedious and error prone.
I remember many times, as we were
developing our middleware over the years.
We would apply certain patterns that we
had learned about in
the literature or we ourselves have
discovered and documented through previous
effort.
And even though we were very glad we had
the patterns
to guide us, inevitably there would come a
time when implementation, complexity.
Was the main challenge of our development
effort.
Remember when we were developing some of
our
middleware, using this leader followers
pattern, I mentioned before.
And, even though we understood the
pattern, as we started
to implement the pattern, in various kinds
of real time context.
Where we had to move information between
threads, running at different priorities.
There were some pretty nasty
implementation considerations.
And so, even though the patterns helped to
guide us,
we still had a lot of work ahead of us.
You might want to take a look at the URL
here to learn more about leader followers
and some of the
many different variations you have to be
considering when you
try to apply it in a range of different
application domains.
Another limitation with patterns is that
in
the wrong hands, patterns can be
deceptively simple.
In the right hands, of course, in the
hands of an expert.
In the hands of a senior architect.
Patterns are extremely helpful to separate
concerns.
To move key challenges and key solutions
at the
right point in the right phase of the
software lifecycle.
But in the hands on an amateur or
dilettante, these patterns can often lure
or lull people into thinking something
hard is actually easier than it really is.
Many times, I've been working on
projects for mission-critical, distributed
real-time, embedded systems.
And often, I'm surrounded by fantastic
architects and
developers who understand the proper use
of patterns.
Of course, as always, the pointy-haired
boss, who doesn't really
understand the complexities of software,
who hears part of the
story about how patterns can simplify
development, and who therefore
comes to the conclusion that we can simply
apply patterns.
Get rid of the need to have those
expensive A team members, and instead, use
junior developers,
or even worse, start trying to outsource
the development
to off the shelf technologies that are
very inexpensive.
That appear at face value to implement the
patterns but in fact, don't adequately
address many of the subtleties, many of
the quality of service considerations, and
so on.
So you have to be careful.
Just because you can say things like,
broker.
Or proxy, or publisher subscriber as a
design team doesn't necessarily qualify
you to
understand how to apply these techniques
effectively
for many of the more mission critical
environments.
Where the right answer that's delivered
too late becomes the wrong answer.
Another related challenge with patterns,
is that limited knowledge of patterns
can often constrain the design options of
an individual, or team.
Many times I've gone into projects as a
consultant where
the team took some patterns training,
several months or years ago.
And they probably learned about some of
the patterns in the,
the Gang of Four book, or maybe one of the
POSA books.
And they've been conscientiously applying
those patterns to their code.
And when I come along at some point for a
review, or some kind of analysis,
people will sometimes pull me aside and
say,
before we learned patterns, design was a
creative activity.
We could do all kinds of interesting
things.
We could solve the problems in the way
that made the most sense.
But since we started to study patterns, we
feel like
we're locked into a Procrustean bed of
very limited approaches.
And we keep seeming to apply, say, the
broker.
Or the proxy.
Or the adaptor.
Or the observer.
Or the reactor.
And, and those are the only things we seem
to
be able to do, and our ability to do more
creative solutions that really meet the
needs of our sponsors
and customers seem a lot harder than they
used to be.
Whenever I hear that, I, I sort of chuckle
to myself.
When I was growing up, in high school I
played soccer, what the rest of the world
calls football.
And I lived in the Washington DC area of
the United States.
And many of the people who I played soccer
with were my friends from all around the
world.
It was a very cosmopolitan place to grow
up.
People were there from Asia, they were
there from South America,
they were there from the Middle East, they
were there from Africa.
And, we all had a great time playing
together, as
15 to 16 year old boys, on the soccer
team.
What do you think happens when you get a
bunch of teenager boys together, who are
playing sports?
What do you learn to do?
Well, one of the first things we learned
to
do, we learned to swear in each others
languages.
So we could swear in Farsi, we could swear
in Hindi,
we could swear in French, and German, and
Spanish, and so on.
Did that mean that those languages were
only suitable for swearing?
Of course not.
It meant that we had an extremely limited
vocabulary
in which to express our thoughts in those
languages.
And the same thing is true of patterns.
If you only know some of the Gang of Four
patterns, or even if you know all of
the Gang of Four patterns, or even if you
know all of the POSA 2 patterns and that's
it.
You're going to find yourself limited when
you try to solve
larger problems because bigger problems
require
a broader range of solution approaches.
So don't blame the patterns.
Blame the lack of knowledge, lack of
breadth
and depth of knowledge, of the appropriate
patterns.
One of the other issues with patterns,
which is kind of ironic because it's a
flip side of one of the benefits,
is that sometimes patterns will neglect
essential implementation.
And especially optimization details.
So you might not adequately address those
things early enough in
the design to avoid programming yourself
into a corner later on.
Just as a simple example, when
implementing the reactor
pattern, which we documented in the early
to mid 90s.
Initially the types of synchronous event
demultiplexers that
were used were all so called level
triggered demultiplexers.
What that means is that as long as there
is data available,
the multiplexer will return immediately
saying there is work for you to do.
The select mechanism, the select function
works that way for example.
Later people began to add other kinds of
event
demultiplexer semantics into common
systems
that were so-called edge triggered.
Things like dev poll that occurs on some
versions of Unix.
Unfortunately the edge triggered approach
only
returns when some state transition occurs.
Which means you have to change some
aspects of your pattern interface and
certainly your pattern implementation in
order
to be able to reflect those differences.
So if you're not aware of these kinds of
things early and you over commit yourself
to a particular approach based on the
patterns
that you understand at a particular point
in time.
You can get burned, later down the road.
A similar issue arose that we discussed in
an earlier module with
the singleton pattern, which was
originally
designed without consideration for
concurrency and multi-threading.
And when those factors became important,
as
people began to use singleton in those
environments.
Some of the earlier details that have been
swept under the rug became very important.
And actually, somewhat limiting, without
further consideration.
You can take a look at this URL to find
out more information about edge
triggered versus level triggered event
demultiplexing.
Another limitation with patterns is that
not
all patterns are applicable to non-object
oriented languages.
We sometimes like to think that the
patterns are pretty interchangeable.
That if you understand patterns you can
apply them in Java, or C#, or C++.
And that's largely true, with some
exceptions.
But when you start trying to program in
other languages, languages
like C, or Fortran, or Ada, or Prolog,
much more different
from C++ or Java, you find that some of
the pattern
abstractions just don't really map, or
don't map in any sensible way.
For example, early versions of Ada don't
really
support the concepts of inheritance to
dynamic binding effectively.
So, common implementations of patterns
that rely on those
language features have to be radically
modified to use them.
Likewise, languages like Fortran and C
lack certain features.
Fortran doesn't really have the concept of
pointers.
C doesn't really have the concept of
destructors or the concepts of classes.
You can always mimic these things with the
languages using the mechanisms in a
building block way, but that can become
awfully complicated if you are not
careful.
Likewise, sometimes even when it is
possible to implement.
The patterns in different languages.
They don't get applied in exactly the same
way.
So for example, if you were implementing
iterator in
C++ you would undoubtedly implement it in
a different way
than if you were applying it in C or
even in Java where the abstractions tend
to be different.
It's the same pattern but the realization
is different.
This is not a showstopper, but it's
something to keep
in mind that your patterns don't always
apply blindly or directly.
So to summarize this section, the goal of
patterns is not to restrict
developer creativity, it's not to have
people applying things blindly and rotely.
In a rigid way by a set of design rules
that are not possible to be changed.
Nor is the purpose of patterns to try to
automate humans, it's not trying to
replace humans with tools.
Instead the real goal of patterns is to
try
to codify important insights and
experience that comes from humans.
Who have been there before, who have the
experience, who built software and
have had the good fortune of being able to
step back from their work.
Describe the key interactions, describe
the key roles
and relationships, describe the key
conventions in a way
that other people can learn from, as they
come
up to speed in what they're trying to do.
Another key important thing to remember
about this, is
that good patterns comes from
generalizing, from real experience.
It's very hard to create patterns without
that experience.
If you read a pattern written by
someone who doesn't really quite
understand the domain.
It usually sticks out like a sore thumb.
That's why we use writer workshop methods
when we help
people become better at communicating what
it is that they know.
So they get other eyeballs to look, and
other brains to help consider ways to
describe their
experience in a way that will be more
digestible,
and understandable by other programmers,
other developers, other architects.
Many of the software that I've developed,
and the, the patterns that
I've documented have come out of building
lots of real world systems.
Middleware, applications, and so on.
And if you take a look at this URL, you
can learn about some
of the early experiences we had, where
we gained knowledge of the effective
patterns.
That later led to the pattern
sequences and pattern languages we've been
discussing.
The final point here, is that addressing
these limitations
with patterns, often requires more than
just reuse of design.
Patterns are fantastic at reusing design.
But in a real world system, you often need
more than just design reuse, you need
reuse of code.