[MUSIC].
Welcome to the next part of the module on
Android
Concurrency Frameworks, which continues
our
analysis of the ThreadedDownloads
Application.
In this part, we'll show how to implement
three different
concurrency models using the Android
Hammer and ASYNC Tasks frameworks.
We'll start by analyzing the simplest of
the three concurrency models, which is
triggered when the user selects the Run
Runnable button on the user interface.
This selection initiates a call to the Run
Runnable
Method in the ThreadedDownloads class
shown at this path name.
This method uses the post Runnable
mechanism of
the Hammer framework described in this
earlier video.
The ThreadedDownloads application uses
this framework to retrieve
and display an image by starting a
Background thread,
downloading the image in that thread, and
then
posting a Runnable command to the user
interface Thread.
Instructing it to display the downloaded
image.
The RunRunnable Method called when a user
clicks the Run Runnable
button on the user interface, begins by
obtaining the requested URL
from the user's input, and then informing
the user that download
has begun via a process dialog, as shown
at this link.
Finally, this method creates and starts a
new thread to download the
requested image in the background, via
an anonymous instance of the
RunnableWithHandelers class.
This private class implements Runnable,
and its constructors
stores the requested URL in a data member.
Its run hook method executes in a
background Thread, and calls
the Download Image Method to retrieve the
image from the server.
If all goes well, the downloaded images is
displayed in the user interface Thread.
By posting an anonymous Runnable command
all the activities run on UI
Thread Method, which uses an internal
handler as shown in this earlier video.
The run hook method of this command,
dismisses
the progress dialogue and calls the
displayImage Method.
This method is shared by all three
concurrency models.
It shows the image on the screen, if the
download and conversion process succeeded.
[MUSIC].
We'll now analyze the second of the three
concurrency models, which is
triggered when the user selects the Run
Messages button on the user interface.
This selection initiates a call to the Run
Messages
Method in the ThreadedDownloads class,
shown at this path name.
This method uses the send message
mechanism of
the hammer framework, described in this
earlier video.
The Threaded downloads application uses
this framework to retrieve and display an
image by starting a background Thread,
downloading the image in that Thread.
And then sending several messages to a
Handler associated with the user
interface Thread, instructing it to
display
the downloaded image in that Thread.
This solution is more complicated, than
the Run Runnable implementation examined
previously.
Since it passes messages from a Background
Thread
to the User Interface Thread, via a
MessageHandler class.
Which extends Handler and defines three
types of messages, that the background
Thread can pass to the user
interface Thread, specifying which
processing to perform.
MessageHandler also contains a weak
reference, which enables it
to be garbage collected properly, as
described at this link.
Its constructor initializes this weak
reference, to
store a reference to the enclosing
activity.
The handleMessage hook method processes
the specified messages passed
to the message handler associated with the
user interface Thread.
These messages instruct the Handler to
start showing the progress dialog,
dismiss it, or display the designated
image via an image view object.
An instance of MessageHandler is defined
as a data member in the
ThreadedDownloads class, which passes a
reference
to itself to the MessageHandler's
constructor.
The runMessages Method, called when a user
clicks the Run Messages button on
the user interface, begins by obtaining
the requested URL from the users input.
It then creates and starts a new thread to
download the requested image
in the background, via an anonymous
instance of the Runnable with Messages
class.
This private class implements Runnable,
and its constructor
stores the requests URL in a data member.
Its Run hook Method executes in a
background
Thread, and uses the Hammer framework to
send
messages to the MessageHandler object
which processes them
in the context of the user interface
thread.
Run first or is a copy of the reference to
the MessageHandler, using the byte code
optimization described at this link.
It then creates and sends a message
instructing the
MessageHandler to start showing the
ProgressDialog to the user.
Next it calls the downloadImage Method, to
retrieve the image from the remote server.
If all goes well, a message is created and
sent
to the user interface Thread, instructing
it to dismiss the ProgressDialog.
Finally, a message is created and sent
instructing the
MessageHandler to display the image in the
user interface Thread.
[MUSIC].
We'll now analyze the third and final
concurrency model, which is triggered
when the user selects the Run Async button
on the user interface.
This selection initiates a call to the
runAsyncTask Method,
in the ThreadedDownloads class, shown at
this path name.
This method uses the Async task framework,
which executes
long duration operations in one or more
background threads,
and then gives the user interface Thread a
chance
to process the results as described in
these earlier videos.
The ThreadedDownloads application uses
this framework to retrieve and display an
image by calling the execute template
method on an AsyncTask object.
Which download the image in a Background
Thread that's managed internally by the
AsyncTask framework.
When the image has been downloaded, the
framework invokes a hook method
that displays the downloaded image in the
context of the user interface thread.
Compared with the Hammer based solutions,
especially
the second one that sends and handles
messages.
The Async task solution is easy to
program.
Since there's no need to manipulate
Threads, Messages, Runnables, or Handlers
explicitly.
Instead, the framework uses the Template
Method pattern to allow application
developers to customize hook messages
inherited from the Async Task base class.
The Run Async Task Method begins by
obtaining the requested URL, from the
users input.
It then creates and executes an anonymous
instance of the download task class.
Download task is a private class, that
extends AsyncTask.
Parameterizing it with a string for the
URL type,
and a bitmap that's used as the return
type
for the do in Background Hook Method, and
as
a parameter to the on post execute hook
method.
When the execute template method is called
on the download
task object, the AsyncTask framework
invokes its on pre-execute hook method.
Which starts showing the ProgressDialog in
the context of the
user interface Thread, before the task
starts executing in the background.
When on pre-execute returns, the framework
invokes the do in
background hook method in the context of a
Background Thread.
Do in background forwards the URL past
originally execute to the downloadImage
method, which retrieves the requested
image and returns it to the framework.
Finally, if all goes well, the framework
invokes the on post execute hook method
in the context of the user interface
Thread, passing the downloaded images to
parameter.
Outpost execute dismisses the
ProgressDialogue, and
displays the image to the user.
All the switching of contexts between the
user interface and
Background Threads, are handled seamlessly
and transparently by the AsychTask
framework.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC].
Now that we've analysed all three
concurrency models, implemented by the
threaded downloads application, we'll
compare and
contrast these solutions along several
dimensions.
Including usability for simple and
complex applications, scalability,
flexibility and efficiency.
AsyncTask provides a set of tightly
integrated classes, that
simplify the development of both simple
and complex concurrent applications.
Whose long duration operations run in one
or more background threads and publish the
results to the user interface thread
without
manipulating threads, handlers, messengers
or runables explicitly.
It also enables relatively transparent
scalability by it's thread pull executor.
However, although the AsyncTask framework
is scalable and easy to use
for both simple and complex concurrent
applications, it's not very flexible.
Since its only intended for interactions
between the User Interface
Thread and background Threads, but
not interactions between background
Threads alone.
Likewise, its internal framework
implementation is very sophisticated.
So it incurs a higher overhead, due to
it its many levels of indirection and the
synchronization,
content switching, and data movement costs
associated with
communicating between the threads, as
described at this link.
In contrast, posting runnables is
efficient and
easy to use, when knowledge of what
commands to run can be centralized at the
point where the post method is invoked.
However, this approach isn't very
flexible.
Since it's harder to parametrize or modify
commands once they've been posted.
Posting Runnable commands is also not very
scalable,
since programmers need to manually manage
the thread pools.
Conversely, sending messages is more
flexible
than posting commands, or executing
AsyncTasks.
Since client senders are decoupled from
Handler receivers.
For example, messages can contain data
that
the handlers used to process the messages
they
receive based on their type codes and
fields, as well as the Handler's runtime
context.
Likewise, senders and receivers can engage
in flexible
and efficient peer-to-peer conversations,
by passing messages back and
forth to each other between the user
interface
and background threads, as well as between
background threads.
However, sending messages is more
complicated to use than posting Runnable
commands, since developers must extend a
Handle message hook methods of Handlers.
And write explicit object to process the
messages they receive.
Likewise, thread pools must be managed
manually,
which makes this approach hard to scale.
Ultimately, the right choice concurrency
model for your application depends on your
requirements, and your understanding of
the
Android Concurrency frameworks and their
associated patterns.
[MUSIC].
In summary, the Threaded Downloads
application demonstrated how to implement
three concurrency models, using the
Android hammer, and AsyncTask frameworks.
The solution showed some things in common.
For example, all three used the background
Thread to
connect with the remote server and
download a file.
Which are long duration operations, that
shouldn't run in the user interface
Thread.
Likewise, all three solutions used the
user
interface Thread to perform short duration
operations.
Such as showing and dismissing
ProgressDialogs,
and displaying the image on the screen.
However, the solutions also have some
important differences.
For example, the background Threads, and
user interface
Thread in each model, communicate in
different ways.
The first two solutions are based on the
Hammer framework,
where application code in a background
Thread explicitly communicates to the
user interface Thread, by posting a
Runnable command or sending a
message object to a Handler associated
with the user interface Thread.
These handlers then process what they
receive, in the context
of the user interface Thread, as discussed
in earlier videos.
The third solution used the AsyncTask
framework, or application code
in a user interface Thread in Background
thread, implicitly communicates by
having the framework use synchronized cues
to pass message in
future test objects between the Threads,
also discussed in earlier videos.
Each concurrency model has the pros and
cons covered in this video.
So it's important to understand your
application requirements to make the right
choice.
Likewise it's important to understand the
gang of four and
POSA patterns, that under lie these
concurrency models and frameworks.
It's particularly important to recognize
the pattern
based structure interaction of the hammer
framework,
since knowledge of it's loosely connected
classes
alone, may not clearly articulate their
proper usage.
The key patterns underlie the Android
hammer and AsyncTask frameworks are
discussed further
in the next module, which also
examines these framework implementations
in more detail.
[MUSIC]