[MUSIC]
Welcome to the next part of the module on
Android
Concurrency Frameworks which completes our
coverage of the AsyncTask framework.
The previous video, discussed how Async
Task and bodies key characteristics of
frameworks.
Such as their support for inversion of
control.
The name specific structure of
functionality.
And semi-complete portions of
applications.
This part extends this earlier discussion,
by examining two common types
of frameworks, black box and white box,
described at this link.
It also demonstrates how AsyncTask
contains elements
of both black box and white box
frameworks.
The first type of framework, is the
black-box framework, where application
developers only need to understand, the
external interfaces of its classes.
Elements in black-box frameworks are
typically reused,
by paramaterizing or assembling, instances
of these classes.
The second type of framework is the
white-box framework, where
application developers must also
understand
some parts of the framework
implementation.
Elements and white-box frameworks expend
base
classes, and override their hook methods.
Black-box and white-box frameworks are
based on different types of patterns.
For example, black-box frameworks are
often developed
using patterns that emphasize
extensibility, via object composition.
Examples of these types of patterns
include strategy, or decorator.
Describe these lengths.
Likewise, white box frameworks are often
developed using patterns
that emphasize extensibility via
sub-classing,
and overriding of hook methods.
Examples of these types of patterns
include template method, or state.
Described at these links.
To make the discussions of black box, and
white box frame works concrete, we'll show
how Async
Task contains elements of both these types
of frameworks,
which helps application developers, extend
and customize it's capabilities.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We first examine the white box elements of
the Async Task framework, that
enable long duration operations to
interact
and communicate with the user interface
thread.
The Async Task base class, uses a template
method pattern.
To define the program skeleton of an
algorithm in its execute method, which
defers some
steps to sub-classes, in accordance with
the
white-box framework design principles, as
described this link.
After the execute template method is
called, the
AsyncTask framework dictates the
subsequently flow of control, and
evokes the on pre execute hook method, to
perform the initialization actions in the
user interface thread.
When this hook method returns, the
framework dispatches
the doInBackground hook method, which runs
in a
background thread, and can thus block
while performing
long duration operations, without
affecting the user interface thread.
When doInBackground finishes,.
Its results are returned by the on post
execute hook
method, which performs operations that
must run, in these interface thread.
Such as displaying an image to the screen.
Although the variant, the template method
pattern, used by the
Async Task framework, follows the
[UNKNOWN] structure of the pattern.
Which involves overriding hook methods.
It extends the pattern, by allowing hook
methods to run in different threads of
control.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
We now examine some black-box elements of
the AsynTask framework.
Which enable application developers, to
configure the number
and behaviour of threads that run in the
background.
And perform Async Tasks concurrently.
Async Task uses the strategy pattern, to
select its internal concurrency model at
runtime.
The default concurrency model, used by
Async Task, has changed over time.
As described in the discussion on, order
of execution, at this link.
In recent releases of Android, the default
behavior of Async Task is to use a
single background thread in each process,
to
run all due in background methods of
tasks.
Thereby avoiding common application
errors, caused by concurrent execution.
Async Task concurrency model, can be
configured by a several different executor
strategies.
The default behavior is implemented by a
serial executor strategy.
Which executes task, one at a time, in
sequential order, within a process.
Some applications however, benefit from
the ability to
run multiple AsyncTasks, within a process
and parallel.
For example, to take advantage of multi
core chipsets.
To support this use case, AsyncTask
incidents can be configured.
With a thread pool executor strategy,
which executes
multiple long duration tasks in parallel
within a process.
The AsyncTask framework, also supports
custom executors, which application
developers create,
by implementing the executor interface, to
define their own concurrency models.
The executor interface defines a strategy.
That enables runtime configuration of
concurrency models, that implement,
executor.
These strategies can be passed to an
AsyncTask, by its executor on executor
method.
Or, by calling its undocumented set
default executor method.
These executor strategies are treated as
black-box plug-ins by the AsyncTask
framework,
so there's no need to subclass AsyncTask,
to configure different concurrency models.
Regardless of which concurrency model is
configured,
the AsyncTask framework ensures that all
hook methods
are synchronized, in such a way, that
certain
operations are safe, without making
explicit synchronization calls.
In particular, member fields, can be set
in the constructor, or the on
pre execute hook method, and safely
referred to by the doInBackground hook
method.
Likewise, member fields set in
doInBackground, can be safely referred to,
by the on progress update and on post
execute hook methods.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
In summary, the Async Task framework
combines
black box and white box techniques and
patterns.
Which enables application developers to
easily extend and customize it's
capabilities.
In general.
White-box frameworks are easier to
develop, because their
design needn't anticipate a wide range of
use
cases, since that's the responsibility of
application developers,
that extend and customize their base
classes or interfaces.
They're also harder to use
however, because application developers
must understand
more framework implementation details,
such as which hook methods to override.
Conversely, black box frameworks are
harder to build, because their interfaces
and control flow, must anticipate a wider
range of use cases.
However, they're easier to configure and
use,
since they're customized by a self
contained plug-ins.
Which enable dynamic variation of
framework behavior.
Without extending or changing framework
code, as described at this link.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The AsyncTask framework applies several
Gang of Four patterns.
For example, it applies the template
method pattern, to implement its white-box
capabilities.
So users must subclass it, and then decide
which of is on pre execute,
doInBackground, on progress update, on
post execute,
and on cancel hook methods to override.
After an application running in the user
interface thread,
calls an Async Task execute template
method, the framework invokes
these hook methods at different points of
time, and
at different context, such as in the user
interface thread.
Or one or more background threats.
Likewise, Async Tasks applies the strategy
pattern to
implements black-box capabilities, which
enable applications to dynamically
configure,
predefined or custom executors, which
designates which concurrency model
to use when running Async Tasks within a
process.
It also applies the POSA2 Half-Sync
Half-Async pattern.
To guide the design of it's internal
concurrency structure and functionality.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[MUSIC]